<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
   schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
   <fileDesc>
       <titleStmt>
         <title><!-- ellenton --> Code of Ordinances</title>
         <editor xml:id="JHT">Jacqueline Hettel Tidwell</editor>
         <editor xml:id="E">Emily Grubert</editor>
         <respStmt xml:id="AG">
            <resp>Text markup</resp>
            <name>Anna Gardner</name>
         </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
         <distributor>SolarSMART - Social Responsibility CODEC Lab</distributor>
         <address>
            <addrLine>University of Georgia</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Park Hall</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Athens, GA 30602</addrLine>
         </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt><note><!-- Jacque to determine if we need or not. --></note></notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
         <p>Original code accessed at <!-- https://library.municode.com/ga/ellenton/codes/code_of_ordinances -->. Adopted <!-- January 17 2002 -->. Effective <!-- January 17 2002 -->.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
   </fileDesc>
   <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc><p><!-- Jacque to update with encoding description text. --></p></projectDesc>
   </encodingDesc>
   <profileDesc>
      <langUsage><language ident="en">English</language></langUsage>
      <textDesc n="code-of-ordinance">
         <channel>print</channel>
         <constitution type="single"/>
         <derivation type="original"/>
         <domain type="policy"/>
         <factuality type="fact"/>
         <interaction type="none"/>
         <preparedness type="formulaic"/>
         <purpose type="inform" degree="high"/>
      </textDesc>
   </profileDesc>
   <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-09-10" who="#JHT">Created header structure for template.</change>
      <change when="2019-10-14" who="#AMG">Added Municipal code and structured it.</change>
   </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <body>
        <div type="cover-info">
           <p>﻿THE CODE OF THE CITY OF ELLENTON, GEORGIA 
____________ 
Published 2013 by Order of the Mayor and City Council 
____________ 


OFFICIALS of the CITY OF ELLENTON, GEORGIA AT THE TIME OF THIS RECODIFICATION 
____________ 
Audie Perry, Sr. 
Mayor 
____________ 
James Perry, Jr. 
Brenda Castleberry 
Myrtice Bunn 
Donald Branch 
Joseph Burgess 
City Council 
____________ 
F. Marion Hay 
City Manager 
____________ 
William McCalley 
City Attorney 
____________ 
Darlene C. Hancock 
Clerk/Secretary 
PREFACE 
</p>
        </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <p>PREFACE This Code constitutes a recodification of the general and permanent ordinances of the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
Source materials used in the preparation of the Code were the Prior Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, as updated through the resolution adopted March 7, 2011, and ordinances subsequently adopted by the Mayor and City Council. The source of each section is included in the history note appearing in parentheses at the end thereof. The absence of such a note indicates that the section is new and was adopted for the first time with the adoption of the Code. By use of the comparative tables appearing in the back of this Code, the reader can locate any section of the Prior Code, as updated, and any subsequent ordinance included herein. 
The chapters of the Code have been conveniently arranged in alphabetical order, and the various sections within each chapter have been catchlined to facilitate usage. Notes which tie related sections of the Code together and which refer to relevant state law have been included. A table listing the state law citations and setting forth their location within the Code is included at the back of this Code. 
Chapter and Section Numbering System 
The chapter and section numbering system used in this Code is the same system used in many state and local government codes. Each section number consists of two parts separated by a dash. The figure before the dash refers to the chapter number, and the figure after the dash refers to the position of the section within the chapter. Thus, the second section of chapter 1 is numbered 1-2, and the first section of chapter 6 is 6-1. Under this system, each section is identified with its chapter, and at the same time new sections can be inserted in their proper place by using the decimal system for amendments. For example, if new material consisting of one section that would logically come between sections 6-1 and 6-2 is desired to be added, such new section would be numbered 6-1.5. New articles and new divisions may be included in the same way or, in the case of articles, may be placed at the end of the chapter embracing the subject, and, in the case of divisions, may be placed at the end of the article embracing the subject. The next successive number shall be assigned to the new article or division. New chapters may be included by using one of the reserved chapter numbers. Care should be taken that the alphabetical arrangement of chapters is maintained when including new chapters. 
Page Numbering System 
The page numbering system used in this Code is a prefix system. The letters to the left of the colon are an abbreviation which represents a certain portion of the volume. The number to the right of the colon represents the number of the page in that portion. In the case of a chapter of the Code, the number to the left of the colon indicates the number of the chapter. In the case of an appendix to the Code, the letter immediately to the left of the colon indicates the letter of the appendix. The following are typical parts of codes of ordinances, which may or may not appear in this Code at this time, and their corresponding prefixes: 

 
Indexes 
The indexes have been prepared with the greatest of care. Each particular item has been placed under several headings, some of which are couched in lay phraseology, others in legal terminology, and still others in language generally used by local government officials and employees. There are numerous cross references within the indexes themselves which stand as guideposts to direct the user to the particular item in which the user is interested. 
Looseleaf Supplements 
A special feature of this publication is the looseleaf system of binding and supplemental servicing of the publication. With this system, the publication will be kept up to date. Subsequent amendatory legislation will be properly edited, and the affected page or pages will be reprinted. These new pages will be distributed to holders of copies of the publication, with instructions for the manner of inserting the new pages and deleting the obsolete pages. 
Keeping this publication up to date at all times will depend largely upon the holder of the publication. As revised pages are received, it will then become the responsibility of the holder to have the amendments inserted according to the attached instructions. It is strongly recommended by the publisher that all such amendments be inserted immediately upon receipt to avoid misplacing them and, in addition, that all deleted pages be saved and filed for historical reference purposes. 
Acknowledgments 
This publication was under the direct supervision of Jim Jenkins, Senior Code Attorney, and Howard George, Editor, of the Municipal Code Corporation, Tallahassee, Florida. Credit is gratefully given to the other members of the publisher's staff for their sincere interest and able assistance throughout the project. 
The publisher is most grateful to Mr. F. Marion Hay, City Manager, for his cooperation and assistance during the progress of the work on this publication. It is hoped that his efforts and those of the publisher have resulted in a Code of Ordinances which will make the active law of the city readily accessible to all citizens and which will be a valuable tool in the day-to-day administration of the city's affairs. 
Copyright 
All editorial enhancements of this Code are copyrighted by Municipal Code Corporation and the City of Ellenton, Georgia. Editorial enhancements include, but are not limited to: organization; table of contents; section catchlines; prechapter section analyses; editor's notes; cross references; state law references; numbering system; code comparative table; state law reference table; and index. Such material may not be used or reproduced for commercial purposes without the express written consent of Municipal Code Corporation and the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
© Copyrighted material.  Municipal Code Corporation and the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 2013. 
ORDINANCE NO. 2013-1 
AN ORDINANCE ADOPTING AND ENACTING A NEW CODE FOR THE CODE OF THE CITY OF ELLENTON, GEORGIA; PROVIDING FOR THE REPEAL OF CERTAIN ORDINANCES NOT INCLUDED THEREIN; PROVIDING A PENALTY FOR THE VIOLATION THEREOF; PROVIDING FOR THE MANNER OF AMENDING SUCH CODE; AND PROVIDING WHEN SUCH CODE AND THIS ORDINANCE SHALL BECOME EFFECTIVE. 
BE IT ORDAINED BY THE MAYOR AND CITY COUNCIL: 
Section 1. The Code entitled "The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia," published by Municipal Code Corporation, consisting of Chapters 1 through 22, each inclusive is adopted. 
Section 2. All ordinances of a general and permanent nature enacted on or before March 7, 2011, and not included in the Code or recognized and continued in force by reference therein, are repealed. 
Section 3. The repeal provided for in section 2 hereof shall not be construed to revive any ordinance or part thereof that has been repealed by a subsequent ordinance that it repealed by this ordinance. 
Section 4. Unless another penalty is expressly provided, every person convicted of a violation of any provision of the Code or any ordinance, rule or regulation adopted or issued in pursuance thereof shall be punished by a fine not to exceed $1,000.00 and imprisonment in the City or County jail and work and labor on the streets or public works of the city, whether within or without the corporate limits, not to exceed twelve months or both a fine and sentence of imprisonment and labor. Each act of violation and each day upon which any such violation shall continue or occur shall constitute a separate offense. The penalty provided by this section, unless another penalty is expressly provided, shall apply to the amendment of any Code Section, whether or not such penalty is reenacted in the amendatory ordinance. In addition to the penalty prescribed above, the City may pursue other remedies such as abatement of nuisances, injunctive relief and revocation of licenses or permits. 
Section 5. Additions or amendments to the Code when passed in such form as to indicate the intention of the City to make the same part of the Code shall be deemed to be incorporated in the Code, so that reference to the Code includes the additions and amendments. 
Section 6. Ordinances adopted after March 7, 2011, that amend or refer to ordinances that have been codified in the Code shall be construed as if they amend or refer to like provisions of the Code. 
Section 7. This ordinance shall become effective upon adoption by the Mayor and City Council. 
Passed and adopted by the City Council this 11 th day of September, 2013. 

ATTEST: 


SUPPLEMENT HISTORY TABLE 
The table below allows users of this Code to quickly and accurately determine what ordinances have been considered for codification in each supplement. Ordinances that are of a general and permanent nature are codified in the Code and are considered "Included." Ordinances that are not of a general and permanent nature are not codified in the Code and are considered "Omitted." 
In addition, by adding to this table with each supplement, users of this Code of Ordinances will be able to gain a more complete picture of the Code's historical evolution. 

 
PART I - CHARTER[1] 
</p>
        </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <p>PART I - CHARTER[1]                   Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  Editor's note— Printed herein is the Charter of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, as enacted and set forth in 1975 Ga. Laws (Act No. 202), p. 3073. Amendments are indicated by parenthetical history notes following amended provisions. The absence of a history note indicates that the provision remains unchanged from the original. Any provisions regarding the title, enactment date, severability, repealer, transitional language, ratification date, publication date or effective date of the ordinance have been omitted. Obvious misspellings and punctuation errors have been corrected without notation. The style used for headings and catchlines has been made uniform and consistent with those appearing in the Code. The same system of capitalization and expression of numbers in text has been used as it appears in the Code of Ordinances. Additions made for clarity, such as consistent state statute citations and catchline modifications, are indicated by brackets. 
                  State Law reference— Home rule for municipalities, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ II; municipal Home Rule Act of 1965, O.C.G.A. § 36-35-1 et seq. 

                  ARTICLE I. - INCORPORATION AND POWERS 

                  Sec. 1.10. - Incorporation. 
                  This Act shall constitute the whole Charter of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, repealing and replacing the charter provided by an Act of the General Assembly approved August 13, 1910 (Ga. L. 1910, p. 703), as amended. The City of Ellenton, Georgia, in the County of Colquitt, and the inhabitants thereof, are hereby constituted and declared a body politic and corporate under the same name and style of Ellenton, Georgia, and by that name shall have perpetual succession, may sue and be sued, plead and be impleaded, in all the courts of law and equity, and in all actions whatsoever, and may have and use a common seal and change it at pleasure. 
                  Sec. 1.11. - Corporate boundaries. 
                  (a)  The boundaries of the City of Ellenton shall be those existing on the effective date of the adoption of this Charter with such alterations as may be made from time to time in the manner provided by law. The current boundaries of the City of Ellenton, at all times, shall be shown on a map, a written description or any combination thereof, to be retained permanently in the city hall and to be designated, as the case may be: "Map (or Description) of the Corporate Limits of the City of Ellenton, Georgia." Alterations in these boundaries shall be indicated by appropriate entries upon or additions to such map or description. Such entries or additions shall be made by and under the direction of the mayor. Photographic, typed, or other copies of such map or description certified by the mayor shall be admitted in evidence in all courts and shall have the same force and effect as with the original map or description. 
                  (b)  The city council may provide for the redrawing of any such map. A redrawn map shall supersede for all purposes the earlier map or maps which it is designated to replace. 
                  Sec. 1.12. - Specific powers. 
                  The corporate powers of the government of the City of Ellenton, to be exercised by the governing authority, shall include the following: 
                  (1)  To levy and to provide for the assessment, valuation, revaluation and collection of taxes on all property subject to taxation; 
                  (2)  To levy and to provide for the collection of license fees and taxes on privileges, occupations, trades and professions; to license and regulate such privileges, occupations, trades and professions; and to provide for the manner and method of payment of such licenses and taxes; 
                  (3)  To make appropriations for the support of the government of the city; to authorize the expenditure of money for any purposes authorized by this Charter and for any purpose for which a municipality is authorized by the laws of the State of Georgia; and to provide for the payment of expenses of the city; 
                  (4)  To appropriate and borrow money for the payment of debts of the city and to issue bonds to raise revenue for any project, program or venture authorized by this Charter or the laws of the State of Georgia; 
                  (5)  To acquire, dispose of and hold in trust or otherwise any real, personal or mixed property in fee simple or lesser interest inside or outside the property limits of the city; 
                  (6)  To accept or refuse gifts, donations, bequests or grants from any source for any purpose related to the powers and duties of the city and the general welfare of its citizens, on such terms and conditions as the donor or grantor may impose; 
                  (7)  To condemn property, inside or outside the corporate limits of the city, for present or future use and for any corporate purpose deemed necessary by the governing authority, under section 36-302 of the Code of Georgia, 1933, or under other applicable Public Acts as are or may be enacted; 
                  (8)  To acquire, lease, construct, operate, maintain, sell and dispose of public utilities, including, but not limited to, a system of waterworks, sewers and drains, sewage disposal, gas works, electric light plants, transportation facilities, public airports and any other public utility; to fix the taxes, charges, rates, fares, fees, assessments, regulations, penalties and withdrawal of service for refusal or failure to pay same; and to fix the manner in which such remedies shall be enforced; 
                  (9)  To grant franchises or make contracts for public utilities and public services not to exceed periods of 30 years; and to prescribe the rates, fares, regulations, standards and conditions of service applicable to the service to be provided by the franchise grantee or contractor insofar as not in conflict with such regulations of the Public Service Commission; 
                  (10)  To lay out, open, extend, widen, narrow, establish, change the grade of, abandon, close, construct, pave, curb, gutter, adorn with shade trees or otherwise improve, maintain, repair, clean, prevent erosion of and light roads, alleys and walkways within the corporate limits of the city; 
                  (11)  To grant franchises and rights-of-way throughout the streets and roads and over the bridges of the city for the use of public utilities; 
                  (12)  To provide for the acquisition, constructing, building, operation and maintenance of public ways, parks and playgrounds, recreational facilities, cemeteries, markets and market houses, public buildings, libraries, sewers, drains, sewerage treatment, airports, hospitals and charitable, cultural, educational, recreational, conservation, sport, curative, corrective, detentional, penal and medical institutions, agencies and facilities, and any other public improvements inside or outside the corporate limits of the city; and to regulate the use thereof, and for such purposes, property may be acquired by condemnation under section 36-202 of the Code of Georgia, 1933, or other applicable Public Acts, as are or may be enacted; 
                  (13)  To require real estate owners to repair and maintain in a safe condition the sidewalks adjoining their lots or lands; and to enact ordinances establishing the terms and conditions under which such repairs and maintenance shall be effected, including the penalties to be imposed for failure to do so; 
                  (14)  To regulate the erection and construction of buildings and all other structures; to adopt building, housing, plumbing, electrical, gas and heating and air conditioning codes; to regulate all housing, building and building trades; to license all building trades; and to license the construction and erection of buildings and all other structures; 
                  (15)  To provide for the prevention and punishment of riots and public disturbances; 
                  (16)  To regulate or prohibit junk dealers, pawn shops, the manufacture, sale or transportation of intoxicating liquors, the use and sale of firearms, the transportation, storage and use of combustible, explosive and inflammable materials, the use of lighting and heating equipment, and any other business or situation which may be dangerous to persons or property; 
                  (17)  To regulate and control by taxation or otherwise the conduct of peddlers, itinerant trades, theatrical performances, exhibitions and shows of any kind whatever; 
                  (18)  To license, tax, regulate or prohibit professional fortunetelling or palmistry; 
                  (19)  To prohibit or regulate and control the erection, removal and maintenance of signs, billboards, trees, shrubs, fences, buildings and any and all other structures or obstructions upon or adjacent to the rights-of-way of streets and roads or within view thereof, within or abutting the corporate limits of the city; and to prescribe penalties and punishment for violation of such ordinances; 
                  (20)  To prescribe standards of health and sanitation and to provide for the enforcement of such standards; 
                  (21)  To regulate the emission of smoke or other exhaust which pollutes the air and to prevent the pollution of natural streams which flow within the corporate limits of the city; 
                  (22)  To fix and establish fire limits and from time to time to extend, enlarge or restrict same; to prescribe fire safety regulations not inconsistent with general law, relating to both fire prevention and detection and to firefighting; and to prescribe penalties and punishment for violation thereof; 
                  (23)  To provide for the destruction and removal of any building or other structure which may or might become dangerous or detrimental to the public; 
                  (24)  To provide for the collection and disposal of garbage, rubbish and refuse; to regulate the collection and disposal of garbage, rubbish and refuse by others; to provide for the separate collection of glass, tin, aluminum, cardboard, paper and other recyclable materials; and to provide for the sale of such items; 
                  (25)  To levy, fix, assess and collect a garbage, refuse and trash collection and disposal and other sanitary service tax, or fee for such services as may be necessary in the operation of the city from all individuals, firms and corporations residing in or doing business therein and benefiting from such services; to enforce the payment of such charges, taxes or fees; and to provide for the manner and method of collecting such service charges and for enforcing payment of same; 
                  (26)  To charge, impose and collect a sewer connection fee or fees and to charge the same from time to time, such fees to be levied on the users connecting with the sewerage system; 
                  (27)  To define, regulate and prohibit any act, practice, conduct or use of property which is detrimental, or likely to be detrimental, to the health, sanitation, cleanliness, welfare and safety of the inhabitants of the city; and to provide for the enforcement of such standards; 
                  (28)  To define a nuisance and provide for its abatement whether on public or private property; 
                  (29)  To provide for the preservation and protection of property and equipment of the city and the administration and use of same by the public; and to prescribe penalties and punishment for violations thereof; 
                  (30)  To establish minimum standards for and to regulate building construction and repair, electrical wiring and equipment, gas installation and equipment, plumbing and housing, for the health, sanitation, cleanliness, welfare, and safety of inhabitants of the city; and to provide for the enforcement of such standards; 
                  (31)  To provide that persons given jail sentences in the municipal court may work out such sentence in any public works or on the streets, roads, drains and squares in the city; or to provide for commitment of such persons to any county work camp or jail by agreement with the appropriate county officials; 
                  (32)  To adopt ordinances and regulations for the prevention of loitering, disorderly conduct and disturbing the peace in the corporate limits of the City of Ellenton; to prohibit the playing of lotteries therein; and to prohibit or regulate by ordinance such other conduct and activities within the city which, while not constituting offenses against the laws of this state, are deemed by the governing authority to be detrimental and offensive to the peace and good order of the City of Ellenton or to the welfare of the citizens thereof; 
                  (33)  To regulate and license, or prohibit the keeping or running at large of animals and fowl; to provide for the impoundment of same if in violation of any ordinance; to provide for their disposition by sale, gift or humane destruction when not redeemed as provided by ordinance; and to provide punishment for violation of ordinance enacted hereunder; 
                  (34)  To regulate the operation of motor vehicles and exercise control over all traffic, including parking, upon or across the streets, roads, alleys and walkways of the city; 
                  (35)  To regulate and license vehicles operated for hire in the city; to limit the number of such vehicles; to require the operators thereof to be licensed; to require public liability insurance on such vehicles in the amounts to be prescribed by ordinance; and to regulate and rent parking spaces in public ways for the use of such vehicles; 
                  (36)  To provide and maintain a system of pensions and retirement for officers and employees of the city; 
                  (37)  To levy and provide for the collection of special assessments to cover the costs of any public improvements; 
                  (38)  To enter into contracts and agreements with other governmental entities and with private persons, firms and corporations providing for services to be furnished and payments to be made therefor; 
                  (39)  To create, alter or abolish departments, boards, offices, commissions and agencies of the city and to confer upon such agencies the necessary and appropriate authority for carrying out all powers conferred upon or delegated to same; 
                  (40)  To make, ordain and establish such bylaws, ordinances, rules and regulations as shall appear necessary for the security, welfare, convenience and interest of the city and the inhabitants thereof and for preserving the health, peace, order and good government of the city; 
                  (41)  To provide penalties for violations of any ordinance adopted pursuant to the authority of this Charter and the laws of the State of Georgia; 
                  (42)  To exercise the power of arrest through duly appointed policemen; 
                  (43)  To establish procedures for determining and proclaiming that an emergency situation exists within or without the city and to make and carry out all reasonable provisions deemed necessary to deal with or meet such an emergency for the protection, safety, health or well-being of the citizens of the city; 
                  (44)  To exercise and enjoy all other powers, functions, rights, privileges and immunities necessary or desirable to promote or protect the safety, health, peace, security, good order, comfort, convenience or general welfare of the city and its inhabitants; to exercise all implied powers necessary to carry into execution all powers granted in this Charter as fully and completely as if such powers were fully enumerated herein; and to exercise all powers now or in the future authorized to be exercised by other municipal governments under other laws of the State of Georgia. No enumeration of particular powers in this Charter shall be held to be exclusive of others nor restrictive of general words and phrases granting power, but shall be held to be an addition to such powers unless expressly prohibited to municipalities under the Constitution or applicable laws of the State of Georgia. 
                  Sec. 1.13. - General powers. 
                  In addition to all other powers herein granted, the city shall be vested with any and all powers which municipal corporations are or may hereafter be authorized or required to exercise under the Constitution and laws of the State of Georgia, as fully and completely as though such powers were specifically enumerated herein, and any and all powers which the city was heretofore authorized to exercise upon the effective date of this Charter. 
                  Sec. 1.14. - Construction. 
                  The powers of the city shall be construed liberally and in favor of the city. The specific mention or failure to mention particular powers in this Charter shall not be construed as limiting in any way the general power of the city as stated in this Charter. It is the intention hereof to grant the city full power and right to exercise all governmental authority necessary for the effective operation and conduct of the city and all of its affairs. 
                  Sec. 1.15. - Exercise of powers. 
                  All powers, functions, rights, privileges and immunities of the city, its officers, agencies or employees shall be carried into execution as provided by this Charter. If this Charter makes no provision, such powers, functions, rights, privileges and immunities shall be carried into execution as provided by ordinance of the governing authority and as provided by pertinent laws of the State of Georgia. 
                  ARTICLE II. - LEGISLATIVE BRANCH[2] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (2) --- 
                  Editor's note— The City of Ellenton, Georgia, currently practices a "strong council-weak mayor" form of government. 

                  Sec. 2.10. - Creation, composition, number, election. 
                  The legislative authority of the government of the City of Ellenton except as otherwise specifically provided in this Charter shall be vested in a city council to be composed of a mayor and five councilmen. The mayor and councilmen shall be elected in the manner provided by article V of this Charter. 
                  Sec. 2.11. - Terms and qualifications of office. 
                  The mayor and councilmembers shall serve for terms of four years and until their respective successors are elected and qualified. The term of office of the mayor and each councilmember shall begin on January 1 immediately following their election. No person shall be eligible to serve as mayor or councilmember unless: 
                  (1)  He has been a resident of the city for a period of one year immediately prior to the date of the election for mayor or councilman; 
                  (2)  He continues to reside within the city during his term of office; 
                  (3)  He is registered and qualified to vote in municipal elections of the City of Ellenton; and 
                  (4)  He meets the qualifications for holding civil office as provided in section 45-2-1 of the O.C.G.A. [O.C.G.A. § 45-2-1], or any other general law applicable to that office. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 1) 
                  Sec. 2.12. - Vacancy; forfeiture of office; filling of vacancies. 
                  (a)  The office of mayor or councilman shall become vacant upon the incumbent's death, resignation, forfeiture of office or removal from office in any manner authorized by this Charter or the laws of the State of Georgia. 
                  (b)  The mayor or any councilman shall forfeit his office if he: 
                  (1)  Lacks at any time during his term of office any qualification of the office as prescribed by this Charter or the laws of the State of Georgia; 
                  (2)  Willfully and knowingly violates any express prohibition of this Charter; or 
                  (3)  Is convicted of a crime involving moral turpitude. 
                  (c)  A vacancy in the office of mayor or councilman shall be filled for the remainder of the unexpired term, if any, as provided for in article V [of this Charter]. 
                  Sec. 2.13. - Compensation and expenses. 
                  The mayor and councilmembers shall receive as compensation for their services an amount prescribed by ordinance lawfully adopted by the city council. The mayor and councilmembers shall also be entitled to receive reimbursement for their actual and necessary expenses incurred in the performance of their official duties. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 2) 
                  Sec. 2.14. - Prohibitions. 
                  (a)  Except as authorized by law, neither the mayor nor any councilman shall hold any other elective city office during the term for which he was elected. 
                  (b)  Neither the mayor nor any councilman shall vote upon any question in which he is personally interested. 
                  Sec. 2.15. - Inquiries and investigations. 
                  The council may make inquiries and investigations into the affairs of the city and the conduct of any department, office or agency thereof and for this purpose may subpoena witnesses, administer oaths, take testimony and require the production of evidence. Any person who fails or refuses to obey a lawful order issued in the exercise of these powers by the council shall be punished as provided by ordinance. 
                  Sec. 2.16. - General power and authority of the council. 
                  (a)  Except as otherwise provided by law or by this Charter, the council shall be vested with all the powers of government for the City of Ellenton as provided by article I [of this Charter]. 
                  (b)  In addition to all other powers conferred upon it by law, the council shall have the authority to adopt and provide for the execution of such ordinances, resolutions, rules and regulations, not inconsistent with this Charter, the Constitution, and the laws of the State of Georgia, which it shall deem necessary, expedient or helpful for the peace, good order, protection of life and property, health, welfare, sanitation, comfort, convenience, prosperity or well-being of the inhabitants of the City of Ellenton. The council may enforce such ordinances by imposing penalties for violation thereof. 
                  Sec. 2.17. - Chief executive officer. 
                  The mayor shall be the chief executive of the City of Ellenton. He shall possess, have and exercise all of the executive and administrative powers granted to the city under the Constitution and laws of the State of Georgia and all the executive and administrative powers contained in this Charter. 
                  Sec. 2.18. - Duties of mayor. 
                  The mayor shall: 
                  (a)  Preside at all meetings of the city council; 
                  (b)  Be the official head of the city for the service of process and for ceremonial purposes; 
                  (c)  Have power to administer oaths and to take affidavits; 
                  (d)  Sign all written contracts entered into by the council on behalf of the city and all other contracts and instruments executed by the city which by law are required to be in writing; 
                  (e)  See that all laws and ordinances of the city are faithfully executed; 
                  (f)  Exercise supervision over all executive and administrative activities; 
                  (g)  Recommend to the council such measures relative to the affairs of the city, improvement of the government and promotion of the welfare of its inhabitants as he may deem expedient; 
                  (h)  Call special meetings of the council as provided for in section 2.21(b) of this Charter; 
                  (i)  Examine and audit all accounts of the city before payment; 
                  (j)  Require any department or agency of the city to submit written reports in connection with the affairs thereof whenever he deems it expedient; 
                  (k)  Perform other duties as may be required by law, this Charter or ordinance; 
                  (l)  Vote at council meetings only in case of a tie vote among the councilmen. 
                  Sec. 2.19. - Mayor pro tempore. 
                  During the absence or disability of the mayor for any cause, the mayor pro tempore, or in his absence or disability for any reason, any one of the councilmen chosen by the council, shall be clothed with all the rights and privileges of the mayor and shall perform the duties of the office of the mayor so long as such absence or disability shall continue. The mayor pro tempore shall be elected by the members of the council at the first regular meeting of the council in January each year for a term of office of one year. 
                  Sec. 2.20. - Organizational meeting. 
                  The council shall meet for organization at the regular scheduled meeting following the election. The meeting shall be called to order by the city clerk and the oath of office shall be administered to the newly elected members as follows: 
                  "I do solemnly swear that I will well and truly perform the duties of (mayor or councilman as the case may be) of the City of Ellenton and that I will support and defend the Charter thereof as well as the Constitution and laws of the State of Georgia and of the United States of America." 
                  Sec. 2.21. - Regular and special meetings. 
                  (a)  The council shall hold regular meetings at such times and places as prescribed by ordinance. The council may recess any regular meeting and continue such meeting on any weekday or hour it may fix and may transact any business at such continued meeting as may be transacted at any regular meeting. 
                  (b)  Special meetings of the council may be held on call of the mayor. Notice of such special meeting shall be served on all other members personally, or by telephone personally, or shall be left at their residences in advance of the meeting. Such notice shall not be required if the mayor and all councilmen are present when the special meeting is called. Notice of any special meeting may be waived in writing before or after such meeting, and attendance at the meeting shall also constitute a waiver of notice of any special meeting. Only the business stated in the call may be transacted at the special meeting, except by unanimous consent of all members present. With such consent any business which may be transacted in a regular meeting may be conducted at the special meeting. 
                  (c)  All meetings of council shall be public. 
                  Sec. 2.22. - Rules of procedure. 
                  The council shall adopt its rules of procedure and order of business consistent with the provisions of this Charter and shall provide for keeping a journal of its proceedings, which journal shall be a public record. 
                  Sec. 2.23. - Quorum, voting. 
                  Three councilmen shall constitute a quorum and shall be authorized to transact business of the council. Voting on the adoption of ordinances shall be taken by voice vote and the ayes and nays shall be recorded in the journal but any member of the council shall have the right to request a roll call vote. The affirmative vote of three or more councilmen shall be required for the adoption of any ordinance, resolution or motion except as otherwise provided in this Charter. 
                  Sec. 2.24. - Action requiring an ordinance. 
                  (a)  Except as herein provided, every official action of the council which is to become law shall be by ordinance. No ordinance shall contain a subject which is not expressed in its title. The enacting clause shall be: "The Council of the City of Ellenton hereby ordains…." 
                  (b)  An ordinance may be introduced by any member of the council and read at a regular or special meeting of the council. Ordinances shall be considered and adopted or rejected by the council in accordance with the rules which it shall establish. 
                  Sec. 2.25. - Codes of technical regulations. 
                  (a)  The council may adopt any standard code of technical regulations by reference thereto in an adopting ordinance. The procedures and requirements governing such adopting ordinance shall be as prescribed for ordinances generally except that a copy of each adopted code of technical regulations, as well as the adopting ordinance, shall be authenticated and recorded by the city clerk pursuant to section 2.26 of this Charter. 
                  (b)  Copies of any adopted code of technical regulations shall be made available by the clerk for distribution or for purchase at a reasonable price. 
                  Sec. 2.26. - Signing, authenticating, recording; codification; printing. 
                  (a)  The clerk shall authenticate by his signature and record in full in a properly indexed book kept for the purpose all ordinances adopted by the council. Every ordinance shall be signed by the mayor as a matter of course after adoption. 
                  (b)  The council shall provide for the preparation of a general codification of all of the ordinances of the city. The general codification shall be adopted by ordinance and shall be published promptly, together with all amendments thereto, with this Charter and any amendment thereto, and such codes of technical regulations and other rules and regulations as the city council may specify. This compilation shall be known and cited officially as "The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia." Copies of the Code shall be furnished to all officers, departments and agencies of the city and shall be made available for purchase by the public at a reasonable price as fixed by the council. 
                  (c)  The council shall cause each ordinance and each amendment to this Charter to be printed promptly following its adoption, and the printed ordinances and charter amendments shall be made available for purchase by the public at reasonable prices to be fixed by the council. Following publication of the first Code of the City of Ellenton, and at all times thereafter, the ordinances and charter amendments shall be printed in substantially the same style as the Code currently in effect and shall be suitable in form for incorporation therein. The council shall make such further arrangements as deemed desirable with respect to reproduction and distribution of any current changes in or additions to codes of technical regulations and other rules and regulations included in the Code. 
                  ARTICLE III. - EXECUTIVE BRANCH 

                  Sec. 3.10. - Administrative and service departments. 
                  (a)  The council by ordinance may establish, abolish, merge or consolidate offices, positions of employment, departments and agencies of the city as it shall deem necessary for the proper administration of the affairs and government of the city. The council shall prescribe the functions and duties of existing departments, offices and agencies hereinafter created or established; may provide that the same person shall fill any number of offices and positions of employment; and may transfer or change the function or duties of offices, position of employment, departments and agencies of the city. 
                  (b)  The operations and responsibilities of each department now or hereafter established in the city shall be distributed among such divisions or bureaus as may be provided by ordinance. Each department shall consist of such officers, employees and positions as may be provided by this Charter or by ordinance and shall be subject to the general supervision and guidance of the council. 
                  (c)  Except as otherwise provided by this Charter the directors of departments and other appointed officers of the city shall serve at the pleasure of the appointing authority. Vacancies occurring in an appointive office shall be filled in the same manner as prescribed by this Charter for an original appointment. 
                  (d)  Except as otherwise provided by law, the directors of departments and other appointed officers of the city shall be appointed solely on the basis of their respective administrative and professional qualifications. 
                  (e)  All appointive officers and directors of departments shall receive such compensation as prescribed by ordinance. 
                  Sec. 3.11. - Boards, commissions, and authorities. 
                  (a)  All members of boards, commissions and authorities shall be appointed by the council for such terms of office and such manner of appointment as provided by ordinance, except where other appointing authority, term of office or manner of appointment is prescribed by this Charter or by applicable state law. 
                  (b)  No member of any board, commission or authority shall hold any elective office in the city. 
                  (c)  Any vacancy in office of any member of a board, commission or authority of the city shall be filled for the unexpired term in the manner prescribed herein for original appointment, except as otherwise provided by this Charter or any applicable state law. 
                  (d)  No member of any board, commission or authority shall assume office until he shall have executed and filed with the clerk of the city an oath obligating himself to perform faithfully and impartially the duties of his office, such oath to be prescribed by ordinance and administered by the mayor. 
                  (e)  Any member of a board, commission or authority may be removed from office for cause by a vote of two or more members of the council. 
                  (f)  Members of boards, commissions and authorities may receive such compensation and expenses in the performance of their official duties as prescribed by ordinance. 
                  (g)  The qualifications required of members of boards, commissions and authorities shall be as prescribed by ordinance. 
                  (h)  Except as otherwise provided by this Charter or by applicable state law, each board, commission or authority of the city government shall elect one of its members as chairman and one member as vice chairman for terms of one year and may elect as its secretary one of its own members or may appoint as secretary an employee of the city. Each board, commission or authority of the city government may establish such bylaws, rules and regulations, not inconsistent with this Charter, ordinances of the city, or applicable state law, as it deems appropriate and necessary for the conduct of its affairs, copies of which shall be filed with the clerk of the city. 
                  Sec. 3.12. - City manager. 
                  The council may appoint a city manager. The duties and authority of the city manager shall be established by ordinance, and the council may specifically delegate to the city manager any of the administrative or budgetary duties of the mayor. 
                  Sec. 3.13. - City attorney. 
                  The council may appoint a city attorney, together with such assistant city attorneys as may be authorized by ordinance, and shall provide for the payment of such attorney or attorneys for services rendered to the city. The city attorney shall be responsible for representing and defending the city in all litigation in which the city is a party; may be the prosecuting officer in the municipal court; shall attend the meetings of the council as directed; shall advise the council and other officers and employees of the city concerning legal aspects of the city's affairs; and shall perform such other duties as may be required of him by virtue of his position as city attorney. 
                  Sec. 3.14. - City clerk. 
                  The council may appoint a city clerk to keep a journal of the proceedings of the city council; to maintain in a safe place all records and documents pertaining to the affairs of the city; and to perform such other duties as may be required by law or as the council may direct. 
                  Sec. 3.15. - City tax collector. 
                  The council may appoint a city tax collector to collect all taxes, licenses, fees and other monies belonging to the city subject to the provisions of this Charter and the ordinances of the city. The city tax collector shall diligently comply with and enforce all general laws of Georgia relating to the collection, sale, or foreclosure of taxes by municipalities. 
                  Sec. 3.16. - City accountant. 
                  The council may appoint a city accountant to perform the duties of an accountant. 
                  Sec. 3.17. - Consolidation of functions. 
                  The council may consolidate any two or more of the positions of city clerk, city tax collector, city accountant or any other positions or may assign the function of any one or more of such positions to the holder or holders of any other position. 
                  Sec. 3.18. - Position classification and pay plan. 
                  The council may prepare a position classification and pay plan. Said plan may apply to all employees of the City of Ellenton and to any of its agencies and offices. When a pay plan has been adopted, the council shall not increase or decrease the salaries of individual employees except by amendment of said pay plan. 
                  Sec. 3.19. - Personnel policies. 
                  The council may adopt rules and regulations consistent with this Charter concerning: 
                  (1)  The method of employee selection and probationary periods of employment; 
                  (2)  The administration of the position classification and pay plan, methods of promotion and application of service ratings thereto, and transfer of employees within the classification plan; 
                  (3)  Hours of work, vacation, sick leave and other leaves of absence, overtime pay, and the order and manner in which layoff shall be effected; and 
                  (4)  Such other personnel policies as may be necessary to provide for the adequate and systematic handling of the personnel affairs of the City of Ellenton. 
                  ARTICLE IV. - JUDICIAL BRANCH 

                  Sec. 4.10. - Municipal court. 
                  There is hereby established a court to be known as the municipal court of the City of Ellenton which shall have jurisdiction and authority to try offenses against the laws and ordinances of said city and to punish for a violation of the same. Such court shall have the power and authority to enforce its judgments by the imposition of such penalties as may be provided by law; to punish witnesses for nonattendance; to punish any person who may counsel, advise, aid, encourage or persuade another whose testimony is desired or material in any proceeding before said court to go or move beyond the reach of the process of the court; and to try all offenses within the territorial limits of the city constituting traffic cases which under the laws of Georgia are placed within the jurisdiction of municipal or police courts to the extent of and in accordance with the provisions of such laws and all laws subsequently enacted amendatory thereof. Said court shall be presided over by the judge of said court. In the absence or disqualification of the judge, the judge pro tem shall preside and shall exercise the same powers and duties as the judge when so acting. 
                  Sec. 4.11. - Judge. 
                  (a)  No person shall be qualified or eligible to serve as judge unless he shall have attained the age of 21 years. The judge shall serve at the discretion of the council. The compensation of the judge shall be fixed by the council. 
                  (b)  The judge pro tem shall serve in the absence of the judge, shall be appointed by the council and shall take the same oath as the judge. 
                  (c)  Before entering on the duties of his office, the judge shall take an oath before an officer duly authorized to administer oaths in this state that he will truly, honestly and faithfully discharge the duties of his office to the best of his ability without fear, favor or partiality. The oath shall be entered upon the minutes of the council. 
                  State Law reference— Requirements for municipal court judges, O.C.G.A. § 36-32-1.1. 
                  Sec. 4.12. - Convening. 
                  Said court shall be convened at such times as designated by ordinance or at such times as deemed necessary to keep current the dockets thereof. 
                  Sec. 4.13. - Jurisdiction; powers. 
                  (a)  The municipal court shall try and punish for crimes against the City of Ellenton and for violation of its ordinances. The municipal court shall have authority to punish those in its presence for contempt, provided that such punishment shall not exceed $25.00 or three days in jail. The municipal court may fix punishment for offenses within its jurisdiction [according to the penalties allowed under state law]. As an alternative to fine or imprisonment, the municipal court may sentence any offender upon conviction to labor in a city work gang or on the streets, sidewalks, squares or other public works for a period not exceeding 60 days. 
                  (b)  The municipal court shall have authority to establish a schedule of fees to defray the cost of operation and shall be entitled to reimbursement to the cost of meals, transportation and caretaking of prisoners bound over to superior courts for violations of state law. 
                  (c)  The municipal court shall have authority to establish bail and recognizances to insure the presence of those charged with violations before said court and shall have discretionary authority to accept cash or personal or real property as surety for appearance of persons charged with violations. Whenever any person gives bail for his appearance and fails to appear at the time fixed for trial, his bond shall be forfeited by the judge presiding at such time and an execution shall be issued thereon by serving the defendant and his sureties with a rule nisi. If cash or property is accepted in lieu of bond for security for the appearance of a defendant at trial and such defendant fails to appear at the time and place fixed for trial, the cash so deposited shall have a lien against it for the value forfeited, which lien shall be enforceable in the same manner and to the same extent as a lien for city property taxes. 
                  (d)  The municipal court shall have the authority to bind prisoners over to the appropriate court when it appears by probable cause that a state law has been violated. 
                  (e)  The municipal court shall have the authority to administer oaths and to perform all other acts necessary or proper to the conduct of said court. 
                  (f)  The municipal court may compel the presence of all parties necessary to a proper disposal of each case by the issuance of summons, subpoena and warrants which may be served as executed by any officer as authorized by this Charter or by state law. 
                  (g)  The municipal court is specifically vested with all of the jurisdiction and powers throughout the entire area of the City of Ellenton granted by state laws generally to mayor's, recorder's and police courts, and particularly by such laws as authorize the abatement of nuisances. 
                  Sec. 4.14. - Appeal. 
                  The right of appeal and any bond as may be required to secure the costs on appeal to the Superior Court of Colquitt County from the municipal court shall lie in the same manner and under the same procedure as generally prescribed for appeals and appeal bonds from the probate court; provided, however, that any person who fails to file his appeal within ten days of the date on his conviction shall be deemed to have waived any such right. An appeal to the superior court shall be a de novo proceeding. 
                  Sec. 4.15. - Rules for court. 
                  With the approval of the council, the judge shall have full power and authority to make reasonable rules and regulations necessary and proper to secure the efficient and successful administration of the municipal court; provided, however, that the council may adopt in part or in toto the rules and regulations relative to the procedure of the operation of the superior court under the general laws of the State of Georgia. The rules and regulations made or adopted for said court shall be filed with the city clerk, shall be available for public inspection, and, upon request, a copy shall be furnished to all defendants in municipal court proceedings at least 48 hours prior to said proceedings. 
                  ARTICLE V. - ELECTIONS 

                  Sec. 5.10. - Regular elections. 
                  (a)  For purposes of electing the mayor and five councilmembers as provided in this Charter, each shall be elected at large. The mayor and councilmember positions shall be designated by post number. The mayor shall be designated Post 1 and the councilmembers elected in even-numbered years as of the effective date of this Act [Charter] shall be designated Posts 2 and 3. The councilmembers elected in odd-numbered years as of the effective date of this Act [Charter] shall be designated as 
                  Posts 4, 5 and 6. The mayor shall be considered a councilmember for all purposes, except as may be specifically limited in this Charter. A reference in a city ordinance to the mayor and council shall mean the city council. 
                  (b)  The members of the city council serving in the office on the effective date of this Act [Charter] and any person selected to fill a vacancy in any such office shall continue to serve until the expiration of the terms for which they were elected and until their successors are elected and qualified. 
                  (c)  The members of the reconstituted city council shall be elected as provided in this subsection. The members from Posts 1, 2 and 3 shall be elected at the general election on the Tuesday following the first Monday in November 2014, shall take office January 1 immediately following that election, and shall serve for initial terms of office of three years. The first members from Posts 4, 5 and 6 shall be elected at the general election on the Tuesday following the first Monday in November 2013, shall take office on January 1 immediately following that election, and shall serve for initial terms of office of two years. Those and all future successors to councilmembers whose terms of office are to expire shall be elected at the time of the election in November immediately preceding the expiration of such terms, shall take office January 1 immediately following that election, and shall serve for terms of office of four years each. 
                  (d)  All members of the city council who are elected thereto shall be nominated and elected in accordance with Chapter 2 of Title 21 of the O.C.G.A. [O.C.G.A. § 21-2-1 et seq.], the Georgia Election Code. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 3) 
                  Sec. 5.11. - Election procedures. 
                  The council may, by ordinance not in conflict with or preempted by general law, provide rules and regulations governing qualifying fees, the nomination of candidates, and such other procedures as are necessary for the conduct of elections. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 3) 
                  Sec. 5.12. - Reserved. 
                  Editor's note— Section 5.12 pertaining to applicability of general election laws was deleted pursuant to section 3 of 2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68). 
                  Sec. 5.13. - Vacancies on council. 
                  If the office of mayor or councilman becomes vacant for any cause whatsoever, the council or those remaining shall fill such vacancy by appointment. The qualifications of the appointee shall conform to the requirements of this Charter. 
                  Upon all five positions of the council becoming vacant, at the same time, the mayor shall call for a special election to be held within 30 days after the call therefor for the purpose of filling such vacancies for the remainder of the respective terms of office for each council position. Upon the office of mayor and all five positions of the council becoming vacant, at the same time, the city clerk shall call for a special election to be held within 30 days after the call therefor for the purpose of filling such vacancies for the remainder of the respective terms of office for each council position and for the office of mayor. 
                  Sec. 5.14. - Grounds for removal. 
                  The mayor or any councilman shall be subject to removal from office for any one or more of the following causes: 
                  (a)  Incompetence, misfeasance or malfeasance in office; 
                  (b)  Conviction of a crime involving moral turpitude; 
                  (c)  Failure at any time to possess any of the qualifications of office as provided by this Charter or by law; 
                  (d)  Willful violation of any express prohibition of this Charter; 
                  (e)  Abandonment of office or neglect to perform the duties thereof; or 
                  (f)  Failure for any other cause to perform the duties of office as required by this Charter or by law. 
                  Sec. 5.15. - Procedure for removal. 
                  Removal of an elected officer from office may be accomplished by one of the following methods: 
                  (a)  By action of four-fifths vote of the entire membership of the council. If an elected officer is sought to be removed by the action of the council, such officer shall be entitled to a written notice specifying the ground for removal and to a public hearing which shall be held not less than ten days after the service of such written notice. Any elected officer sought to be removed from office as herein provided shall have the right of appeal from the decision of the council to the Superior Court of Colquitt County. Such appeal shall be governed by the same rules as govern appeals to the superior court from the probate court. 
                  (b)  By information filed in the Superior Court of Colquitt County as provided by law. 
                  ARTICLE VI. - FINANCE AND FISCAL 

                  Sec. 6.10. - Property taxes. 
                  All property subject to taxation for state or county purposes, assessed as of January 1 in each year, shall be subject to the property tax levied by the City of Ellenton. The 
                  council shall use the county assessment for the year in which the city taxes are to be levied and shall request the county to furnish appropriate information for such purpose. 
                  Sec. 6.11. - Tax levy. 
                  The council shall be authorized to levy an ad valorem tax on all real and personal property within the corporate limits of the city for the purpose of raising revenue to defray the cost of operating the city government, providing governmental services and for any other public purpose as determined by the council. The council is also authorized to provide for sufficient levy to pay principal and interest on general obligations. The City of Ellenton is hereby exempted from the provisions of Georgia Code sections 92-4101 through 92-4104 inclusive. 
                  Sec. 6.12. - Tax due dates and tax bills. 
                  The council shall provide by ordinance when the taxes of the city shall fall due, in what length of time said taxes may be paid, whether said taxes may be paid in installments or in one lump sum, and when, how and upon what terms such taxes shall be due and payable. The council may authorize the voluntary payment of taxes prior to the time when due. 
                  Sec. 6.13. - Collection of delinquent taxes. 
                  The council may provide by ordinance for the collection of delinquent taxes by fi. fa. issued by the city clerk and executed by any police officer of the city under the same procedure provided by the laws governing execution of such process from the superior court or by the use of any other available legal processes and remedies. A lien shall exist against all property upon which city property taxes are levied, as of the assessment date of each year, which lien shall be superior to all other liens, except that it shall have equal dignity with those of federal, state or county taxes. In cases of hardship, the council shall have discretionary authority to waive any and all penalties imposed by this Charter on delinquent taxes, fees, assessments or on other amounts due to the city. 
                  Sec. 6.14. - Licenses, occupational taxes, excise taxes. 
                  The council shall have full power to levy by ordinance such license and specific or occupational taxes upon the residents of the City of Ellenton, both individual and corporate, and on all those who transact or offer to transact business therein, or who practice or offer to practice any profession or calling therein, as the council may deem expedient for the public health, safety, benefit, convenience or advantage of the city; to classify businesses, occupations, professions or callings for the purpose of such taxation in any way which is lawful; to require such persons to procure licenses; to compel the payment of such licenses by execution or any other lawful manner; to make laws and regulations necessary or proper to carry out the powers herein conferred; and to prescribe penalties for the violation thereof. The council shall have full power and authority to levy an excise tax not prohibited by general law. 
                  Sec. 6.15. - Sewer service charges. 
                  The council by ordinance shall have the right, power and authority to assess and collect fees, charges and tolls for sewer services rendered both within and without the corporate limits of the City of Ellenton to provide for the cost and expense of collecting and disposing of sewage through the sewerage facilities of said city. If unpaid, said sewer service charge shall constitute a lien against any property served, second in priority only to liens for county and city property taxes. Said lien shall be enforceable in the same manner and under the same remedies as a lien for city property taxes. 
                  Sec. 6.16. - Sanitary and health services charge. 
                  The council shall have authority by ordinance to provide for, enforce, levy and collect the cost of sanitary and health services necessary in the operation of the city from all individuals, firms, and corporations, residing in or doing business in said city and benefiting from such service. Such authority shall include the power to assess, levy and collect annual or monthly sanitary taxes or fees in such amount or amounts, and based upon and in accordance with such classification of property and sanitary service or services provided, as may be fixed by ordinance. Said sanitary taxes and the assessment thereof shall be a charge and lien against the real estate in respect to which said taxes are so assessed, and the owner or owners thereof, superior to all other liens except liens for county and city property taxes. Said lien shall be enforceable in the same manner and under the same remedies as a lien for city property taxes. 
                  Sec. 6.17. - Special assessments. 
                  The council shall have power and authority to assess all or part of the cost of constructing, reconstructing, widening or improving any public way, street, sidewalk, curbing, gutters, sewers or other utility mains and appurtenances against the abutting property owner or owners, under terms and conditions as may be prescribed by ordinance. Such special assessments shall become delinquent 30 days after their due dates, shall thereupon be subject, in addition to fi. fa. charges, to a penalty of ten percent and shall thereafter be subject to interest at the rate of seven percent per annum from date due until paid. A lien shall exist against the abutting property superior to all other liens, except that it shall be of equal dignity with liens for county and city property taxes. Said lien shall be enforceable by the same procedures and under the same remedies as provided for in this article for city property taxes. 
                  Sec. 6.18. - Transfer of executions. 
                  The city clerk shall be authorized to assign or transfer any fi. fa. or execution issued for any tax or for any street, sewer or other assessment in the same manner and to the same extent as provided by Georgia law regarding sales and transfers of tax fi. fas. Such transfer or assignment, when made, shall vest the purchaser or transferee with all right, title and interest as provided by Georgia law governing sales and transfers of tax fi. fas.; provided, that upon levy of execution and sale of property pursuant to such tax fi. fa., whether assigned, transferred or executed by the city, the owner of such property in fee simple or lesser interest shall not lose his right to redeem the property in accordance with the requirements of redemption of property sold under state or county ad valorem tax fi. fas., as said requirements now exist or as may be hereinafter provided by law. 
                  Sec. 6.19. - General obligation bonds. 
                  The council shall have the power to issue bonds to raise revenue for any project, program or venture authorized under this Charter or the general laws of the state. Such bonding authority shall be exercised in accordance with the laws governing bond issuances by municipalities in effect at the time said issue is undertaken. 
                  Sec. 6.20. - Revenue bonds. 
                  Revenue bonds may be issued by the council as provided by an act of the General Assembly of Georgia, approved March 31, 1937, known as the Revenue Bond Law (Ga. Laws 1937, p. 761), [O.C.G.A. § 36-82-60 et seq.], as now or hereafter amended, or by any other Georgia law as now or hereafter provided. 
                  Sec. 6.21. - Short term notes. 
                  Pursuant to applicable state law, the city may obtain temporary loans between January 1 and December 31 of each year. 
                  Sec. 6.22. - Fiscal year. 
                  The council may set the fiscal year by ordinance. Said fiscal year shall constitute the budget year and the year for financial accounting of every office, department, institution, agency and activity of the city government unless otherwise provided by state or federal law. 
                  Sec. 6.23. - Preparation of budgets. 
                  The council may provide by ordinance the procedures and requirements for the preparation and execution of an annual operating budget, a capital improvement program and a capital budget including requirements as to the scope, content and form of such budgets and programs. 
                  Sec. 6.24. - Additional appropriations. 
                  The council may make appropriations in addition to those contained in the current operating budget at any regular or special meeting called for such purpose, but any such additional appropriations may be made only from an existing unappropriated surplus in the fund to which it applies. 
                  Sec. 6.25. - Contracting procedures. 
                  All contracts shall be made or authorized by the council, and no contracts shall bind the city unless reduced to writing and approved by the council. 
                  Sec. 6.26. - Centralized purchasing. 
                  (a)  The council may by ordinance prescribe procedures for a system of centralized purchasing for the City of Ellenton. 
                  (b)  The council may sell and convey any real or personal property owned or held by the City of Ellenton for governmental or other purposes, at a public or private sale, with or without advertisement, for such consideration as it shall deem equitable and just for the city. 
                  (c)  The council may quitclaim any rights it may have in property not needed for public purposes upon report by the mayor and adoption of a resolution, both finding that the property is not needed for public or other purposes and that the interest of the city has no readily ascertainable monetary value. 
                  (d)  Whenever in opening, extending or widening any street, avenue, alley or public place of the city a small parcel or tract of land is cut off or separated by such work from a larger tract or boundary of land owned by the city, the council may authorize the mayor to execute and deliver in the name of the city a deed conveying said cutoff or separated parcel or tract of land to an abutting or adjoining property owner or owners in exchange for rights-of-way of said street, avenue, alley or public place or in settlement of any alleged damages sustained by said abutting or adjoining property owners. All deeds and conveyances heretofore and hereafter so executed and delivered shall convey all title and interest the city has in such property, notwithstanding the fact that no public sale after advertisement was or is hereafter made. 
                  ARTICLE VII. - GENERAL PROVISIONS 

                  Sec. 7.10. - Official bonds. 
                  The officers and employees, both elected and appointed, of the City of Ellenton shall execute such official bond in such amounts and upon such terms and conditions as the city council may from time to time require. 
                  Sec. 7.11. - Existing ordinances and regulations. 
                  Existing ordinances and resolutions of the City of Ellenton not inconsistent with the provisions of this Charter shall continue in effect until they have been repealed, modified or amended by the council. Existing rules and regulations of departments or agencies of the City of Ellenton not inconsistent with the provisions of this Charter shall continue in effect until they have been repealed, modified or amended. 
                  Sec. 7.12. - Section captions, appendices. 
                  The captions to the several sections of this Charter are informative only and are not to be considered as a part thereof. 
                  Sec. 7.13. - Penalties. 
                  The violation of any provisions of this Charter for which penalty is not specifically provided shall be a misdemeanor, punishable by imprisonment of not more than 12 months or a fine of not more than $1,000.00, or both. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 4) 
                  Sec. 7.14. - Specific repealer. 
                  An act incorporating the City of Ellenton in the County of Colquitt, approved August 13, 1910 (Ga. Laws 1910, p. 703), is hereby repealed in its entirety and all amendatory acts thereto and all laws and parts of laws in conflict with this Charter are likewise repealed in their entirety. 
                  Sec. 7.15. - Severability. 
                  If any article, section, subsection, paragraph, sentence or part thereof of this Charter shall be held to be invalid or unconstitutional, such invalidity or unconstitutionality shall not affect or impair other parts of this Charter, unless it clearly appears that such other parts are wholly and necessarily dependent upon the part or parts held to be invalid or unconstitutional, it being the legislative intent in enacting this Charter that each article, section, subsection, paragraph, sentence or part thereof be enacted separately and independently of each other. 
                  Sec. 7.16. - Enumeration of powers. 
                  The enumeration of powers contained in this Charter shall be unrestrictive such that the city council may exercise all powers, authority, and jurisdiction needed to fulfill the purposes of this Charter as if the same were specifically enumerated. The city council may pass all laws, ordinances, rules, and regulations, consistent with its authority and the laws of this state, deemed necessary for the health, safety, and welfare of the residents of the City of Ellenton. Where powers are conferred by this Charter but the manner of exercising such powers is not fully specified, the city council may provide by ordinance, rule, or regulation procedures necessary for the implementation of such powers. 
                  (2013 Ga. Laws (Act 68), § 5) 
                  Sec. 7.17. - Repealer. 
                  All laws and parts of laws in conflict with this Charter are hereby repealed. 
                  CHARTER COMPARATIVE TABLE - GEORGIA LAWS 
                  This table shows the location of the sections of the basic Charter and any amendments thereto. 

                   
                  PART II - CODE OF ORDINANCES 
</p>
         </div>
         <div type="related-laws"></div>
         <div type="special-acts"></div>
         <div type="code">
            <div type="chapter" n="1">
               <head>Chapter 1 - GENERAL PROVISIONS[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Authority of municipality to adopt ordinances, resolutions or regulations, O.C.G.A. § 36-35-3. 

                  Sec. 1-1. - How Code designated and cited. 
                  The provisions embraced in the following chapters and sections shall constitute and be designated "The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia," and may be so cited. The Code may also be cited as the "Ellenton City Code" or the "City Code." 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-101) 
                  Sec. 1-2. - Rules of construction. 
                  In the construction of this Code and of all ordinances, the following rules shall be observed unless such construction would be inconsistent with the manifest intent of the mayor and council: 
                  (1)  General rule. All words and phrases shall be construed and understood according to the common and approved usage of the language, but technical words and phrases and such others as may have acquired a peculiar and appropriate meaning in the law shall be construed and understood according to such peculiar and appropriate meaning. 
                  (2)  Gender; singular and plural. Every word in any Code provision or ordinance importing the masculine gender shall extend to and be applied to females as well as males; and every word importing the singular number only shall extend and be applied to several persons or things as well as to one person or thing; and every word importing the plural number only shall extend and be applied to one person or thing as well as to several persons or things. 
                  (3)  Tenses. The use of any verb in the present tense shall include the future when applicable. 
                  (4)  Joint authority. All words purporting to give a joint authority to three or more city officers or other persons shall be construed as giving such authority to a majority of such officers or other persons unless it shall be otherwise expressly declared in the law giving the authority. 
                  (5)  Delegation of authority. Whenever a provision requires the head of a department or other officer of the city to do some act or perform some duty, it shall be construed to authorize subordinates to do the required act or perform the required duty unless the terms of the provision designate otherwise. 
                  (6)  Computation of time. Except as otherwise provided by time period computations specifically applying to other laws, when a period of time measured in days, weeks, months, years or other measurements of time except hours is prescribed for the exercise of any privilege or the discharge of any duty, the first day shall not be counted but the last day shall be counted; and, if the last day falls on Saturday or Sunday, the party having such privilege or duty shall have through the following Monday to exercise the privilege or to discharge the duty. When the last day prescribed for such action falls on a public and legal holiday as set forth in O.C.G.A. § 1-4-1, the party having the privilege or duty shall have through the next business day to exercise the privilege or to discharge the duty. When the period of time prescribed is less than seven days, intermediate Saturdays, Sundays and legal holidays shall be excluded in the computation. 
                  (7)  Overlapping provisions. Where any provision of this Code imposes greater restrictions upon the subject matter than any general provisions imposed by this Code, the provision imposing the greater restriction or regulation shall be applicable. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-102) 
                  Sec. 1-3. - Definitions. 
                  Words and phrases used in this Code shall have the following meanings, unless otherwise specified. 
                  City. The term "the city" or "this city" means the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
                  City council, council. The term "city council" or "council" means the city council of the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
                  Code. The term "Code" means The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, as designated in section 1-1. 
                  Conjunctions. In a provision involving two or more items, conditions, provisions or events, which items, conditions, provisions or events are connected by the conjunction "and," "or" or "either … or," the conjunction shall be interpreted as follows, except that in appropriate cases the terms "or" and "and" are interchangeable: 
                  (1)  The term "and" indicates that all the connected terms, conditions, provisions or events apply. 
                  (2)  The term "or" indicates that the connected terms, conditions, provisions or events apply singly or in any combination. 
                  (3)  The term "either…or" indicates that the connected terms, conditions, provisions or events apply singly but not in combination. 
                  County. The term "the county" or "this county" means the County of Colquitt, Georgia. 
                  Court. The term "court" means the recorder's court of the city. 
                  Day. The term "day" means a calendar day of 24 hours. 
                  Delegation of authority. Whenever a provision appears requiring the head of a department of the county to do some act or make certain inspections, it is to be construed to authorize the head of the department to designate, delegate and authorize subordinates to perform the required act or make the required inspection unless the terms of the provision or section designate otherwise. 
                  Gender. Words importing the masculine gender shall include the feminine and neuter. 
                  Governing authority, governing body. The term "governing authority" or "governing body" means the mayor and city council of the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
                  Interpretation. In the interpretation and application of any provision of this Code, it shall be held to be the minimum requirements adopted for the promotion of the public health, safety, comfort, convenience and general welfare. Where any provision of the Code imposes greater restrictions upon the subject matter than the general provision imposed by the Code, the provision imposing the greater restriction or regulation shall be deemed to be controlling. 
                  Judge or recorder. The term "judge" or "recorder" means the judge of the recorder's court of the city. 
                  Keeper and proprietor. The terms "keeper" and "proprietor" mean and include persons, firms, associations, corporations, receivers, trustees, personal representatives, clubs and partnerships, whether acting by themselves or through a servant, agent or employee. 
                  Mayor. The term "mayor" means the mayor of the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 
                  Month. The term "month" means a calendar month. 
                  Names of officers and departments. The name or title of any officer or department shall be read as though the words "of the City of Ellenton" were added thereto. 
                  Nontechnical and technical words. Words and phrases shall be construed according to the common and approved usage of the language, but technical words and phrases and such others as may have acquired a peculiar and appropriate meaning in law shall be construed and understood according to such meaning. 
                  Number. Words used in the singular include the plural and the plural includes the singular number. 
                  Oath. The term "oath" shall be construed to include an affirmation in all cases in which, by law, an affirmation may be substituted for an oath, and in such cases the terms "affirm" and "affirmed" shall be equivalent to the terms "swear" or "sworn." 
                  O.C.G.A. The abbreviation "O.C.G.A." means the Official Code of Georgia Annotated. 
                  Owner. The term "owner," applied to a building or land, includes any part owner, joint owner, tenant in common, joint tenant or tenant by the entirety, of the whole or a part of such building or land. 
                  Person. The term "person" includes a corporation, firm, partnership, association, organization and any other group acting as a unit, as well as an individual. 
                  Personal property. The term "personal property" includes every species of property except real property, as hereinafter defined. 
                  Preceding, following. The terms "preceding" and "following" mean next before and next after, respectively. 
                  Property. The term "property" includes real, personal and mixed estates and interests. 
                  Real property. The term "real property" includes lands, tenements and hereditaments. 
                  Reasonable time or notice. Reasonable time or notice shall be deemed to mean only such time as may be necessary for the prompt performance of the act required. 
                  Seal. The term "seal" means the city seal. 
                  Sidewalk. The term "sidewalk" means any portion of a street between the curbline and the adjacent property line intended for the use of pedestrians, but shall not include any unimproved areas between the curbline and improved walkways. 
                  Signature, subscription. The term "signature" or "subscription" includes a mark intended as such when the person cannot write. 
                  State. The term "the state" or "this state" means the State of Georgia. 
                  Street. The term "street" means and includes any public way, road, highway, street, avenue, boulevard, parkway, alley, viaduct, bridge, and the approaches thereto, within the city. 
                  Tenant or occupant. The term "tenant" or "occupant," applied to a building or land, includes any person holding a written or oral lease of, or who occupies the whole or a part of such building or land, either alone or with others. 
                  Week. The term "week" means seven days. 
                  Writing or written. The term "writing" or "written" includes printing and any other mode of representing words and letters. 
                  Year. The term "year" means a calendar year. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-103) 
                  State Law reference— Statutory definitions and rules of construction, O.C.G.A. § 1-3-1 et seq.; computation of time, O.C.G.A. § 1-3-1; construction of definitions, O.C.G.A. § 1-3-2; meaning of certain words, O.C.G.A. § 1-3-3; time, O.C.G.A. § 9-11-6. 
                  Sec. 1-4. - Section headings. 
                  (a)  The headings of the several sections and subsections of this Code are intended as mere captions to indicate the contents of the section or subsection and shall not be deemed or taken to be titles of such sections, nor as any part of the section or subsection, nor, unless expressly so provided, shall they be so deemed when any of such sections or subsections, including the headings, is amended or re-enacted. 
                  (b)  The history notes appearing in parentheses after each section and the references and editor's notes scattered throughout the Code are for the benefit of the user of the Code and shall have no legal effect. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-104) 
                  Sec. 1-5. - Severability of parts of Code. 
                  It is hereby declared to be the intention of the mayor and city council that the sections, paragraphs, sentences, clauses and phrases of this Code are severable, and if any phrase, clause, sentence, paragraph or section of this Code shall be declared unconstitutional by the valid judgment or decree of any court of competent jurisdiction, such unconstitutionality shall not affect any of the remaining clauses, sentences, paragraphs and sections of this Code. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-105) 
                  Sec. 1-6. - Effect of repeal or expiration of Code section. 
                  (a)  The repeal of a Code section or ordinance, or its expiration by virtue of any provision contained therein, shall not affect any right accrued or any offense committed, any penalty or punishment incurred, or any proceeding commenced before the repeal took effect or the ordinance expired. 
                  (b)  When any ordinance repealing a former Code section, ordinance, clause or provision shall be itself repealed, such repeal shall not be construed to revive such former Code section, ordinance, clause or provision unless it shall be expressly so provided. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-106) 
                  Sec. 1-7. - Amending Code. 
                  (a)  All ordinances passed subsequent to this Code which amend, repeal or in any way affect this Code shall be numbered in accordance with the numbering system of this Code and printed for inclusion herein. In the case of repealed chapters, sections, and subsections or any part thereof by subsequent ordinances, such repealed portions may be excluded from the Code by omission from reprinted pages affected thereby. The subsequent ordinances as numbered and printed, or omitted, in the case of repeal, shall be prima facie evidence of such subsequent ordinances until such time as the Code and subsequent ordinances are readopted as a new code by the city council. 
                  (b)  Amendments to any of the provisions of this Code may be made by amending such provisions by specific reference to the section number of this Code in the following language: "That section ____________ of The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, is hereby amended to read as follows…." The new provisions may then be set out in full as desired. 
                  (c)  In the event a new section not heretofore existing in the Code is to be added, the following language may be used: "The Code of the City of Ellenton, Georgia, is hereby amended by adding a section (or subsection or chapter) to be numbered ____________ , which section reads as follows…." The new provision shall then be set out in full as desired. 
                  (d)  All sections, chapters or provisions sought to be repealed must be specifically repealed by section, chapter or provision number, as the case may be. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-107) 
                  Sec. 1-8. - Altering Code. 
                  It shall be unlawful for any person to change or amend by additions or deletions any part or portion of this Code, or to insert or delete pages or portions thereof, or to alter or tamper with such Code in any manner whatsoever, except by ordinance or resolution or other official act of the mayor and city council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-108) 
                  Sec. 1-9. - Penalty where no penalty provided. 
                  (a)  In this section, the term "violation of this Code" means any of the following: 
                  (1)  Doing an act that is prohibited or made or declared unlawful, an offense, a violation or a misdemeanor by ordinance, by statute adopted by reference in this Code, by state rule or regulation adopted by reference in this Code, or by rule or regulation authorized by ordinance. 
                  (2)  Failure to perform an act that is required to be performed by ordinance, by statute adopted by reference in this Code, by state rule or regulation adopted by reference in this Code or by rule or regulation authorized by ordinance. 
                  (3)  Failure to perform an act if the failure is prohibited or is made or declared unlawful, an offense, a violation or a misdemeanor by ordinance, by statute adopted by reference in this Code, by state rule or regulation adopted by reference in this Code or by rule or regulation authorized by ordinance. 
                  (b)  In this section, the term "violation of this Code" does not include the failure of a city officer or city employee to perform an official duty unless it is specifically provided that the failure to perform the duty is to be punished as provided in this section. 
                  (c)  Unless a higher penalty is otherwise specified, whenever in this Code or in any ordinance of the city any act is prohibited or is made or declared to be unlawful or an offense, or whenever in this Code or any ordinance the doing of any act is required and the failure to do such act is declared to be unlawful, and no specific penalty is provided, and unless otherwise provided by state law, the violation of any such provision of this Code or any such ordinance shall be punished by a fine not to exceed $1,000.00 and imprisonment in the city or county jail and work and labor on the streets or public works of the city, whether within or without the corporate limits, not to exceed one year, or both a fine and sentence of imprisonment and labor; and all sentences may be in the alternative and fines may be imposed with the alternative of sentence to imprisonment and labor if the fines are not paid. Each day any violation of this Code or of any ordinance shall continue shall constitute a separate offense. 
                  (d)  Violations of this Code may be abated by injunctive or other equitable relief. The imposition of a penalty does not prevent injunctive relief. 
                  (e)  The judge of the municipal court shall have the power and authority to: 
                  (1)  Impose upon persons convicted in the municipal court the fines provided for in this Code, the ordinances of the city, or as otherwise provided by law, with the alternative of other punishment allowed by law, if such fines are not paid; 
                  (2)  Sentence such person to community service work; or 
                  (3)  Impose a sentence consisting of any combination of the penalties provided for in this section. 
                  (f)  The judge of the municipal court shall have full power and authority to declare the forfeiture of bonds given by offenders for their appearance before the municipal court upon the offender's failure to appear as provided for in such bond. The procedure for the forfeiture of such bonds shall be as is provided for the forfeiture of bonds and recognizance set forth in O.C.G.A. § 17-6-70 et seq. 
                  (g)  The infliction of a penalty under the provisions of this section shall not prevent the revocation of any permit or license or the taking of other punitive or remedial action where called for or permitted under the provisions of the city's Charter or Code. 
                  (Prior Code, § 1-109) 
                  Sec. 1-10. - Provisions considered as continuation of existing ordinances. 
                  The provisions appearing in this and the following chapters and sections, so far as they are the same as those of ordinances or resolutions existing at the time of the adoption of this Code, shall be considered as a continuation thereof and not as new enactments. 
                  Sec. 1-11. - Prior offenses, penalties and rights not affected by adoption of Code. 
                  (a)  Nothing in this Code or the ordinance adopting this Code shall affect any offense or act committed or done or any penalty of forfeiture incurred or any contract or right established or accruing before the effective date of this Code. 
                  (b)  Nothing contained in this chapter shall be construed as abating any action pending under or by virtue of any general ordinance of the city repealed in this chapter, and all general ordinances contained in this Code shall be deemed to be continuing and not a new enactment of the same ordinance. This chapter shall not be deemed as discontinuing, abating, modifying or altering any penalty accrued or to accrue or as affecting the liability of any person or as waiving any right of the city under any ordinance or section thereof in force at the time of the adoption of this Code. 
                  Sec. 1-12. - Rates, charges, and fees established. 
                  (a)  Unless otherwise provided for, all rates, charges, or fees necessary for the administration and enforcement of the provisions of this Code shall be as currently established or as hereafter adopted by motion, resolution or ordinance of the city council, from time to time. Any rates, charges, or fees established by the city pursuant to the regulations or requirements established herein may be changed from time to time by the city council, and such changes shall both be considered an amendment to this Code. 
                  (b)  Whenever any provision of this Code provides that a rate, charge, or fee shall be established by the city council, from time to time, and the amount of such rate, charge, or fee is not expressed in this Code in any dollar amount, then the amount of such rate, charge, or fee shall be the most recent and latest amount established, set or fixed by the city council by ordinance, resolution or motion. 
                  Sec. 1-13. - Certain ordinances not affected by Code. 
                  Nothing in this Code or the ordinance adopting this Code shall be construed to repeal or otherwise affect the validity of any of the following: 
                  (1)  Any offense or act committed or done or any penalty or forfeiture incurred or any contract or right established or accruing before the effective date of this Code; 
                  (2)  Any ordinance or resolution promising or guaranteeing the payment of money for the city or authorizing the issuance of any bonds of the city or any evidence of the city's indebtedness; 
                  (3)  Any contract or obligation assumed by the city; 
                  (4)  Any ordinance or resolution fixing the salary of any city officer or employee, unless superseded; 
                  (5)  Any ordinance or resolution establishing and/or prescribing employment, benefits, and/or personnel policies and procedures; 
                  (6)  Any right of franchise granted by the city to any person, firm, or corporation; 
                  (7)  Any ordinance or resolution dedicating, naming, establishing, locating, relocating, closing, opening, widening, paving, widening, vacating, etc., any street or public way in the city; 
                  (8)  Any ordinance or resolution establishing and prescribing the street grades of any street in the city; 
                  (9)  Any appropriation ordinance; 
                  (10)  Any ordinance or resolution which, by its own terms, is effective for a stated or limited term; 
                  (11)  Any ordinance or resolution providing for local improvements and assessing taxes therefor; 
                  (12)  Any specific rezoning ordinance or amendments thereto; 
                  (13)  Any ordinance or resolution dedicating or accepting any subdivision plat or providing for subdivision regulations; 
                  (14)  Any ordinance or resolution describing or altering the boundaries of the city or annexing property to the city; 
                  (15)  The administrative ordinances or resolutions of the city not in conflict or inconsistent with the provisions of this Code; 
                  (16)  Any ordinance levying or imposing taxes not included in this Code; 
                  (17)  Any ordinance or regulation prescribing traffic regulations for specific locations concerning through streets, parking limitations, parking prohibitions, one-way traffic, limitations on loads of vehicles or loading zones, not in conflict or inconsistent with this Code; 
                  (18)  Any ordinance or resolution of agreement with another political subdivision; and 
                  (19)  Any other ordinance or resolution, or part thereof, which is not of a general and permanent nature, or which is referred to elsewhere in this Code as continuing in effect; 
                  or shall the repeal of any such ordinance or resolution be construed to revive any ordinance, resolution or part thereof that has been repealed or superseded by a subsequent ordinance or resolution which is repealed or superseded by this chapter. All such ordinances are hereby recognized as continuing in full force and effect to the same extent as if set out at length in this Code. 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="2">
               <head>Chapter 2 - ADMINISTRATION[1] </head>
               <p>                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Supplemental powers of municipalities and counties enumerated, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III; municipal corporations generally, O.C.G.A. § 36-3-1 et seq.; powers of municipal corporations generally, O.C.G.A. § 36-34-1 et seq.; powers relating to administration of municipal government generally, O.C.G.A. § 36-34-2; provisions applicable to counties and municipalities, O.C.G.A. § 36-60-1 et seq.; provisions applicable to counties and municipal corporations, O.C.G.A. § 36-80-1 et seq. 

                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 2-1. - Exercise of governmental authority. 
                  The corporate governmental powers of the city shall be exercised by the mayor and council in the manner provided by charter and by the provisions of this chapter. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-101) 
                  Sec. 2-2. - Code of ethics. 
                  (a)  Prohibited conduct. Public officials and employees of the city shall treat all citizens with courtesy, impartiality, fairness, and equality under the law, and shall avoid both actual and potential conflicts between their private self-interest and the public interest. Prohibited conduct of each such official and employee shall include, but not be limited to, the following: 
                  (1)  Granting or making available to any person any special consideration, treatment, advantage, or favor beyond that which it is the general practice to grant or make available to the public at large; 
                  (2)  Requesting, using, or permitting the use of any publicly owned or publicly supported property, vehicle, equipment, labor or service for the personal convenience or the private advantage of himself or any other person, except as otherwise allowed by law; 
                  (3)  Participating in the deliberation of or voting on any matter involving his financial or personal interest; 
                  (4)  Engaging in private employment with, or rendering services for, any private person who has business transactions with the city, unless the has made full public disclosure of the nature and extent of such employment or services; 
                  (5)  Appearing on behalf of any private person, other than himself, before any public body in the city; 
                  (6)  Accepting any gift, whether in the form of money, thing, favor, loan or promise, that would not be offered or given to him if he were not an official or employee; 
                  (7)  Disclosing any confidential information concerning any official or employee, or any other person, or any property or governmental affairs of the city, without prior formal authorization of the governing body; 
                  (8)  Using or permitting the use of confidential information to advance the financial or personal interest of himself or any other person; 
                  (9)  Appointing or voting for the appointment of any person in such public official's immediate family. "Immediate family" is hereby defined to mean spouse, children, grandchildren, parents, siblings, uncles, aunts, nieces, nephews, first cousins, spouse's children, spouse's parents, spouse's siblings, spouse's uncles and/or aunts, spouse's nieces and/or nephews, and spouse's first cousins. 
                  (b)  Hearings and determinations. Upon the sworn complaint of any person alleging facts which, if true, would constitute a violation of this section, the council shall conduct a public hearing in accordance with all of the requirements of due process of law, and, in written findings of fact and conclusions based thereon, make a determination concerning the propriety of the conduct of the officers or employee in question. 
                  (Ord. No. 2014-1, § (b), 2-10-2014) 
                  State Law reference— Code of ethics for public officials and employees, O.C.G.A. § 45-10-1 et seq. 
                  Sec. 2-3. - Administrative policy and procedures. 
                  (a)  Officers. Each officer shall perform all duties required of his office by state law, the Charter, and this Code, and such other duties not in conflict therewith as may be required by the mayor. 
                  (b)  Department heads. All department heads shall: 
                  (1)  Be immediately responsible to the mayor for the effective administration of their respective departments and all activities assigned thereto; 
                  (2)  Keep informed as to the latest practices in their particular field and inaugurate, with the approval of the mayor, such new practices as appear to be of benefit to the service and to the public; 
                  (3)  Establish and maintain a system of filing and indexing records and reports in sufficient detail to furnish all information necessary for proper control of departmental activities and to form a basis for the periodic reports to the mayor; 
                  (4)  Have power, when authorized by the mayor, to appoint and remove, subject to personnel regulations, all subordinates under him; and 
                  (5)  Be responsible for the proper maintenance of all city property and equipment used in their respective departments. 
                  (c)  Departments. Each department shall cooperate with every other department and shall furnish, upon the direction of the mayor, any other department such service, labor and materials as may be requisitioned by the head of each department, as its own facilities permit. 
                  (d)  Operation of administrative service. All units in the administrative service shall: 
                  (1)  Office hours. Be open between the hours as determined by council from time to time. 
                  (2)  Daily deposit. Make deposits of any monies received directly from the public. 
                  (3)  Payment of monies. Pay out monies belonging to the city only in the manner prescribed herein. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-103) 
                  Sec. 2-4. - Oaths. 
                  All officers and employees required by charter or some other provision of law to take an oath shall, before entering upon the discharge of their respective duties, take and subscribe the following oath before an officer authorized by law to administer oaths: 
                  I, ____________ , do solemnly swear that I will support the Constitution of the United States, the Constitution of Georgia, the Charter and Ordinances of the City of Ellenton; and that I will, to the best of my ability, faithfully perform the duties of the office of ____________ during my continuance therein, so help me God. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-104) 
                  Sec. 2-5. - Bonds. 
                  Except as otherwise provided by law, the mayor and council may require any department head, city official or employee, before entering upon the discharge of his duties, to give good and sufficient bond in any amount decided by the mayor and council. Said bond shall be payable to the city for the faithful performance of said duties and to secure against corruption, malfeasance, misappropriations or unlawful expenditures in office. Said surety bonds shall be obtained from a surety company licensed to do business in the state and approved by the mayor and council. The premiums thereon shall be paid by the city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-105) 
                  Sec. 2-6. - Compensation. 
                  Each officer and employee of the city shall receive such compensation as may be provided from time to time by resolution. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-106) 
                  Secs. 2-7—2-30. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - LEGISLATIVE AUTHORITY 

                  Sec. 2-31. - Qualifications for office. 
                  Any person who is a bona fide resident and qualified voter of the city and who (see Charter section 2.11) shall be eligible to the office of mayor or councilmember. Should the mayor or any councilmember cease to be a bona fide resident of the city during his term of office, such office shall thereby become vacant. All candidates must be able to read and write. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-202) 
                  Sec. 2-32. - Vacancies. 
                  In case of a vacancy in the office of mayor or councilmember, from forfeiture of office, death, removal or any cause whatsoever, such vacancy shall be filled by appointment of the city council or those remaining pursuant to the Charter. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-203) 
                  Sec. 2-33. - Meetings. 
                  The city council shall hold regular meetings on the second Monday of each month at 7:00 p.m. unless otherwise ordered by the council, provided that the mayor may convene the council whenever, in his opinion, the public business requires it, and he shall do so upon the application of three members of the city council. All meetings at which official actions are to be taken shall be open to the public. 
                  (1)  Notice. Notice of any special or called meeting shall be given to all councilmembers by the city clerk. 
                  (2)  Duty to attend. It shall be the duty of each member of the city council to attend each meeting of the city council, unless he is prevented by some unavoidable circumstance. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-204) 
                  Sec. 2-34. - Standing committees. 
                  The following may be the standing committees of the city council: 
                  (1)  Finance. 
                  (2)  Fire. 
                  (3)  Health and sanitation. 
                  (4)  Licenses. 
                  (5)  Police. 
                  (6)  Public works and property. 
                  (7)  Recreation. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-205) 
                  Sec. 2-35. - Rules for the conduct of business. 
                  (a)  Call to order. All meetings of the council shall be open to the public. The mayor, or, in his absence, the mayor pro tempore, shall take the chair at the hour appointed for any regular, adjourned, special, or called meeting; and shall immediately call the council to order. 
                  (b)  Roll call. Before proceeding with the business of the council, the city clerk or his deputy shall call the roll of the members, and the names of those present shall be entered in the minutes. 
                  (c)  Quorum. A majority of all the members elected to the council shall constitute a quorum at any regular or special meeting of the council. 
                  (d)  Order of business. The business of the council shall be taken up for consideration and disposition in the following order: 
                  (1)  Call to order by presiding officer. 
                  (2)  Roll call. 
                  (3)  Approval of minutes of previous meeting. 
                  (4)  Petitions and communications. 
                  (5)  Reports of standing committees. 
                  (6)  Reports of special committees. 
                  (7)  Unfinished business. 
                  (8)  New business. 
                  (9)  Adjournment. 
                  (e)  Reading of minutes. Unless a reading of the minutes of a council meeting is requested by a councilmember, such minutes may be approved without a reading if the city clerk has previously furnished each member with a copy thereof. 
                  (f)  Reports by committees. 
                  (1)  Any business coming before the city council concerning the subject matter of which any standing or special committee has jurisdiction, may be referred to the proper committee for investigation and report. It shall be the duty of each standing or special committee, whenever required by the mayor or by the city council, or any member of the city council, to examine any matter referred to such committee, and make a report thereof at the next regular meeting of the city council, or show good cause why no report is made. Such reports shall not be in writing unless so directed by the presiding officer. 
                  (2)  Each standing committee shall examine into the condition of the matters within its jurisdiction, and make such reports and recommendations from time to time as may be necessary. 
                  (g)  Limitations on addressing council. Any person not a member of city council who desires to address the council shall first secure the permission of the presiding officer so to do, and then shall step up in front of the rail, give his name and address in an audible tone of voice for the record, and direct his remarks to the council as a body rather than to any particular member, limiting such remarks to 30 minutes unless additional time is granted by council. 
                  (h)  Ordinances, resolutions and contracts. All ordinances, resolutions and contracts of the city shall be prepared, approved, introduced and adopted in the following manner: 
                  (1)  Preparation. All ordinances may be prepared by a city attorney. No ordinance shall be prepared for presentation to the council unless ordered by a majority vote of the council, requested in writing by the mayor, or prepared by a city attorney on his own initiative. 
                  (2)  Administrative staff approval. All ordinances, resolutions and contract documents may before presentation to the council, have been approved as to form and legality by a city attorney or his authorized representative, and shall have been examined and approved for administration by the mayor or his authorized representative, where there are substantive matters of administration involved. All such instruments shall have first been referred to the head of the department under whose jurisdiction the administration of the subject matter of the ordinance, resolution or contract document would devolve and be approved by said department head; provided, however, that if approval is not given, then the same shall be returned to the mayor with a written memorandum of the reasons why such approval is withheld. In the event the questioned instrument is not redrafted to meet a department head objection, or objection is not withdrawn and approval in writing given, then the mayor shall so advise the council and give the reasons advanced by the department head for withholding approval. 
                  (3)  Introduction and adoption. 
                  a.  Ordinances, resolutions, and other matters or subjects requiring action by the council must be introduced and sponsored by a member of the council, except that the mayor or city attorney may present ordinances, resolutions and other matters or subjects to the council, and any councilmember may assume sponsorship thereof by moving that such ordinances, resolutions, matters or subjects be adopted. 
                  b.  All ordinances shall have one reading. 
                  c.  No ordinance shall relate to more than one subject, which shall be clearly expressed in its title, and no ordinance, or section thereof, shall be amended or repealed unless the new ordinance contains the title of the ordinance or section amended or repealed, and, when practicable, all ordinances shall be introduced as amendments to this Code. 
                  d.  An ordinance, resolution or contract shall be deemed adopted or approved when it receives the affirmative vote of a majority of the whole council. 
                  (4)  Effective date. No ordinance shall take effect until five days after the date of its publication, except that an ordinance passed by a majority plus one of the whole membership of the council, designated therein as a public emergency ordinance necessary for the protection of public health, public safety, public property or the public peace, may be made effective upon adoption. 
                  (i)  Recording vote. Whenever any member shall request it the yeas and nays of the members present shall be recorded on the minutes on any question taken. 
                  (j)  Questions of order. The presiding officer shall decide all questions of order, but any councilmember who is dissatisfied with the decision may appeal to the city council. 
                  (k)  Elections. All elections by the city council shall be by ballot, and a majority vote of the whole council shall be necessary to an election. 
                  (l)  Executive session. The city council may, at any time, upon call therefor by the presiding officer or upon motion duly carried by a councilmember, meet in executive session. Attendance at such sessions shall be limited to the mayor and members of council and such invitees as shall be invited with the unanimous consent of the mayor and council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-206) 
                  Sec. 2-36. - Legislative functions. 
                  The city council shall exercise the legislative functions of the city, and may pass any ordinance or resolution that it deems best for the government of the city in the manner set forth in this chapter, provided that the same is not in conflict with the Charter of the city or the laws of the state. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-207) 
                  Secs. 2-37—2-60. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - MAYOR 

                  Sec. 2-61. - Election. 
                  The mayor shall be elected for a four-year term and the councilmembers shall be elected for four-year overlapping terms, and each elected officer shall serve until his successor is elected and qualified. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-201) 
                  Sec. 2-62. - General authority. 
                  The mayor shall be the chief executive and administrative officer of the city government, shall enforce the laws of the city and shall require the faithful performance of all administrative duties. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-301) 
                  Sec. 2-63. - Duties. 
                  The mayor shall have the following duties: 
                  (1)  Presiding at meetings. The mayor shall preside at all meetings of the city council, but the mayor shall not be allowed to vote at such meetings except in the case of a tie vote by the council on any question. 
                  (2)  Appointment of standing committees. The mayor shall appoint at the first meeting each year, or as soon thereafter as expedient, standing committees for that year; but the mayor may at any time alter the committees and make such changes as the interest of the city may require. 
                  (3)  Appointment and dismissal of officers and employees. The mayor shall appoint by and with the advice and consent of the city council, all officers and employees of the city whose election or appointment is not otherwise provided for and to dismiss, suspend and discipline for cause all officers and employees under his control. 
                  (4)  Preparation of annual report. The mayor shall prepare and present to the council an annual report of the city's affairs including a summary of reports of department heads, and such other reports as the council shall require. 
                  (5)  Executing legal documents. The mayor shall sign and execute all contracts, deeds and bonds of the city duly authorized by the mayor and council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-302) 
                  Sec. 2-64. - Powers. 
                  The mayor shall have the following powers: 
                  (1)  Rule making. The mayor shall have the power to prescribe such rules and regulations as may be deemed necessary or expedient for the conduct of administrative agencies subject to his authority, and to revoke, suspend or amend any rule or regulation of the administrative service by whomever prescribed. 
                  (2)  Investigation. The mayor shall have the power to investigate and to examine or inquire into, either by himself or by any officer or person designated for the purpose by him, the affairs or operation of any department, including the power to employ consultants and professional counsel when so authorized by the council to aid in such investigations, examinations or inquiries. 
                  (3)  Overriding. The mayor shall have the power to set aside any action taken by a department head and to supersede him in the functions of his office. 
                  (4)  Delegation. The mayor shall have the power to direct any department to perform the work for any other department, and to authorize any department head or officer responsible to him to appoint and remove subordinates serving under such person. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-303) 
                  Sec. 2-65. - Acting mayor. 
                  In the event of a vacancy in the office of mayor and mayor pro tem, the council may appoint one of its members as acting mayor and another one of its members as acting mayor pro tem to serve until the vacancy is filled at a regular or special election as provided by law. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-305) 
                  Secs. 2-66—2-88. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE IV. - CITY CLERK/TREASURER 

                  Sec. 2-89. - Hire. 
                  The city council shall hire a city clerk/treasurer. Once hired, the city clerk/treasurer shall continue in office until terminated or removed by the city council or until resignation by the city clerk/treasurer. 
                  (Ord. No. 2014-1, § (a), 2-10-2014) 
                  Editor's note— Ord. No. 2014-1, § (a), adopted Feb. 10, 2014, repealed the former § 2-89, and enacted a new section as set out herein. The former § 2-89 pertained to the election of a city clerk/treasurer and derived from Prior Code, § 3-401. 
                  Sec. 2-90. - Term of office. 
                  The city clerk shall be appointed by the mayor and council subject to removal for cause, and until his successor is elected and qualified. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-402) 
                  Sec. 2-91. - Bond. 
                  Before entering upon the duties of his office, the city clerk/treasurer shall give a good and sufficient bond, payable to the city council, such bond to be fixed and approved by the city council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-403) 
                  Sec. 2-92. - Duties as city clerk. 
                  The city clerk/treasurer shall have the following duties in his capacity as city clerk: 
                  (1)  To attend all meetings of the city council; 
                  (2)  To keep correct and full minutes of the proceedings of city council, together with all ordinances and resolutions passed by it, in a properly indexed book or register kept for that purpose; 
                  (3)  To receive all applications or petitions made to the city and to place them before the mayor and city council at the meeting of council next succeeding the receipt thereof; 
                  (4)  To issue all licenses, and keep a record thereof, and all badges and permits authorized by the council; 
                  (5)  To attend all sessions of the municipal court; 
                  (6)  To keep an execution docket, in which he shall enter the names of all persons tried and fined by the municipal court, the nature of the offense, date of trial, amount of fine, and return of the police officer thereon; 
                  (7)  To issue all summons, processes and subpoenas to witnesses that may be necessary in the enforcement of this Code or other rules, regulations and ordinances of the city council; 
                  (8)  To be the custodian of the city seal and affix its impression on documents whenever required; 
                  (9)  To carefully preserve the records and documents belonging to the city which are not assigned to the custody of some other office, and to maintain a proper index to all such records and documents so that ready access thereto and use thereof may be had. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-404) 
                  State Law reference— Georgia Records Act, O.C.G.A. § 50-18-90 et seq. 
                  Sec. 2-93. - Duties as city treasurer. 
                  The city clerk/treasurer shall have the following duties in his capacity as city treasurer: 
                  (1)  To receive all money due the city council, including taxes, and pay out the same only upon orders passed by the city council and signed by the mayor, or, in his absence, the mayor pro tempore; 
                  (2)  To keep a book of accounts showing all money received on behalf of the city and the source and disposition thereof, which book shall be open for inspection by the public and city councilmembers; 
                  (3)  To keep such other records and accounts as may be required by statute or ordinance; 
                  (4)  To furnish the council with quarterly statements detailing all receipts and payments of funds for the quarter. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-405) 
                  Secs. 2-94—2-114. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE V. - OFFICERS AND EMPLOYEES 

                  Sec. 2-115. - City attorney. 
                  (a)  Appointment and qualifications. The city attorney may be appointed by the city council and shall serve until a successor is appointed and has qualified. No person shall be so appointed unless he is a member in good standing of the State Bar of Georgia and has been actively engaged in the practice of law for at least five years preceding his appointment. 
                  (b)  Oath. Before entering upon the duties of his office, the city attorney shall take the oath prescribed by this Code for city officers. 
                  (c)  Powers and duties. The city attorney shall be the legal advisor and representative of the city and in such capacity shall: 
                  (1)  Advise the council or its committees or any city officer, when thereto requested, upon all legal questions arising in the conduct of city business. 
                  (2)  Prepare or revise ordinances when so requested by the council or any committee thereof, and keep the Code of Ordinances of the city up-to-date and properly indexed. 
                  (3)  Give his opinion upon any legal matter or question submitted to him by the council, or any of its committees, or by any city officer. 
                  (4)  Attend meetings of the city council when requested to do so. 
                  (5)  Prepare for execution all contracts and instruments to which the city is a party and approve, as to form, all bonds required to be submitted to the city. 
                  (6)  Prepare, when authorized by the council, all charges and complaints against, and appear in the municipal court in the prosecution of every person charged with the violation of this Code or of a city ordinance or of any regulations adopted under authority of the Charter, and see to the full enforcement of all judgments or decrees rendered or entered in favor of the city. 
                  (7)  Defend any and all suits and actions at law or equity brought against the city, unless otherwise directed by city council. 
                  (8)  Make immediate report to the mayor and council of the outcome of any litigation in which the city has an interest. 
                  (9)  Make an annual report to the mayor and council of all pending litigation in which the city has an interest and the status thereof. 
                  (10)  Have the power to adjust, settle, compromise or submit to arbitration any action, causes of action, accounts, debts, claims, demands, disputes and matters in favor of or against the city or in which the city is concerned as debtor or creditor, now existing or which may hereafter arise may be resolved by the specific approval of the mayor and the council. 
                  (11)  Keep complete and accurate records of the following, which records shall forever remain the property of the city: 
                  a.  All suits in which the city had or has an interest, giving the names of the parties, the nature of the actions, the disposition of the case or its status, if pending, and the briefs of counsel. 
                  b.  All written opinions prepared by the city attorney and all certificates or abstracts of titles furnished by him to the city, or any department or official thereof. 
                  (12)  Render such other legal services as may be required by the mayor or council. 
                  (d)  Compensation. The city attorney may submit to the council a monthly bill for his services, itemizing the type of work performed for the city and the number of hours engaged in each type of work during the month. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-501) 
                  Sec. 2-116. - Personnel policy manual adopted. 
                  The city employee personnel policy manual is hereby adopted by reference and incorporated herein as if fully set out. 
                  (Prior Code, § 3-502) 
                  Secs. 2-117—2-145. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE VI. - ELECTIONS[2] 
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (2) --- 
                  State Law reference— Georgia Election Code, O.C.G.A. § 21-2-1 et seq. 

                  DIVISION 1. - GENERALLY 

                  Sec. 2-146. - Adoption of state rules and regulations. 
                  The rules and regulations promulgated by the state election board which pertain to municipal elections, together with the provisions of the Georgia Election Code contained in O.C.G.A. § 21-2-1 et seq., are hereby adopted as the rules, regulations and provisions that shall govern the conduct of municipal general and special elections in this city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-101) 
                  Sec. 2-147. - Expenses. 
                  Such funds as are necessary for the conduct of elections and for the performance of the duties that are specified by this article shall be budgeted and appropriated annually, and from time to time. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-102) 
                  Sec. 2-148. - Registrars and deputy registrars. 
                  (a)  Appointment. 
                  (1)  Registrars and deputy registrars shall be appointed by the mayor and council, as necessary, and shall serve at the pleasure of same. One such appointee shall be designated as chief registrar, and such person shall serve as the chief administrative officer of the board of registrars and shall generally supervise and direct the administration of the affairs of said board. 
                  (2)  All appointments shall be entered on the minutes of the council meeting at which they are made. 
                  (b)  Qualifications. Registrars and deputy registrars shall be electors of the municipality and shall be able to read, write and speak the English language. Such appointees, while serving as registrars or deputy registrars or within a period of six months after so serving, shall not be eligible to any nomination or office to be voted for at a primary or election. 
                  (c)  Oath. Prior to entering upon his duties, each registrar and deputy registrar shall swear to faithfully perform his duties, such oath to be administered by an officer authorized by law to administer the oath. 
                  (d)  Term of office. Registrars shall be appointed by the mayor and council and shall serve until their successors are appointed and qualified, except in the event of resignation or removal as hereinafter provided. 
                  (e)  Powers. The registrars and deputy registrars shall exercise those powers and duties and shall be subject to such regulations as are set forth in the Georgia Election Code, O.C.G.A. § 21-2-1 et seq. 
                  (f)  Resignation or removal. Any registrar or deputy registrar shall have the right to resign at any time by submitting a resignation to the mayor and council. The mayor and council shall have the right at any time to remove one or more of such registrars for cause after notice and hearing. If any registrar resigns or is removed for cause, his duties and authority as such shall terminate instanter. In the event of the death, resignation or removal of a registrar or deputy registrar, the mayor and council shall appoint a successor who shall serve out the unexpired term. Each such appointment shall be entered on the minutes of the council meeting at which the appointment is made. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-201) 
                  Sec. 2-149. - Qualification fees. 
                  The qualification fee for candidates filing a notice of candidacy for any office in any general or special election for mayor and for councilmembers shall be in amounts as established by the city council from time to time, as shown on the city fee schedule. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-302) 
                  Editor's note— Candidate filing fees, even if reasonable, may be subject to federal Constitutional attack on equal protection grounds if payment of the fee is the sole means of access to the ballot. See Jenness v. Little, 306 F. Supp. 925 (1968) Jenness v. Fortson, 315 F. Supp. 1035 (1970); and Billoch v. Carter, 405 U.S. 134 (1972) 
                  Sec. 2-150. - Campaign financing disclosure. 
                  All candidates for municipal public office shall keep all such records and file all such reports as are required by the Ethics in Government Act, O.C.G.A. § 21-5-1 et seq. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-303) 
                  Sec. 2-151. - Election officials. 
                  (a)  Appointment. The following election officials may be appointed by the mayor and council and shall receive such compensation as is provided by same: 
                  (1)  Municipal election superintendent. 
                  (2)  Chief manager. 
                  (3)  Two assistant managers. 
                  (4)  Clerks, as necessary. 
                  (b)  Qualifications and powers. The municipal election superintendent and all poll officers shall meet such qualifications and exercise all such powers and duties as are provided under state law. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-401) 
                  Sec. 2-152. - Election posts of mayor and council. 
                  (a)  A candidate for mayor shall at the time of qualifying designate that such candidate is seeking the office of Mayor, Post No. 1. The councilmember positions upon the city council shall be designated as Councilmember, Post No. 2; Councilmember, Post No. 3; Councilmember, Post No. 4; Councilmember, Post No. 5; and Councilmember, Post No. 6. A candidate for any position as councilmember shall at the time of qualifying designate by post number the position that candidate is seeking. The candidate for mayor and the candidate for each post who receive a majority of the votes cast for the respective office shall be elected thereto. 
                  (b)  A candidate for councilmember may qualify for any one of the posts for which councilmembers are to be elected. The election of mayor and councilmembers shall be conducted in the manner hereinafter prescribed for regular elections. In the event of a tie vote for any aforementioned position, the winner shall be determined by a special election. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-402) 
                  Sec. 2-153. - Polling places. 
                  The city council shall select and fix the polling place within the precinct. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-403) 
                  Secs. 2-154—2-174. - Reserved. 
                  DIVISION 2. - IMPEACHMENT AND REMOVAL 

                  Sec. 2-175. - Grounds for removal. 
                  The mayor or any councilmember shall be subject to removal from office for any one or more of the following causes: 
                  (1)  Incompetence, misfeasance or malfeasance in office; 
                  (2)  Conviction of a crime involving moral turpitude; 
                  (3)  Failure at any time to possess any of the qualifications of office as provided by charter or by law; 
                  (4)  Willful violation of any express prohibition of the municipal Charter; 
                  (5)  Abandonment of office or neglect to perform the duties thereof; or 
                  (6)  Failure for any other cause to perform the duties of office as required by charter or by law. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-501) 
                  Sec. 2-176. - Procedure for removal. 
                  Removal of any elected officer from office shall be brought about in the following manner: 
                  (1)  Initiation of proceedings. Any person desiring to initiate removal proceedings against an elected officer shall file a complaint in writing with the city clerk, which complaint shall set forth distinctly the alleged grounds for removal and the names of witnesses, if any. 
                  (2)  Preliminary hearing. Immediately upon receipt of a complaint as provided for in the preceding subsection, the city clerk shall notify the mayor (except in case of his own impeachment, when the clerk shall then notify the mayor pro tem), who shall call a meeting of the city council. If, at such meeting, a majority of the council shall deem the complaint sufficient to authorize an investigation, they shall call, at the earliest date practicable, a meeting for the trial of the officer complained of. 
                  (3)  Articles of impeachment and notice. If a trial is ordered as provided in the preceding subsection, it shall be the duty of the city attorney to immediately draw articles of impeachment, based upon the complaint, which shall be filed with the city clerk at least five days prior to the date set for the trial. Upon receipt of the articles of impeachment, it shall be the duty of the city clerk to attach to the same a notice directed to the party complained against, which notice shall specify the time and place of the trial and command the appearance of the accused. The notice and copy shall be served upon the accused by a police officer at least seven days before the date of trial. 
                  (4)  Conduct of trial. The trial shall be conducted in the manner employed by the courts, both the council and the accused having the right to introduce evidence and be represented by counsel, it being the duty of the city attorney to act as prosecuting officer in such trials. 
                  (5)  Verdict and judgment. The council shall render a verdict upon each article of impeachment, to be followed by the judgment, which shall be entered by the city attorney upon the original articles and signed by the mayor or other presiding officer. Such verdict and judgment shall be spread upon the minutes of the council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-502) 
                  Sec. 2-177. - Appeal of decision. 
                  Any officer removed from office by the action of city council as provided in section 2-176 shall have the right of appeal from the decision of the council to the superior court of the county in which city hall is located. Such appeal shall be governed by the same rules as govern appeals to the superior court from the court of probate. 
                  (Prior Code, § 2-503) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="4">
               <head>Chapter 4 - ANIMALS[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Authority to exercise animal control, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III(a)(3); dogs generally, O.C.G.A. § 4-8-1 et seq.; Georgia Animal Protection Act, O.C.G.A. § 4-11-1 et seq. 

                  Sec. 4-1. - Livestock regulation. 
                  (a)  Term defined. The term "livestock" means all animals of the equine, bovine, or swine class, including goats, sheep, mules, horses, hogs, cattle, and other grazing animals. 
                  (b)  Livestock prohibited; exception. It shall be unlawful for any person to keep within the city any livestock; except under the following conditions: 
                  (1)  Any housing or enclosure used by such animals or fowl shall be well drained, free from accumulations of animal excrement and objectionable odors, and otherwise clean and sanitary. Animal excrement shall be disposed of in a manner approved by health officer, animal control officer, or the city council. 
                  (2)  Livestock must have adequate space provided, no less than one acre of land. 
                  (3)  Animals and fowl shall be kept at minimum distances deemed reasonable and necessary by the health officer, animal control officer, or the city council. 
                  (4)  All animals or fowl, except dogs in areas where confinement of dogs under the rabies control regulations does not apply. 
                  (5)  In the case of bona fide licensed pet shops, veterinary hospitals, stockyards, poultry houses and similar commercial establishments, the health officer, animal control officer, or the city council may modify the requirements of this section where undue hardship would result from their strict enforcement. 
                  (c)  Impoundment; penalty. Provided any of said livestock shall be found to be illegally kept within the city, notification shall be made to the livestock's owner, and this owner shall be ordered to correct his violation of said livestock ordinance. Any livestock found running at large shall be impounded. The owner of the livestock thus impounded shall be summoned to municipal court, and in order to regain his livestock, the owner shall be subject to a fine set by the council from time to time. This fine may also be imposed on the owner if his livestock shall be found to be kept within the city in violation of said livestock ordinance. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-101) 
                  Sec. 4-2. - Dog control. 
                  (a)  Rabies inoculation tag required by state law. All dog owners within the city must abide by the rabies inoculation tag requirements pursuant to state law. 
                  (b)  Dogs as nuisances; penalties. 
                  (1)  The mayor, city council or code enforcer, upon formal complaint by any citizen concerning a dog, shall conduct an investigation to determine whether said dog constitutes a nuisance. 
                  (2)  Standards upon which the mayor and council may deem that a dog constitutes a nuisance shall include, but not be limited to, the following: 
                  a.  Molests passersby or passing vehicles; 
                  b.  Attacks other animals; 
                  c.  Trespasses on school grounds, recreational areas or parks; 
                  d.  Is repeatedly at large; 
                  e.  Damages private or public property; 
                  f.  Barks, whines or howls in an excessive, continuous or untimely fashion; or 
                  g.  Constitutes a nuisance as the term is defined by the state law. 
                  (3)  If the mayor, city council or code enforcer determines that a dog does constitute a nuisance, the owner of said dog shall be so notified and shall be given a reasonable period of time during which to correct those conditions constituting the nuisance. Failure to correct said nuisance within a period of time considered reasonable by the mayor and council shall be punishable as prescribed in section 1-9. 
                  (4)  An exception to the prohibition in this section shall be permitted for hunting dogs, which will be allowed to run in wooded areas where permitted by the owner of the property, during hunting season, as established by federal and/or state laws and regulations. All hunting dogs shall bear tags containing the owner's name, address and phone number, and shall be vaccinated in accordance with state rabies shot regulations. All hunting dogs used in hunting games shall be properly supervised. 
                  (c)  General restraint requirements. 
                  (1)  The owner of any animal shall keep such animal in a condition of restraint to prevent such animal from being at large. An animal is under restraint within the meaning of this section if it is: 
                  a.  Controlled by a leash; 
                  b.  On or within a vehicle being driven or parked on the streets, provided the animal must be confined within any open vehicle by leash; or 
                  c.  Confined on the owner's property at all times as defined by state law. 
                  (2)  No animal shall be confined on the owner's premises by a leash less than ten feet in length, except by a leash which is a free running line. The length of the leash shall not be long enough to allow the animal to leave the premises of the owner. The term "free running line" means one which is attached or is secured by a swivel or other device which will turn and remain free running when wrapped around some object. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-102; Prior Ord., § 31-102) 
                  State Law reference— Control of rabies, O.C.G.A. § 31-19-1 et seq.; inoculation of animals against rabies, O.C.G.A. § 31-19-5. 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="6">
               <head>Chapter 6 - BUILDING REGULATIONS AND CONSTRUCTION CODES[1] </head>
               <p>                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Authority to adopt technical codes, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III(a)(12); construction standards generally, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-1 et seq.; minimum state construction codes, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-25; enforcement of minimum state construction codes, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-26. 

                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 6-1. - Definitions. 
                  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this chapter, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Building official or building inspector means the qualified building official or qualified building inspector as designated by the city. 
                  Sec. 6-2. - Enforcement. 
                  (a)  The building official is hereby authorized to enforce within the city the provisions of this chapter and the state minimum codes adopted herein. 
                  (b)  The building official is further authorized to render interpretations of this Code and the adopted state codes and to adopt policies and procedures in order to clarify the application of their provisions. Such interpretations, policies and procedures shall be in compliance with the intent and purpose of this chapter. Such policies and procedures shall not have the force and effect of law and shall not have the effect of waiving requirements specifically provided for in this Code or in the adopted state codes. 
                  Sec. 6-3. - References to officials in adopted technical codes. 
                  Where reference is made to the duties of certain officials named within the technical codes which are adopted by reference in this chapter, then that designated official of the city who has duties corresponding to those of the named official in said technical code shall be deemed to be the responsible official insofar as enforcing the provisions of that technical code are concerned. 
                  Sec. 6-4. - State minimum technical codes. 
                  (a)  The following technical and building codes, as adopted and amended by the state department of community affairs, are adopted by reference and incorporated into this Code as if set out fully herein, including the administration and appendix chapters: 
                  (1)  International Building Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2007. 
                  (2)  International Residential Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2007 and 2008. 
                  (3)  International Fire Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2008. 
                  (4)  International Plumbing Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2007 and 2008. 
                  (5)  International Mechanical Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2007 and 2008. 
                  (6)  International Fuel Gas Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2007 and 2008. 
                  (7)  National Electrical Code, 2005 edition, with Georgia Amendments 2006. 
                  (8)  International Energy Conservation Code, 2006 edition, with Georgia Supplements and Amendments 2008. 
                  (9)  International Property Maintenance Code, 2003 edition, as amended. 
                  (10)  International Existing Building Code, 2006 edition. 
                  (11)  CABO One- and Two-Family Dwelling Code, appendix G, as the Standard Swimming Pool Code. 
                  (b)  If any of the publications listed in subsection (a) of this section are adopted as a state minimum code pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 8-2-20 et seq., then the edition adopted by the state shall control. If any of the publications listed in subsection (a) of this section are less stringent than the state minimum codes promulgated pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 8-2-20 et seq., then the state minimum code shall control. 
                  (c)  A copy of each of the publications listed in subsection (a) of this section, as adopted by the state, is filed in the office of the city clerk and available for review by the public. The same is adopted and incorporated as fully as if set out at length herein, and from the date on which this section shall take effect, the provisions thereof shall be controlling within the corporate limits of the city. 
                  Sec. 6-5. - Statewide application. 
                  (a)  The city shall enforce those state minimum standard codes which have statewide application. 
                  (b)  The provisions of this chapter shall apply to the construction, erection, installation, alteration, demolition, repair, relocation, replacement, addition to, use or maintenance of buildings or structures, plumbing, mechanical, gas, and electrical systems within the city. Any and all requirements of this chapter shall expressly include any and all technical codes as amended by the city pursuant to this chapter. 
                  Secs. 6-6—6-28. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - MANUFACTURED HOMES AND MOBILE HOMES[2] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (2) --- 
                  State Law reference— Standards and requirements for installation, licensing of manufactured homes and mobile homes, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-110 et seq.; the Uniform Standards Code for Manufactured Homes Act, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-130 et seq. 

                  Sec. 6-29. - Manufactured/mobile home regulations. 
                  (a)  Requirements. Each manufactured home and mobile home in the city shall meet the standards established by the county health authorities, as approved by the mayor and city council. 
                  (b)  Relocation permit/fee. Every manufactured home or mobile home must first obtain a city and county relocation permit before relocating to the city. Before setting up or relocating a mobile home within the corporate limits of the city, for any purpose, the owner of said home shall first obtain a relocation permit and pay to the city clerk a non-refundable relocation fee. The amount of the fee shall be as established by the mayor and city council, from time to time. 
                  (c)  Registration. Every mobile home located within the city must have a valid county registration sticker attached to it before city utilities shall be connected. 
                  (d)  Specifications. All mobile homes manufactured after 1976 shall meet all HUD House Specifications. No mobile home manufactured previous to 1976 and not meeting the standards established under the National Manufactured Housing and Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974, 42 USC 5401 et. seq. will be allowed to be located within the city. Mobile camping trailers shall not be classified as a single family home and therefore will not be considered as such. 
                  (e)  Lot size and approval. Only one single-family home shall be allowed per lot. Each single family home must meet the minimum lot set-back requirements of ten feet side-yard, 15 feet back-yard and 35 feet front-yard set-back from the public right-of-way. Each lot shall be approved by the city building inspector and the county health officer as meeting the lot size and specifications. 
                  (f)  In city home relocation inspections. Each home proposed for relocating within the city shall first be inspected and receive approval of the city building inspector before locating within the city as well as all other requirements as specified in this section. 
                  (g)  Installation. Each home shall be set-up and installed by a state-licensed contractor as approved by the city's building inspector. Each home shall have appropriate skirting installed before an official certificate of occupancy is issued and before permanent municipal utilities are connected. 
                  (h)  Storage. No manufactured home or mobile home shall be moved into the city for the purpose of storage on any private lot. 
                  (i)  Posting of address. Each home being allowed to locate in the city must have an approved address posted so as to be visible from the public right-of-way. 
                  (j)  Offense; penalty. It is hereby declared to be an offense for any person, owner, agent, or tenant to violate any provision of this section. Each day a violation is continued shall constitute a separate offense. Upon conviction, unless otherwise provided by state law, the judge may impose a fine not exceeding $1,000.00 and imprisonment in the county jail not exceeding six months, and work on the city streets and public works not exceeding 30 days. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-107; Ord. No. 2017-2, 3-13-2017) 
                  Sec. 6-30. - Definitions. 
                  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Manufactured home means a structure, transportable in one or more sections, which, in the traveling mode, is eight body feet or more in width or 40 body feet or more in length or, when erected on site, is 320 or more square feet and which is built on a permanent chassis and designed to be used as a dwelling with or without a permanent foundation when connected to the required utilities and includes the plumbing, heating, air conditioning, and electrical systems contained therein; except that the term "manufactured home" includes any structure which meets all the requirements of this definition except the size requirements and with respect to which the manufacturer voluntarily files a certification required by the secretary of housing and urban development and complies with the standards established under the National Manufactured Housing Construction and Safety Standards Act of 1974, 42 USC 5401 et seq. 
                  Mobile home means a structure, transportable in one or more sections, which, in the traveling mode, is eight body feet or more in width or 40 body feet or more in length or, when erected on site, is 320 or more square feet and which is built on a permanent chassis and designed to be used as a dwelling with or without a permanent foundation when connected to the required utilities and includes the plumbing, heating, air conditioning, and electrical systems contained therein and manufactured prior to June 15, 1976. 
                  Sec. 6-31. - Septic tank. 
                  The design and/or construction of a septic tank for anyone setting up a new manufactured home or mobile home or house with septic tank shall equal or exceed minimum design and construction criteria established by the department of human resources of the state, as published in the current manual for on-site sewage management systems, and the rules, regulations, and standards as established by the county board of health. If not, the city cannot give them any water. 
                  (Mo. of 7-6-1988) 
                  Sec. 6-32. - Permit required. 
                  Moving manufactured homes or mobile homes in the city requires that the mover obtain a permit as issued by the city. The cost for a permit to move a manufactured home or mobile home in the city shall be in an amount as established by the city council, from time to time. 
                  (Mo. of 6-3-2002) 
                  Sec. 6-33. - Emergencies. 
                  Whenever the code enforcement officer finds that an emergency exists which requires immediate action to protect the public health, including violations of any of the applicable rules and regulations of the city, county or state health authorities, such officer may without notice or hearing issue an order reciting the existence of such an emergency and requiring that such action be taken as such officer may deem necessary to meet the emergency, including the suspension of the permit. Notwithstanding any other provisions of this article, such order shall be effective immediately. Any person to whom such an order is directed shall comply therewith immediately, but upon petition to the city council, such person shall be afforded a hearing as soon as possible. 
                  Secs. 6-34—6-55. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - PROPERTY NUMBERING 

                  Sec. 6-56. - Uniform numbering system. 
                  A uniform system of numbering properties and buildings as described by a map and material filed in the office of the city clerk is hereby adopted. The map and system description as filed is hereby adopted and made a part of this article. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(1), § 1) 
                  Sec. 6-57. - Assignment of numbers. 
                  (a)  All properties, lots and parcels of land within the corporate limits of the city shall hereafter be identified by reference to the uniform numbering system adopted herein, except that all existing number identification of buildings or lots or parcels not in conformity with the system adopted herein shall be changed in not more than six months from the adoption of this article so as to conform. 
                  (b)  Each principal building shall bear the number assigned to it by the administrator of the system as herein provided and where more than one business or family dwelling unit occupies a single structure shall bear, in addition to the basic number assigned to the structure, the supplementary numerals or letters assigned to them. 
                  (c)  Numerals and letters indicating the official property number designation shall be posted at the entrance for which the designated number has been assigned in such a manner as to provide an unobstructed sighting from the street on which the building is located. 
                  (d)  No person, agency or business shall adopt, assign, display or cite any number other than that assigned as provided herein for the purpose of property identification or for the purpose of designating location of property. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(1), § 2) 
                  Sec. 6-58. - Administration. 
                  (a)  The compliance officer shall be responsible for implementing and maintaining the numbering system as adopted by this article including the supplementary documents referred to herein. 
                  (b)  The compliance officer or his designee shall assign and maintain a record of all property numbers for the city. 
                  (c)  The compliance officer or his designee may make available to public agencies such as those responsible for emergency services, tax officials, and post office such part of the records of property number assignments as may be required to accomplish a public purpose. 
                  (d)  The compliance officer shall issue one set of numerals for each property number assigned, including any future legally accomplished subdivision such as the establishment of apartments. The maintenance of the numbers is the responsibility of the property owner, except that, at the discretion of the city clerk, numerals may be replaced if they have been destroyed by an act of God. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(1), § 4) 
                  Secs. 6-59—6-76. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE IV. - ESTABLISHING STREET NAMES 

                  Sec. 6-77. - Established. 
                  There is hereby established an official system of street names in the city as shown on the map entitled Base Map—City of Ellenton, as produced by the Southwest Georgia Regional Development Center, which is made a part of this article. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(2), § 1) 
                  Sec. 6-78. - Existing street names unchanged. 
                  Names of streets in the city shall remain as shown on said map unless officially changed by ordinance. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(2), § 2) 
                  Sec. 6-79. - New street names. 
                  No new streets shall be accepted by the city and no municipal improvements made therein until such streets have been named. If they are extensions of existing streets, the existing names shall be continued if not an extension. Names recorded may not duplicate or closely approximate street names already assigned. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(2), § 3) 
                  Sec. 6-80. - Copy of street name map. 
                  The city clerk shall be responsible for the maintenance of the system of street names. He or his designee shall maintain a copy of the map adopted by this article and shall record thereon all changes made by ordinance or new assignments accepted by subdivision platting or other legal means. From time to time he shall cause to be made revisions to the official map to include all official changes made up to the date of revision, which date is also to be clearly recorded thereon. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(2), § 4) 
                  Sec. 6-81. - Street naming. 
                  (a)  Berrien Street is the dividing line north and south while Baker Street is the east-west dividing line for a system that separates the city for street designation purposes into quadrants. 
                  (b)  Baker Street north of Berrien Street will be known as North Baker Street, south of Berrien Street will be known as South Baker Street. 
                  (c)  Street designations will require these directional prefixes to be complete. 
                  (d)  Streets east of North Baker and north of Berrien Street will be known by a basic name plus the designation northeast or N.E. 
                  (e)  Streets west of North Baker Street and north of Berrien Street will be known by a basic name plus the designation of northwest or N.W. 
                  (f)  Streets south of Berrien Street and east of South Baker Street will carry a basic name plus the designation southeast or S.E. 
                  (g)  Streets west of South Baker and south of Berrien Street will carry a basic name, plus the designation southwest or S.W. 
                  (h)  A map with all complete street names reflecting the official system described in subsections (a) through (g) of this section carrying the date on which it and the implementing ordinance were adopted is to be kept in the custody of the city clerk or his designee as the official street naming map of the city. 
                  (i)  A copy of said map is to be available to the city clerk or his designee to be used as a work sheet on which to record street additions and street name changes. At the city clerk's discretion, he should have the original, official map revised periodically to record all marked up additions and changes and this revised map and copies of it then used in lieu of those previously in use. Care should be taken to ensure that the date of revision is recorded on the face of any official revision. 
                  (j)  Streets that change from one predominant direction (such as east-west) to another predominant direction (north-south) will be assigned a different name for that segment that deviates in directions. This provision is necessary so that the numbering system can be used without confusion. 
                  (Ord. of 7-12-2004(3)) 
                  Secs. 6-82—6-107. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE V. - HIGH-EFFICIENCY PLUMBING FIXTURES[3] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (3) --- 
                  State Law reference— Water efficiency requirements, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-1 et seq.; flow-rate restrictions on plumbing fixtures, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-3. 

                  Sec. 6-108. - Definitions. 
                  (a)  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Commercial means any type of building other than residential. 
                  Residential means any building or unit of a building intended for occupancy as a dwelling but shall not include a hotel or motel. 
                  (b)  The definitions set forth in O.C.G.A. § 8-2-3 (high-efficiency plumbing fixtures) shall be effective as definitions of the words, terms and phrases used in this article. All words, terms and phrases used herein, other than those specifically defined elsewhere in this article, shall have the respective meanings ascribed to them in O.C.G.A. § 8-2-3, and shall have the same scope and effect that the same words, terms and phrases have where used in O.C.G.A. § 8-2-3. 
                  Sec. 6-109. - Residential building construction. 
                  (a)  No plumbing fixture shall be installed which does not meet the standards listed in this section or the state minimum plumbing code, whichever is stricter. This includes all plumbing fixtures installed in newly constructed buildings or when replacing plumbing fixtures during remodeling or renovation of existing buildings. 
                  (b)  The standards are as follows: 
                  (1)  A water closet or toilet that: 
                  a.  Is a dual flush water closet that meets the following standards: 
                  1.  The average flush volume of two reduced flushes and one full flush may not exceed 1.28 gallons; 
                  2.  The toilet meets the performance, testing, and labeling requirements prescribed by the following standards, as applicable: 
                  (i)  American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.19.2-2008; and 
                  (ii)  American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.19.14-2006 Six-Liter Water Closets Equipped with a Dual Flushing Device; and 
                  3.  The toilet is listed to the WaterSense™ Tank-Type High Efficiency Toilet Specification; or 
                  b.  Is a single flush water closet, including gravity, pressure assisted, and electro-hydraulic tank types, that meets the following standards: 
                  1.  The average flush volume may not exceed 1.28 gallons; 
                  2.  The toilet must meet the performance, testing, and labeling requirements prescribed by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.192/CSA B45.1 or A112.19.14; and 
                  3.  The toilet must be listed to the WaterSense™ Tank-Type High Efficiency Toilet Specification; 
                  (2)  A shower head that allows a flow of no more than an average of 2.5 gallons of water per minute at 60 pounds per square inch of pressure; 
                  (3)  A urinal and associated flush valve that: 
                  a.  Uses no more than 0.5 gallons of water per flush; 
                  b.  Meets the performance, testing, and labeling requirements prescribed by the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.19.2/CSA B45.1; 
                  c.  For flushing urinals, meets all WaterSense™ specifications for flushing urinals; and 
                  d.  Where non-water urinals are employed, complies with American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.19.3/CSA B45.4 or American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.19.19/CSA B45.4. Non-water urinals shall be cleaned and maintained in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions after installation. Where non-water urinals are installed, they shall have a water distribution line roughed-in to the urinal location at a minimum height of 56 inches (1,422 mm) to allow for the installation of an approved backflow prevention device in the event of a retrofit. Such water distribution lines shall be installed with shutoff valves located as close as possible to the distributing main to prevent the creation of dead ends. Where non-water urinals are installed, a minimum of one water-supplied fixture rated at a minimum of one water supply fixture unit shall be installed upstream on the same drain line to facilitate drain line flow and rinsing; 
                  (4)  A lavatory faucet or lavatory replacement aerator that allows a flow of no more than 1.5 gallons of water per minute at a pressure of 60 pounds per square inch in accordance with American Society of Mechanical Engineers Standard A112.18.1/CSA B.125.1 and listed to the WaterSense™ High-Efficiency Lavatory Faucet Specification; and 
                  (5)  A kitchen faucet or kitchen replacement aerator that allows a flow of no more than 2.0 gallons of water per minute. 
                  Sec. 6-110. - Commercial building construction. 
                  There shall be no construction of any commercial building initiated within the city for any commercial building of any type which does not meet the requirements of this article. 
                  Sec. 6-111. - Exemptions. 
                  (a)  New construction and the repair or renovation of an existing building shall be exempt from the requirements of this article when: 
                  (1)  The repair or renovation of the existing building does not include the replacement of the plumbing or sewage system servicing toilets, faucets or showerheads within such existing buildings; 
                  (2)  Such plumbing or sewage system within such existing building, because of its capacity, design, or installation, would not function properly if the toilets, faucets or showerheads required by this chapter were installed; 
                  (3)  Such system is a well or gravity flow from a spring and is owned privately by an individual for use in such individual's personal residence; or 
                  (4)  Units to be installed are: 
                  a.  Specifically designed for use by the handicapped; 
                  b.  Specifically designed to withstand unusual abuse or installation in a penal institution; or 
                  c.  Specifically designed as toilets for juveniles. 
                  (b)  The owner, or his agent, of a building undergoing new construction or repair or renovation who is entitled to an exemption as specified in subsection (a)(2), (3) or (4) of this section shall obtain the exemption by applying at the office of the building official. A fee, as determined by the city council and shown on the city fee schedule, shall be charged for the inspection and issuance of such exemption. 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="8">
               <head>Chapter 8 - BUSINESS REGULATION AND LICENSING[1] </head>
               <p>                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Local taxes and fees, Ga. Const. art. IX, § IV, ¶ I; limitation on expanding the power of municipal regulation over any business activity regulated by the public service commission, O.C.G.A. § 36-35-6(a)(5); business and occupation taxes, O.C.G.A. § 48-13-5 et seq. 

                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 8-1. - Penalties. 
                  Any person who shall conduct a business or occupation without having obtained a license therefor as required by this chapter, or who shall violate any other provisions of this chapter, shall, upon conviction therefor, be punished according to the general penalties described in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-111) 
                  Sec. 8-2. - Applications. 
                  Every person required to procure a license under the provisions of this chapter or any ordinance or law of this municipality shall submit an application for such license to the city clerk, which application shall conform to the requirements of this section. 
                  (1)  Form. Each application shall be a written statement upon forms provided by the city clerk. 
                  (2)  Contents. Each application shall contain the following information: 
                  a.  Name and home address of the applicant if an individual, or home office address if a corporation or partnership; 
                  b.  Place where the proposed business is to be located; 
                  c.  Kind of business to be carried on; 
                  d.  Name and home addresses of the partners, if a partnership; 
                  e.  Names and home addresses of the officers and directors, if a corporation; 
                  f.  Complete record of all arrests and convictions against the applicant and every partner, officer or director of the applicant for violations of any and all laws and ordinances of the city, state or federal government; 
                  g.  Such additional information which the city clerk or council may find reasonably necessary to the fair administration of this chapter. 
                  (3)  Verification. Each application shall be sworn to by the applicant if an individual, or by a partner if a partnership, or by an officer if a corporation. 
                  (4)  Payment of fee. Each application shall be accompanied by the amount of the fee chargeable for such license. 
                  a.  Penalty. Provided the license fee is not paid by February 15 of each year, a penalty of ten percent will be added to the fee. 
                  b.  Issuance of receipts. The city clerk shall issue a receipt to the applicant for the amount of the fee tendered with the application for a license, provided that such receipt shall not be construed as approval of the application, nor shall it entitle or authorize the applicant to open or maintain any business contrary to the provisions of this chapter. 
                  c.  Rebate of fee. Upon the disapproval of any application for which a fee has been submitted under the provisions of this chapter, the city clerk shall refund such fee, provided that the applicant is not otherwise indebted to the city. 
                  (5)  Confidentiality of information. All information furnished or secured under the authority of this section shall be kept in strict confidence by the city clerk, shall not be subject to public inspection and shall be utilized solely by the officers of the city responsible for administering the provisions of this chapter. 
                  (6)  False statements. False statements on any application for a license shall be grounds for immediate revocation of such license. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-101) 
                  Sec. 8-3. - Procedure for issuance. 
                  (a)  Review by city officers. If any provision of this chapter or any licensing ordinance of the city provides for the review of an application for a license by a city officer designated therein, the city clerk shall forward a copy of the application to such officer within 48 hours of the time of receipt of the application. The officer charged with the duty of reviewing the application shall make a recommendation thereon, favorable or otherwise, and shall return such recommendation to the city clerk within seven days after receiving a copy of the application. 
                  (b)  Council consideration. Upon the receipt of the recommendation of the reviewing officer as hereinabove provided, or upon the receipt of the application if no reviewing officer is designated, the city clerk shall forward such recommendation and/or application to the city council for consideration and action at its next regular scheduled public meeting. 
                  (c)  Limitation on issuance. No license shall be issued to any applicant whose place of business is not in full compliance with all minimum standard building codes adopted by this municipality. 
                  (d)  Issuance of license. Upon the express approval of the city council, the city clerk shall issue a new business license to the applicant therefor, which license shall state the nature of the business authorized and bear the date of issuance and the signatures of the mayor and city clerk. 
                  (e)  Council discretion. The granting of a business license under the provisions of this chapter shall be deemed a privilege only, and nothing herein contained shall be construed as granting any person whose business is subject to municipal regulation any legal right to engage in such business. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-102) 
                  Sec. 8-4. - Display of license. 
                  It shall be the duty of any person conducting a licensed business in the city to keep his license posted in a conspicuous place on the premises used for such business at all times. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-103) 
                  Sec. 8-5. - Inspections. 
                  (a)  Search of premises. Whenever inspections of the premises used for or in connection with the operation of a licensed business or occupation are provided for or required by ordinance, or are reasonably necessary to secure compensation with any ordinance provision or to detect violations thereof, it shall be the duty of the licensee, or the person in charge of the premises to be inspected, to admit thereto for the purpose of making the inspection any officer or employee of the city who is authorized or directed to make such inspection at any reasonable time that admission is requested. 
                  (b)  Testing of material. Whenever an analysis of any commodity or material is reasonably necessary to secure conformance with any ordinance provision or to detect violations thereof, it shall be the duty of the licensee of the municipality whose business is governed by such provision to give to any authorized officer or employee of the city requesting the same sufficient samples of such material or commodity for such analysis upon request. 
                  (c)  Refusal to allow inspection. In addition to any other penalty which may be provided, the mayor may revoke the license of any licensed proprietor of a licensed business in the city who refuses to permit any officer or employee who is authorized to make such inspection or take such sample to make the inspection, or take an adequate sample of the said commodity, or who interferes with such officer or employee while in the performance of his duty in making such inspection; provided that no license shall be revoked for such cause unless written demand is made upon the licensee or person in charge of the premises, in the name of the city, stating that such inspection or sample is desired at the time it is sought to make the inspection or obtain the sample. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-104) 
                  Sec. 8-6. - Termination and renewal of licenses. 
                  (a)  All annual licenses shall terminate on the last day of the fiscal year of the city when no provision to the contrary is made. 
                  (b)  Each licensee shall make a written application for renewal on forms supplied by the city clerk on or before December 15 of each calendar year, which application shall contain substantially the same information as the initial application and be accompanied by all required fees. 
                  (c)  An applicant for renewal of a license shall be entitled to a refund of fees tendered if he withdraws his application for renewal prior to final action on the same by the city council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-105) 
                  Sec. 8-7. - Revocation, suspension, etc. 
                  The city council, after affording the licensee notice of the charges and opportunity to be heard with respect to any revocation proceedings may, if it finds this chapter to have been violated by the licensee, his agent or employee, revoke such license in its entirety, suspend the same for a specified period of time, place the licensee on probation or place other conditions thereon as the council may deem necessary. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-106) 
                  Sec. 8-8. - Change of location. 
                  In the absence of any provision to the contrary, the location of any licensed business or occupation may be changed, provided ten days' notice thereof is given to the city clerk, and provided that all building and zoning requirements are complied with. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-107) 
                  Sec. 8-9. - Transfer of licenses. 
                  All licenses shall be personal to the licensee to whom issued, but in cases where the ownership is changed and both the name and location of the licensed business or occupation are maintained, the mayor and city council may allow the license to be transferred. Application must be made to the city clerk for transference of said license, and upon registration of the change, a fee in an amount as established by the city council from time to time must be paid. The license shall be transferable only one time. Transferred license shall not be valid for longer than a 90-day period. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-108) 
                  Sec. 8-10. - Branch offices. 
                  For the purposes of this chapter, each branch establishment or location wherein a representative of the owner is employed and is authorized to transact business for such owner shall be deemed a separate place of business for which a separate license shall be required, provided that warehouses and distributing plants used in connection with and incidental to a business licensed under the provisions of this chapter shall not be deemed to be separate places of business or branch offices. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-109) 
                  Sec. 8-11. - Joint license. 
                  A person engaged in two or more businesses at the same location shall be required to obtain separate licenses for conducting each of such businesses for which a license is required. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-110) 
                  Secs. 8-12—8-40. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - BUSINESSES REGULATED 

                  Sec. 8-41. - Peddlers and itinerant merchants. 
                  (a)  License required. Each peddler and itinerant merchant, as such terms are defined herein, who does business within the city shall be required to obtain a license from the city clerk in the manner specified in this chapter. 
                  (b)  Definitions. The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this section, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this subsection, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Itinerant merchant means any person, firm or corporation, whether as owner, agent, consignee or employee, whether a resident of the city or not, who engages in a temporary business of selling and delivering goods, wares and merchandise within the city, and who, in furtherance of such purpose, hires, leases, uses or occupies any building, structure, motor vehicle, tent, railroad box car, or boat; public room in hotels, lodginghouses, apartments, shops; or any street, alley or other place within the city, for the exhibition and sale of such goods, wares and merchandise, either privately or at public auction. 
                  Peddler means and includes any person, whether a resident of this city or not, traveling by foot, wagon, automotive vehicle, or any other type of conveyance, from place to place, from house to house, or from street to street, carrying, conveying or transporting goods, wares, merchandise, meats, fish, vegetables, fruits, garden truck, farm products or provisions, offering and exposing the same for sale or who, without traveling from place to place, shall sell or offer the same for sale from a wagon, automotive vehicle, railroad car, or other vehicle or conveyance. 
                  (c)  Fee established. The business license fee for each peddler and itinerant merchant doing business in the city shall be in an amount as established by the city council from time to time. 
                  (d)  Duty to exhibit. All persons obtaining a license under the provisions of this section shall be required to exhibit such license at the request of any citizen. 
                  (e)  Loud noises and speaking devices. No licensee under this section, nor anyone on his behalf, shall shout, make any outcry, blow a horn, ring a bell or use any other sound device including any loudspeaking radio or amplifying system upon any of the streets, alleys, parks or other public places of the city or upon any private premises in the city where sound of sufficient volume is emitted or produced therefrom capable of being plainly heard upon the streets, avenues, alleys or parks or other public places, for the purpose of attracting attention to any goods, wares or merchandise which such licensee proposes to sell. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-207; Ord. of 10-7-2007, § B) 
                  State Law reference— Peddlers and itinerant traders, O.C.G.A. § 43-32-1 et seq.; exception from local peddler or itinerant vendor licensing requirements for persons selling agricultural products, O.C.G.A. § 43-32-6; transient merchants, O.C.G.A. § 43-46-1 et seq. 
                  Sec. 8-42. - Charitable solicitors. 
                  (a)  Registration required. Any person who wishes to solicit donations or contributions for, or to sell any insignia or novelty on the streets of the city on behalf of, or under the sponsorship of, any charitable, religious, social, patriotic or civic club or organization shall be required to register such solicitation or sale with the city clerk at least 48 hours in advance of such event and to obtain a permit therefor. 
                  (b)  Form of registration. The registration required by this section shall be in writing, shall be signed by the chief officer of the club or organization, and shall contain the following information: 
                  (1)  The name and object of the charitable, religious, social, patriotic or civic club or organization conducting or sponsoring the solicitation or sale to which the registration relates. 
                  (2)  The days on which the solicitation or sale will take place. 
                  (3)  The object for which the funds to be derived from the solicitation or sale will be utilized. 
                  (4)  The name and address of the chief officer of the club or organization conducting or sponsoring the solicitation or sale. 
                  (c)  Exemption. This section shall not apply to any locally established organization or church operated exclusively for charitable or religious purposes if the solicitations are in the form of collections or contributions at the regular assemblies of any such organization or church. 
                  (d)  Duty to exhibit. Charitable solicitors shall be required to exhibit their permits at the request of any citizen. 
                  (e)  Unlawful acts. It shall be unlawful for any person to execute a registration which contains any false statement, and it shall be unlawful for any person to solicit donations or contributions or sell any insignia or novelty on the streets of the city purportedly in behalf of or under the sponsorship of any charitable, religious, social, patriotic or civic club or organization which does not in fact exist. 
                  (f)  Permit fee. The permit fee for charitable solicitations or sales will be set by council from time to time. 
                  (Prior Code, § 32-208) 
                  Secs. 8-43—8-72. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - OCCUPATION TAX 

                  Sec. 8-73. - Tax required; requirement for business dealings in the city. 
                  Each person engaged in any business, trade, profession or occupation in the city, whether with a location in city or, in the case of an out-of-state business with no location in the state, exerting substantial efforts within the state pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 48-13-7, shall pay an occupation tax for said business, trade, profession, or occupation; which tax and any applicable registration shall be displayed in a conspicuous place in the place of business, if the taxpayer has a permanent business location in the city. If the taxpayer has no permanent business location in the city, such business tax registration shall be shown to the city clerk or to any police officer of the city, upon request. 
                  (Ord. of 10-7-2007, § C) 
                  Sec. 8-74. - Definitions. 
                  (a)  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Employee. 
                  (1)  Except as otherwise provided in subsection (2) of this definition, the term "employee" means an individual whose work is performed under the direction and supervision of an employer who withholds FICA, federal income tax, or state income tax from such individual's compensation or whose employer issues to such individual for purposes of documenting compensation a form IRS W-2 but not a form IRS 1099. 
                  (2)  The term "employee" also means an individual who performs work under the direction and supervision of one business or practitioner in accordance with the terms of a contract or agreement with another business which recruits such individual is an employee of the business or practitioner that issues to such individual for purposes of documenting compensation a form IRS W-2. 
                  (3)  With respect to the taxation of businesses or practitioners with no location or office in the state, "employees" may only include employees working substantially in the state. 
                  (b)  The definitions set forth in O.C.G.A. § 48-13-5 (specific, business, and occupation taxes—definitions), shall be effective as definitions of the words, terms and phrases used in this chapter. All words, terms and phrases used herein, other than those specifically defined elsewhere in this chapter, shall have the respective meanings ascribed to them in O.C.G.A. § 48-13-5, and shall have the same scope and effect that the same words, terms and phrases have where used in O.C.G.A. § 48-13-5. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 1) 
                  Sec. 8-75. - Tax levied on businesses and practitioners; computation of full-time employees; tax schedule; limitations. 
                  (a)  An occupation tax based upon number of employees is levied upon businesses and practitioners of professions and occupations if the business or practitioner: 
                  (1)  Has one or more locations or offices within the corporate limits of the city; or 
                  (2)  Is an out-of-state business or practitioner with no location or office in the city; but: 
                  a.  Has employees or agents engaging in substantial efforts to solicit business or serve customers or clients within the corporate limits of the city; or 
                  b.  Owns personal or real property that generates income and is located within the corporate limits of the city. 
                  (b)  The occupation tax is levied based on the number of employees of the business or practitioner as computed on a full-time basis or full-time position equivalent basis, provided that, for the purposes of this computation, an employee who works 40 hours or more weekly shall be considered a full-time employee and that the average weekly hours of employees who work less than 40 hours weekly shall be added and such sum shall be divided by 40 to produce full-time position equivalents. 
                  (c)  The occupation tax is levied in accordance with the following schedule: 

                   
                  (d)  A business or practitioner that has locations in the state and is subject to occupation tax by more than one local government in the state shall only be subject to occupation tax by the city for the number of employees who are employed within the corporate limits of the city. 
                  (1)  This limitation shall only apply when the business or practitioner has provided to the city satisfactory proof of current payment of the occupation tax of the other local governments. 
                  (2)  If an employee works for the same business in more than one jurisdiction, the city or county in which the employee works the most in a calendar year may count the employee for occupation tax purposes. 
                  (e)  A business or practitioner with no location or office in the state shall only be required to pay occupation tax to the local government in the state where the largest dollar volume of business is done or service is performed by such business or practitioner. 
                  (1)  This limitation shall only apply when the business or practitioner has provided to the city satisfactory proof of as to the applicability of this subsection. 
                  (2)  If a business or practitioner with no location or office in the state provides to the city proof of payment of a local business or occupation tax in another state that purports to tax the business's or practitioner's sales or services in this state, then the business or practitioner shall be exempt from this occupation tax. 
                  (f)  Real estate brokers shall be subject to occupation tax pursuant to this article only if they maintain a principal or branch office in the city. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 2) 
                  Sec. 8-76. - Exemptions. 
                  (a)  No occupation tax shall be levied on the following: 
                  (1)  Disabled veterans of any war or armed conflict in which any branch of the United States armed forces was involved, whether under United States command or otherwise; 
                  (2)  Blind persons; 
                  (3)  Veterans of peace-time service in the United States armed forces who have a physical disability which was incurred during that service; 
                  (4)  Any practitioner whose office is maintained by and who is employed in practice exclusively by the United States, the state, a municipality or county of the state, or instrumentality of the United States, the state, or a municipality or county of the state; 
                  (5)  Any state or local authority, nonprofit organization, or vendor acting pursuant to a contract with a tax-exempt agricultural fair; 
                  (6)  Real estate brokers, except at the principal or branch office of a real estate broker; 
                  (7)  Motor vehicles required to be registered with the public service commission; 
                  (8)  Those businesses regulated by the state public service commission; 
                  (9)  Those electrical service businesses organized under O.C.G.A. § 46-3-1 et seq.; 
                  (10)  Any farm operation for the production from or on the land of agricultural products, but not including any agribusiness; 
                  (11)  Nonprofit, agricultural product cooperative marketing associations pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 2-10-105; 
                  (12)  Motor common carriers pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 46-7-15; 
                  (13)  Persons purchasing guano, meats, meal, flour, bran, cottonseed, or cottonseed meal and hulls in carload lots for distribution among the purchasers for use and not sale pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 48-5-355; 
                  (14)  Pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 48-5-356 for persons selling or introducing into the city agricultural products or livestock, including animal products, raised in this state when the sale and introduction are made by the producer of the product and the sale is made within 90 days of the introduction of the product into the city; 
                  (15)  Depository institutions pursuant to O.C.G.A. § 48-6-93; or 
                  (16)  Any business on which the levy of such occupation tax is prohibited by the laws of the state or the United States. 
                  (b)  The exemptions and limitations contained in this article shall not be construed to repeal or otherwise affect in any way any franchise fees, business taxes or other fees or taxes otherwise allowed by law. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 3) 
                  Sec. 8-77. - Evidence of state registration, when required. 
                  Each person who is licensed under O.C.G.A. title 43 by the examining boards of the secretary of state's office shall provide evidence of proper and current state licensure before any city occupation tax certificate may be issued. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 4) 
                  Sec. 8-78. - Evidence of qualification required, if applicable. 
                  (a)  Any business required to obtain health permits, bonds, certificates of qualification, certificates of competency or any other regulatory matter shall first, before the issuance of an occupation tax certificate, show evidence of such qualification. 
                  (b)  Any business required to submit an annual application for continuance of the business shall do so before the registration is issued. 
                  (c)  The city shall not impose registration or other regulatory requirements on attorneys authorized to practice law by the state bar. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 5) 
                  Sec. 8-79. - Filing returns; other information required or requested. 
                  (a)  On or before February 15 of each year, an individual, business or practitioner subject to this occupation tax article shall file with the city clerk, on a form approved by and available from the city, a signed return attesting to the number of employees of such business or practitioner during the calendar year. 
                  (b)  Individuals, businesses and practitioners doing business in the city shall submit to the city clerk or make available to the city within 30 days such information as may be required or requested by the city to determine the applicability and amount of the occupation tax or to facilitate levying or collecting the occupation tax. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 6) 
                  Sec. 8-80. - Date due; penalty and interest. 
                  (a)  Any occupation tax due pursuant to this article shall be due and payable annually within 30 days of January 15 for the preceding calendar year. Occupation taxes imposed on businesses commencing after January 15 will be due and payable 30 days following the commencement of business. If a person commences business on or after July 1, the occupation tax for the remaining portion of the year shall be 50 percent of the tax imposed for the entire year. 
                  (b)  If a business or practitioner commences business in the city on or after July 1 in any year, the occupation tax for the remaining portion of the year shall be 50 percent of the tax imposed for the entire year. 
                  (c)  Payment of an occupation tax shall not be required prior to the commencement of business, nor shall it in any other manner act as a precondition on the practice of law. 
                  (d)  Any individual, business or practitioner subject to any occupation tax imposed by this article which is unpaid by March 15 shall be subject to a penalty of ten percent of the tax or fee due, and interest at the rate of 1.5 percent per month. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 7) 
                  Sec. 8-81. - Enforcement; violations. 
                  (a)  It is the duty of the city clerk to administer and enforce the provisions of this article, and to perform all functions necessary to administer and enforce this article. The city clerk may issue executions against individuals, businesses and practitioners for taxes or fees which are due and owing, any penalty imposed by section 8-80, and any interest imposed by section 8-80. 
                  (b)  The city clerk shall issue executions against individuals, businesses and practitioners for taxes or fees which are due and owing, penalties, or interest. Such executions shall bear interest at the rate authorized by O.C.G.A. § 48-2-40 or, if such statute should be repealed or ruled invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, one percent per month. The lien shall cover the property of the individual, business or practitioner liable for payment of the delinquent occupation tax and become fixed as of the date and time the occupation tax became delinquent. The execution shall be levied by the sheriff, his deputy or designee of the city upon property of the delinquent tax or fee payer located in the city and sufficient property shall be advertised and sold to pay the amount of the execution, including penalty, interest and costs. All other proceedings in relation thereto shall be as provided by this Code and the Charter of the city and the laws of the state. The defendants at execution shall have the rights of defense, by affidavit of illegality of the tax or otherwise as provided by the Charter of the city and the laws of the state in regard to tax executions. 
                  (c)  Individuals, businesses and practitioners who fail or refuse to pay any occupation tax charged pursuant to this article shall be subject to a fine, to be imposed by court of competent jurisdiction over enforcement of the city's ordinances, not more than $500.00, that may be enforced by the contempt power of the court. 
                  (d)  Individuals, businesses and practitioners who fail or refuse to make a timely or truthful tax return or make available truthful and accurate information the city requests or requires for determining applicability or amount of occupation tax or for levying or collecting such occupation tax shall be subject to a penalty of ten percent of the taxes due. 
                  (e)  All persons subject to the occupation tax imposed by this article shall be required to file for and pay such tax or fee. For failure to do so, any officers or agents soliciting for or obtaining business for such person, business or practitioner shall be subject to the same penalty as other persons, businesses or practitioners who fail to make a return for or pay the applicable occupation tax. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 8) 
                  Sec. 8-82. - Public hearings. 
                  The city shall conduct at least one public hearing before adopting any ordinance or resolution which will increase the occupation tax rate specified in section 8-75(c). 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 9) 
                  Sec. 8-83. - Prior ordinance. 
                  To the extent that any occupation taxes are owed pursuant to an ordinance passed prior to the ordinance from which this article is derived, such amounts remain due and owing and the provisions of that prior ordinance will remain in effect with respect to such unpaid occupation taxes until such time as they are paid in full. 
                  (Ord. of 10-6-2008, § 10) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="9">
               <head>Chapter 9 - CURFEW FOR JUVENILES </head>
               <p>                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 9-1. - Findings; public purpose. 
                  (a)  The council hereby finds and determines as a matter of fact that the city is facing a mounting crisis caused by crimes committed by juvenile offenders and crimes committed against juvenile victims. 
                  (b)  The council further finds that persons under the age of 17 are particularly susceptible by their lack of maturity and experience to participate in unlawful activities and/or to place themselves in situations which would increase their potential for victimization. 
                  (c)  The council further finds that a need exists for increased parental responsibility and parental control over the activities of juveniles. 
                  (d)  The council further finds that this criminal activity, both individually and collectively, presents a clear and present danger to the citizenry and to public order and safety and that an ordinance establishing a curfew for persons under the age of 17 and parental responsibility for violations of said curfew is an appropriate method of addressing the foregoing issues. 
                  (e)  Therefore, the purpose of this article is to: 
                  (1)  Protect juveniles themselves and other citizens from the dangers of crimes which occur on sidewalks, streets, and in public and semipublic places during late night and early morning hours; 
                  (2)  Decrease the amount of criminal activity committed by juveniles; and, 
                  (3)  Promote and enhance parental control over juveniles. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-2. - Definitions. 
                  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning; 
                  Curfew hours means the hours of 11:00 p.m. until 6:00 a.m. the following day from Sunday to Thursday, and the hours of 12:00 midnight to 6:00 a.m. on Saturday and Sunday mornings. 
                  Emergency means an unforeseen circumstance or combination of circumstances or the resulting state or any situation requiring immediate action to care for or prevent serious bodily injury or loss of life. This term includes, but is not limited to, a fire, natural disaster, or automobile accident. 
                  Juvenile means any person under 17 years of age. 
                  Law enforcement officer means a certified law enforcement officer of any rank who is a duly sworn officer of the Colquitt County Sheriffs Department. 
                  Legal guardian means a person or agency appointed by a court to act in the role of a parent. 
                  Operator means any individual, firm, association, partnership or corporation operating, managing or conducting any licensed business establishment. The term includes the members or partners of an association or partnership and the officers of a corporation. 
                  Parent means the natural parent, adoptive parent, stepparent or custodial grandparent of a juvenile. 
                  Public place means any property owned or controlled by the city or other governmental entity to which the general public has access and a right to resort for business, recreation, entertainment, or other lawful purpose, including sidewalks, streets and highways. 
                  Semipublic place means any privately owned or privately operated real property, including any structure thereon, to which the general public is invited or has the legal right of access and a right to resort for business, recreation, or entertainment, or other lawful purpose, such as, but not limited to, any store, shop, restaurant, lounge, theater, parking lot, alley, road, shopping center, bowling alley, pool hall, any vacant lot, or any vacant or abandoned building. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-3. - Curfew established. 
                  It shall be unlawful and a violation of this article for any juvenile to linger or stay or to congregate, loiter, wander, or stroll in any public place or semipublic place within the city, either on foot or in or upon any conveyance being driven, ridden, or parked thereon, during curfew hours. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-4. - Exceptions. 
                  The provisions of this article shall not apply if the juvenile is: 
                  (1)  Accompanied by a parent or legal guardian. 
                  (2)  Engaged in lawful employment or traveling between such employment and his current residence without any detour. 
                  (3)  Engaged in interstate travel. 
                  (4)  Attending an official school, religious, or other recreational activity supervised by adults and sponsored by the city, the county, the Colquitt County School Board, a civic organization, or other similar entity that takes responsibility for the juvenile, or going to or returning home from, without any detour, any activity previously described in this subsection. 
                  (5)  On the curtilage of his residence or on the sidewalk abutting his residence. 
                  (6)  Attending or returning to his current resident from a specific activity at a public place or semipublic place which is open to the general public and supervised by adults; provided further that such activity begins no later than 10:00 p.m.; provided further that the juvenile has in his immediate possession written permission from his parent or legal guardian authorizing the child to attend or engage in that specific activity. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-5. - Responsibility of parents. 
                  It shall be unlawful for the parent, legal guardian, or other adult person having the care, control or custody of a juvenile to permit or by insufficient control to allow such juvenile to violate and/or to remain in violation of the provisions of section 9-3 of this article. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-6. - Responsibility of operators. 
                  It shall be unlawful for any operator, owner or any employee managing or conducting any establishment to knowingly allow a juvenile to remain or stay or to congregate, loiter, wander, stroll or play upon the premises of the establishment during curfew hours in violation of the provisions of section 9-3 of this article. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-7. - Notice. 
                  Operators are encouraged but not required to conspicuously display in or about the premises of an establishment a legibly printed notice in substantially the following form: 
                  "IT IS UNLAWFUL FOR A PERSON UNDER THE AGE OF 17 TO REMAIN ON THESE PREMISES BETWEEN THE HOURS OF 11:00 P.M. TO 6:00 A.M. FROM SUNDAY TO THURSDAY AND THE HOURS OF 12:00 MIDNIGHT TO 6:00 A.M. ON SATURDAY AND SUNDAY MORNINGS UNLESS SPECIFICALLY ALLOWED BY LAW." 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-8. - Defenses. 
                  (a)  It shall be a defense to any prosecution under the provisions of section 9-3 of this article that: 
                  (1)  The juvenile was married or had been married or had the disabilities of minority removed by a court of law. 
                  (2)  The juvenile was exercising rights protected by the First Amendment to the United States Constitution and/or Ga. Const. Art. I. 
                  (b)  It shall be a defense to any prosecution under the provisions of section 9-5 of this article that: 
                  (1)  The parent, legal guardian or other adult person having the care, control or custody of a juvenile found to be in violation of this article had reported to the police department that said juvenile was missing from such person's control or custody. 
                  (2)  The parent, legal guardian or other adult person having the care, control or custody of a juvenile court not have known, in the exercise of reasonable care and diligence, of the unlawful acts of such juvenile. 
                  (3)  The juvenile on whose conduct the charge against the parent, legal guardian or other adult person responsible for exercising care, control or custody was exercising rights protected by the First Amendment to the United States Constitution and/or Ga. Const. Art. I. 
                  (c)  It shall be a defense to any prosecution under the provisions of section 9-6 of this article that the owner, operator or employee notified the police department that a juvenile was present on the premises of the establishment during curfew hours and refused to leave after being asked to leave the premises. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
                  Sec. 9-9. - Penalties for violations. 
                  (a)  A juvenile charged for violating section 9-3 of this article shall be referred to the juvenile court of the county for disposition in accordance with the laws of the state. 
                  (b)  Any person found guilty of violating section 9-5 or section 9-6 of this article shall be fined not less than $50.00 nor more than $200.00 for a first conviction and not less than $200.00 nor more than $1,000.00 for any subsequent conviction and/or may be sentenced to complete community service work at the discretion of the Colquitt County Juvenile Court or the State Court of Colquitt County. 
                  (Ord. No. 2018-1, § 1(attch.), 9-17-2018) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="10">
               <head>Chapter 10 - FIRE PREVENTION AND PROTECTION[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Authority to provide police and fire protection, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III(a)(1); regulation of fire and other hazards to persons and property generally, O.C.G.A. § 25-2-1 et seq.; statewide application of International Fire Code, O.C.G.A. § 8-2-25(a). 

                  Sec. 10-1. - Adoption of National Fire Prevention Code. 
                  There is hereby adopted by the mayor and city council, for the purpose of prescribing regulations governing conditions hazardous to life and property from fire or explosion, that certain code known as the NFPA 101, 2000 edition, Life Safety Code, thereof and the whole thereof, except for such portions as may be hereinafter deleted, modified or amended, of which code not less than one copy has been and now is filed in the office of the city clerk, and the same is adopted and incorporated as fully as if set out at length herein, and from the date on which this section shall take effect, the provisions thereof shall be controlling within the corporate limits of the city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 10-101) 
                  Sec. 10-2. - Definitions of terms used in code. 
                  (a)  Wherever the term "chief of the bureau of fire prevention" is used in the Fire Prevention Code, it shall be held to mean the chief of the fire department of the city, and whenever the term "bureau of fire prevention" is used in such code, it shall be held to mean the fire department of the city. 
                  (b)  Wherever the term "corporation counsel" is used in the Fire Prevention Code, it shall be held to mean the city attorney. 
                  (c)  Wherever the term "municipality" is used in the Fire Prevention Code, it shall be held to mean this city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 10-102) 
                  Sec. 10-3. - Penalties. 
                  Any person who shall violate any of the provisions of the Fire Prevention Code or fail to comply therewith, or who shall violate or fail to comply with any order made thereunder, shall for each such failure or violation or noncompliance be punished according to the general penalties described in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 10-106) 
                  Sec. 10-4. - Enforcement. 
                  The Fire Prevention Code adopted herein shall be enforced by the fire chief and such subordinate officers and firefighters of the fire department as are required to effectuate the provisions of said code. 
                  (Prior Code, § 10-104) 
                  Sec. 10-5. - Power to make modifications. 
                  The chief of the fire department shall be authorized to modify any of the provisions of the Fire Prevention Code upon application in writing by the owner or lessee of any property, or his duly authorized agent, when there are practical difficulties in the way of carrying out the strict letter of the code, provided that the spirit of the code shall be observed and the public safety secured. The particulars of such modification when granted or allowed and the decision of the fire chief thereon shall be entered upon the records of the department, and a signed copy shall be forwarded to the applicant. 
                  (Prior Code, § 10-105) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="12">
               <head>Chapter 12 - MUNICIPAL COURT[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Municipal authority to establish, maintain and operate a municipal court, O.C.G.A. § 36-32-1 et seq.; city courts generally, O.C.G.A. § 15-8-1 et seq. 

                  Sec. 12-1. - Scope of jurisdiction. 
                  The municipal court of the city shall try violations of municipal ordinances and shall have the power and authority to impose fines upon persons convicted of said offenses, with the alternative of other punishment allowed by law if such fines are not paid. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-101) 
                  Sec. 12-2. - Appointment and qualifications of judge. 
                  The judge of the municipal court shall be appointed by and shall serve at the pleasure of the city council. No person shall be so appointed unless he is a resident of the judicial circuit in which the court is located. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-102) 
                  State Law reference— Qualifications for municipal court judges, O.C.G.A. § 36-32-1.1. 
                  Sec. 12-3. - Bailiff. 
                  (a)  The bailiff of the municipal court shall be appointed by the mayor, by and with the advice and consent of city council. 
                  (b)  The duties of the bailiff shall consist generally of seeing that the courtroom is in proper condition for sessions of court, assisting in keeping order while court is in session, and doing such other acts of assistance as may be required of him by the judge of the court and the city clerk. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-103) 
                  Sec. 12-4. - Record of cases. 
                  A record of all cases heard in the municipal court for violations of this Code or other municipal ordinances shall be kept in a suitable bound volume by the city clerk. Such record shall contain the name of the defendant, the nature of the offense charged, the final disposition of the case, and the date of final disposition. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-104) 
                  Sec. 12-5. - Service of summons. 
                  Any person charged with violating any city ordinance shall receive notice by service of a summons as herein provided. Such summons may be issued by the city clerk, the building inspector, or any police officer of the city. The summons shall be directed to the accused and shall distinctly state the offense charged, the time and place, as far as practicable, of the offense charged, and the day, hour and place of trial, requiring the accused to appear before the judge of the municipal court to answer the accusation made. Service of the summons shall be made by a police officer of the city by serving the accused personally or by leaving a copy at his most notorious place of abode, except that in the case of a summons issued for violation of laws or ordinances relating to the parking of motor vehicles, such summons may be directed to an unknown person as owner of an automobile designated in the summons and may be served upon such person by leaving a copy in or attached to such automobile. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-105) 
                  Sec. 12-6. - Subpoenas. 
                  The city clerk shall issue subpoenas for the appearance of all witnesses necessary for the prosecution or for the defense in any case pending before the municipal court. All subpoenas shall be served in the same manner as a summons. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-106) 
                  Sec. 12-7. - Failure to obey summons or subpoena. 
                  Any person who fails to appear at the time and place set out in any summons or subpoena served upon him shall be guilty of contempt of court and upon conviction thereof shall be punished for same. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-107) 
                  Sec. 12-8. - Arrest and bond. 
                  When a police officer has arrested any person for violation of any provision of this Code or any municipal ordinance and a trial cannot be had immediately, the officer may take a cash bond not exceeding the maximum fine for the offense or a bond with a good security for the appearance of such person before the judge of the municipal court. If such person fails or refuses to give a bond, the officer may confine him or her in the city jail until a trial can be held, provided that the mayor, in his discretion, may release such person on his own recognizance without security. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-108) 
                  Sec. 12-9. - Forfeiture of bond. 
                  Upon the failure of a person to appear in the municipal court at the time and place fixed by the summons, the judge of said court shall enter a judgment of forfeiture on any cash bond, or, in the case of a security bond, shall pass a rule requiring the principal and surety on such bond to show cause on the date named therein, which date shall not be less than ten days from the passage of such ruling, why they should not be required to pay the amount of said bond. If no sufficient cause is shown, the judge shall enter judgment against the principal and surety for the amount of the forfeited bond and shall direct the city clerk to issue execution thereon. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-109) 
                  Sec. 12-10. - Court costs. 
                  The costs which shall be charged against a defendant in the municipal court in the event of his conviction shall not exceed $100.00, which sum shall be paid into the city treasury. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-110) 
                  Sec. 12-11. - Malicious prosecution. 
                  Whenever the judge of the municipal court, after a fair and full trial, is satisfied that any case was frivolously or maliciously prosecuted, he shall assess the prosecution with the court costs and such punitive damages as he deems appropriate. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-111) 
                  Sec. 12-12. - Collection of fines. 
                  When directed by the judge of the municipal court, the city clerk shall issue executions for fines imposed by said court, including the costs, which executions may be levied upon any goods or chattels, lands or tenements of the person so fined. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-112) 
                  Sec. 12-13. - Appeal. 
                  Appeals from decisions of the municipal court shall be taken to the superior court in the manner provided for appeals from the court of probate. 
                  (Prior Code, § 5-113) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="14">
               <head>Chapter 14 - NUISANCES </head>
               <p>                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 14-1. - Periodic inspection. 
                  It will be made the duty of the officer appointed for the purpose to make frequent examination, especially in the spring, summer and fall months, into the condition of all lots and yards and fences in the city, to see if the same are kept in a clean and healthful condition. If he shall find anything which may become a nuisance, he shall notify the city council or board of health who shall proceed as prescribed for the abatement thereof and for the punishment of the owner, occupant or offender. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-106) 
                  Secs. 14-2—14-20. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - ABANDONED VEHICLES[1] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Abandoned motor vehicles, O.C.G.A. § 40-11-1 et seq. 

                  Sec. 14-21. - Definitions. 
                  The definitions set forth in O.C.G.A. § 40-11-1 (abandoned motor vehicle—definitions) shall be effective as definitions of the words, terms and phrases used in this article. All words, terms and phrases used herein, other than those specifically defined elsewhere in this article, shall have the respective meanings ascribed to them in O.C.G.A. § 40-11-1, and shall have the same scope and effect that the same words, terms and phrases have where used in O.C.G.A. § 40-11-1. 
                  (Prior Code, § 40-11-1) 
                  Sec. 14-22. - Duty of person removing or storing motor vehicle. 
                  (a)  Any person who removes a motor vehicle from public property at the request of a law enforcement officer or stores such vehicle shall, if the owner of the vehicle is not present, seek the identity and address of all known owners of such vehicle from a local law enforcement agency for the jurisdiction in which the remover's or storer's place of business is located, or from the state by direct electronic access as provided through its agencies and authorities, within 72 hours of removal. The local law enforcement agency shall furnish such information to the person removing such vehicle within 72 hours after receipt of such request. 
                  (b)  Any person who removes a motor vehicle from private property at the request of the property owner or stores such vehicle shall, if the owner of the vehicle or some person acting for the owner is not present, notify in writing a local law enforcement agency of the location of the vehicle, the manufacturer's vehicle identification number, license number, model, year, and make of the vehicle within 72 hours of the removal of such vehicle and shall seek from the local law enforcement agency or from the state by direct electronic access as provided through its agencies and authorities the identity and address of the all known owners of such vehicle and any information indicating that such vehicle is a stolen motor vehicle. The local law enforcement agency shall furnish such information to the person removing such vehicle within 72 hours after receipt of such request. 
                  (c)  If any motor vehicle removed under conditions set forth in subsection (a) or (b) of this section is determined to be a stolen motor vehicle, the local law enforcement officer or agency shall notify the Georgia Crime Information Center and the owner, if known, of the location of such motor vehicle within 72 hours after receiving notice that such motor vehicle is a stolen vehicle. 
                  (d)  If any motor vehicle removed under conditions set forth in subsection (a) or (b) of this section is determined not to be a stolen vehicle or is not a vehicle being repaired by a repair facility or is not being stored by an insurance company providing insurance to cover damages to the vehicle, the person removing or storing such motor vehicle shall, within seven calendar days of the day such motor vehicle was removed or one business day after the information is furnished to the remover or storer pursuant to subsection (a) or (b) of this section, whichever is later, notify all owners , if known, by written acknowledgment signed thereby or by certified or registered mail or statutory overnight delivery of the location of such motor vehicle, the fees connected with removal and storage of such motor vehicle, and the fact that such motor vehicle will be deemed abandoned under this chapter unless the owner, security interest holder, or lienholder redeems such motor vehicle within 30 days of the day such vehicle was removed. 
                  (e)  If the owner, security interest holder, or lienholder fails to redeem such motor vehicle as described in subsection (d) of this section, or if a vehicle being repaired by a repair facility or being stored by an insurance company providing insurance to cover damages to the vehicle becomes abandoned, the person removing or storing such motor vehicle shall, within seven calendar days of the day such vehicle became an abandoned motor vehicle, give notice by electronic means as provided by the state through its agencies and authorities in writing, or by sworn statement, on the form prescribed by the commissioner, to the department of revenue with a research fee as fixed by rule or regulation payable to the department of revenue, stating: 
                  (1)  The manufacturer's vehicle identification number; 
                  (2)  The license number; 
                  (3)  The fact that such vehicle is an abandoned motor vehicle; 
                  (4)  The model, year, and make of the vehicle; 
                  (5)  The date the vehicle became an abandoned motor vehicle; 
                  (6)  The date the vehicle was removed; and 
                  (7)  The present location of such vehicle; 
                  and requesting the name and address of all owners, lessors, lessees, security interest holders, and lienholders of such vehicle. If the form submitted to the commissioner is rejected because of inaccurate or missing information, the person removing or storing the vehicle shall resubmit, within seven calendar days of the date of the rejection, a corrected notice form to the commissioner together with an additional research fee as fixed by rule or regulation payable to the department of revenue. Each subsequent corrected notice, if required, shall be submitted with an additional research fee as fixed by rule or regulation payable to the department of revenue. If a person removing or storing the vehicle has knowledge of facts which reasonably indicate that the vehicle is registered or titled in a certain other state, he shall check the motor vehicle records of that other state in the attempt to ascertain the identity of the owner of the vehicle. 
                  (f)  Upon ascertaining the owner of such motor vehicle, the person removing or storing such vehicle shall, within five calendar days, by certified or registered mail or statutory overnight delivery, notify all owners of the vehicle of the location of such vehicle and of the fact that such vehicle is deemed abandoned and shall be disposed of if not redeemed. 
                  (g)  If the identity of the owner of such motor vehicle cannot be ascertained, the person removing or storing such vehicle shall place an advertisement in a newspaper of general circulation in the county where such vehicle was obtained or, if there is no newspaper in such county, shall post such advertisement at the county courthouse in such place where other public notices are posted. Such advertisement shall run in the newspaper once a week for two consecutive weeks or shall remain posted at the courthouse for two consecutive weeks. The advertisement shall contain a complete description of the motor vehicle, its license and manufacturer's vehicle identification numbers, the location from where such vehicle was initially removed, the present location of such vehicle, and the fact that such vehicle is deemed abandoned and shall be disposed of if not redeemed. 
                  (h)  Any person storing a vehicle under the provisions of this section shall notify the department of revenue and the Georgia Bureau of Investigation if the vehicle is recovered, is claimed by the owner, is determined to be stolen, or for any reason is no longer an abandoned motor vehicle. Such notice shall be provided within seven calendar days of such event. 
                  (i)  If vehicle information on the abandoned motor vehicle is not in the files of the department of revenue, the department may require such other information or confirmation as it determines is necessary or appropriate to determine the identity of the vehicle. 
                  (j)  Any person who does not provide the notice and information required by this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction thereof, shall be punished as for a misdemeanor, shall not be entitled to any storage fees, shall not be eligible to contract with or serve on a rotation list providing wrecker services for this city, and shall not be licensed by the city to provide removal of improperly parked cars under O.C.G.A. § 44-1-13. 
                  (k)  Any person who knowingly provides false or misleading information when providing any notice or information as required by this section shall be guilty of a misdemeanor and, upon conviction thereof, shall be punished as for a misdemeanor. 
                  (Prior Code, § 40-11-2) 
                  Sec. 14-23. - When peace officers may remove vehicles from public property; notification requirements. 
                  (a)  Any peace officer who finds a motor vehicle which has been left unattended on a public street, road, or highway or other public property for a period of at least five days shall be authorized to cause such motor vehicle to be removed to a garage or other place of safety, if such peace officer reasonably believes that the person who left such motor vehicle unattended does not intend to return and remove such motor vehicle. 
                  (b)  Any law enforcement officer who finds a motor vehicle which has been left unattended on the state highway system shall be authorized to cause such motor vehicle to be removed immediately to a garage or other place of safety when such motor vehicle poses a threat to public health or safety or to mitigate congestion. Any peace officer who finds a motor vehicle which has been left unattended on a public street, road, or highway or other public property, other than the state highway system, shall be authorized immediately to cause such motor vehicle to be removed immediately to a garage or other place of safety when such motor vehicle poses a threat to public health or safety or to mitigate congestion. 
                  (c)  Any peace officer who, under this section, causes any motor vehicle to be removed to a garage or other place of safety shall be liable for gross negligence only. 
                  (d)  Any peace officer or the law enforcement agency which causes a motor vehicle to be removed to a garage or other place of safety or which is notified of the removal of a motor vehicle from private property shall, within 72 hours from the time of removal or notice and if the owner is unknown, attempt to determine vehicle ownership through official inquiries to the department of revenue vehicle registration and vehicle title files. These inquiries shall be made from authorized criminal justice information system network terminals. 
                  (e)  If the name and address of the last known registered owner of the motor vehicle is obtained from the Georgia Crime Information Center, the peace officer who causes the motor vehicle to be removed shall, within three calendar days, make available to the person removing such motor vehicle the name and address of the last known registered owner of such motor vehicle, the owner of the motor vehicle as recorded on the title of such vehicle, and all security interest holders or lienholders. If such information is not available, the peace officer shall, within three calendar days, notify the person removing or storing such vehicle of such fact. 
                  (f)  Law enforcement agencies shall make record entries in the state criminal justice information system files through authorized criminal justice information system network terminals after an unsuccessful attempt to obtain vehicle ownership information and shall remove the record entries when ownership is determined. 
                  (Prior Code, § 40-11-3) 
                  Sec. 14-24. - Unattended vehicle checks. 
                  (a)  It shall be the duty of any peace officer who discovers a motor vehicle which has been left unattended on a public street, road, or highway or other public property to immediately perform an unattended vehicle check on such motor vehicle, unless there is displayed on such motor vehicle an unattended vehicle check card indicating that another peace officer has already performed such an unattended vehicle check. For the purposes of this section, an unattended vehicle check shall consist of such actions as are reasonably necessary to determine that the unattended vehicle does not contain an injured or incapacitated person and to determine that the unattended vehicle does not pose a threat to public health or safety. 
                  (b)  A peace officer completing an unattended vehicle check shall complete and attach to the vehicle an unattended vehicle check card. Unattended vehicle check cards shall be in such form, and shall be attached to vehicles in such manner, as may be specified by rule or regulation of the department of public safety; and to the extent that sufficient funds are available to the department, the department may distribute such forms free of charge to law enforcement agencies in this state. Unattended vehicle check cards shall be serially numbered; shall be of a distinctive color and shape, so as to be readily visible to passing motorists; and shall contain spaces for the investigating police officer to indicate the location of the vehicle, the date and time of the completion of the unattended vehicle check, and the name of such peace officer's law enforcement agency. A detachable stub, which shall be filed with the investigating peace officer's law enforcement agency, shall bear the same serial number and shall contain the same information, together with the identity of the investigating peace officer and the license plate number and other pertinent identifying information relating to the abandoned vehicle. 
                  (Prior Code, § 40-11-3.1) 
                  Secs. 14-25—14-50. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - ABATEMENT OF NUISANCES 

                  Sec. 14-51. - Purpose. 
                  It is important for a community to appear clean, well-kept, and generally clear of public nuisances, eyesores, and unhealthy conditions. The appearance of a community weighs heavily in the decisions of prospective residents and businesses in locating to a particular area. A clean, safe, and well-kept community can stabilize or increase property values, provide a healthy environment, and make citizens proud of the area in which they live. Accordingly, a community needs a set of regulations to keep the area clean, remove unsightly conditions, and prevent unhealthy and unsafe situations from occurring. It is therefore the purpose and intent of this article to encourage a clean, healthy, and satisfying environment free of nuisances, eyesores, and unhealthy, unsafe, or devaluating conditions. To this end, this article seeks to regulate and protect the health, safety, welfare, values, and aesthetics of properties. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § I) 
                  Sec. 14-52. - Definitions. 
                  The definitions set forth in O.C.G.A. §§ 41-1-1 (nuisances—definition in general) and 41-2-8 (nuisances—abatement of nuisances generally—definition) shall be effective as definitions of the words, terms and phrases used in this chapter. All words, terms and phrases used herein, other than those specifically defined elsewhere in this chapter, shall have the respective meanings ascribed to them in O.C.G.A. §§ 41-1-1 and 41-2-8, and shall have the same scope and effect that the same words, terms and phrases have where used in O.C.G.A. §§ 41-1-1 and 41-2-8. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § II) 
                  Sec. 14-53. - Offense; penalty. 
                  It is hereby declared to be an offense for any person, owner, agent, or tenant to maintain or allow a nuisance to exist. Each day a nuisance is continued shall constitute a separate offense. Upon conviction, unless otherwise provided by state law where no specific penalty is provided therefor, the judge may impose a fine not exceeding $1,000.00 and imprisonment in the city or county jail not to exceed six months, and work on the city streets and public works not exceeding 30 days. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § XII) 
                  Sec. 14-54. - Continued use of other laws and ordinances. 
                  It is the intent of the city council that nothing in this article shall be construed to abrogate or impair the powers of the courts or of any department of the city to enforce any provisions of any local enabling act, Charter, or ordinance or regulation nor to prevent or punish violations thereof; and the powers conferred by this article shall be in addition to and supplemental to the powers conferred by any other law or ordinance, legislation, or regulation. 
                  Sec. 14-55. - Illustrative examples of nuisances. 
                  The following conditions, whether on occupied or unoccupied lands, public or private property, are hereby declared to be and constitute a public nuisance and shall be abated, although this section shall not be construed to be limiting with regard to its enumeration of public nuisances: 
                  (1)  Weeds or grass allowed to grow to a height greater than 12 inches on the average, or any accumulation of dead weeds, grass, or brush that may provide safe harborage for rats, mice, snakes, and/or other vermin. 
                  (2)  Vegetation that obstructs the safe passage or line of sight of motorists or pedestrians at an intersection or driveway connection with a public or private street or alley, or along any street or sidewalk. 
                  (3)  Dead or dying trees or other vegetation which may cause a hazardous situation if they fall. 
                  (4)  Accumulation of rubbish, trash, refuse, junk, construction debris, and other abandoned materials, metals, lumber, or other such items. 
                  (5)  The keeping or maintenance of one or more abandoned vehicles in public view or in a manner inconsistent with this article. 
                  (6)  The carcasses of animals or fowl not disposed of within a reasonable time after death. 
                  (7)  Any building or other structure which is in such a dilapidated condition that it is unfit for human habitation, or kept in such an unsanitary condition that it is a menace to the health of people residing in the vicinity thereof, or presents a fire hazard. 
                  (8)  All noises which may annoy or inhibit others in their enjoyment of the use of their property. 
                  (9)  All disagreeable or obnoxious odors or stenches, as well as the condition, substances or other causes which give rise to the emission or generation of such odors and stenches, including smoke and fires. 
                  (10)  The pollution of any public well, stream, lake, canal, or body of water by sewage, dead animals, creamery, industrial wastes, agricultural wastes, industrial wastes, or other substances. 
                  (11)  Any building, structure, or other place or location where any activity is conducted, performed or maintained in violation of local, state, or federal law. 
                  (12)  Any accumulation of stagnant water. 
                  (13)  Any method of human excretion disposal which does not conform to the provisions of local ordinances, or state or federal law. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § III) 
                  Sec. 14-56. - Nuisance prohibited. 
                  It shall be unlawful for any person, firm, corporation or other entity to cause, permit, maintain, or allow the creation or maintenance of a nuisance, as defined or more specifically described in this article. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § IV) 
                  Sec. 14-57. - Notice to abate. 
                  Whenever a nuisance is found to exist within the jurisdiction of the city, the land use officer shall give written notice to the owner or occupant of the property upon which such a nuisance exists, or upon the person causing or maintaining the nuisance, to abate the nuisance. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § V) 
                  Sec. 14-58. - Contents of notice. 
                  The notice to abate a nuisance issued under the provisions of this article shall contain the following: 
                  (1)  An order to abate the nuisance or to request a hearing within a stated time, which shall be reasonable under the circumstances; 
                  (2)  The location of the nuisance, if the nuisance is stationary; 
                  (3)  A description of what constitutes the nuisance; 
                  (4)  A statement of acts necessary to abate the nuisance; and 
                  (5)  A statement that, if the nuisance is not abated as directed, the city will file an action in magistrate court to abate the nuisance. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § VI) 
                  Sec. 14-59. - Provisions for specific nuisances. 
                  (a)  Animals. No domestic animals, excluding cats, shall be permitted to run at large within the city limits. It shall be unlawful for any domestic animal, excluding cats, to be running at large on the streets or sidewalks of the city, unless said domestic pet is under the control of a leash or chain. It shall be the responsibility of the owner of any domestic animal, excluding cats, to provide and keep their domestic animal within a proper enclosure or structure secured from the ground to a sufficient height so that the animal cannot escape enclosure. Structures for horses, cows, or other livestock shall not be located closer than 100 feet from any property line. All animal enclosures or yards shall at all times be kept in a clean condition to prevent any condition detrimental to the public health of the city. No person shall deposit, or cause to be deposited, the carcass of any dead animal in the streets, roads, alleys, woods, or waters within the city. 
                  (b)  Trees and other vegetation. It shall be unlawful for the owner or occupant of any lot or land lying and abutting on an intersection of two streets or the intersection of a driveway and a street to allow any trees, shrubs, or bushes lying on said lot or land to grow to a height or in a manner which restricts the line of sight, or which threatens safety or restricts passage of motorists or pedestrians within a public right-of-way or sidewalk. 
                  (c)  Noise. It shall be unlawful for any person to create or assist in creating, permit, or continue any unreasonably loud, disturbing, or unnecessary noise in the city. Noise of such a character, intensity, and duration that is detrimental to the reasonable comfort, health, or life of any individual is prohibited. The following acts, among others, are declared to be loud, disturbing, and unnecessary noises that constitute a public nuisance in violation of this article, and which shall be abated: 
                  (1)  The keeping or maintenance of any domestic animal which, due to prolonged or habitual barking, howling, whining, or other noises, causes annoyance to neighboring residents, or interferes with the reasonable use and enjoyment of the premises occupied by such residents, is hereby declared to be a public nuisance and shall be abated as provided in this article. 
                  (2)  The sounding of any bell, horn, whistle, mechanical device operated by compressed air, or signal device while not in motion, except as a danger signal, for an unnecessary and unreasonable period of time. 
                  (3)  The use of any siren, other than police, fire, or emergency vehicle. 
                  (4)  The use or operation of any musical instrument, radio, loudspeaker, or sound-amplifying device so loud as to disturb persons in the vicinity thereof. 
                  (5)  The erection, excavation, demolition, alteration, or repair of any building or structure in the vicinity of residential dwellings between the hours of 10:00 p.m. and 7:00 a.m., except in the case of urgent necessity in the interest of public safety, and then only with a permit from the land use officer. 
                  (6)  The creation of excessive noise on any street adjacent to any school, institution of learning, court, or religious congregation while the same are in session, or within 150 feet of a hospital, which unreasonably interferes with the working of such institution. 
                  (7)  The shouting or crying of peddlers, vendors, or residents which disturbs the peace and quiet of a residential area. 
                  (8)  Then unnecessary creation of loud or excessive noise in connection with unloading or loading vehicles or merchandise. 
                  (9)  The use of any vehicle that is in a state of disrepair as to create loud or unnecessary grinding, rattling, backfiring, or other noise. 
                  Any of these enumerated nuisances, if violated, would be a misdemeanor and could be prosecuted in the local court just as the violation of any other ordinance. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § VII) 
                  Sec. 14-60. - Jurisdiction. 
                  By contract, the magistrate court of the county shall have full jurisdiction to try issues concerning the existence and abatement of nuisances existing or occurring within the limits of the city. The magistrate court, its judges, and personnel have the full authority to act as municipal court judges and personnel. The magistrate court shall also have jurisdiction, in cases of conviction, to punish persons found guilty of maintaining a nuisance. The maximum punishment imposed for violation of this chapter shall not exceed $1,000.00 or six months' imprisonment, or both, unless some other general law authorizes greater punishment. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § VIII) 
                  Sec. 14-61. - Citation; service of process. 
                  (a)  Contents of a citation. 
                  (1)  The citation shall name as respondent the person alleged responsible for maintenance of the public nuisance. Where the alleged public nuisance involves a condition or activity existing upon private property, the owner of such property and any interested party shall also be named as respondents. 
                  (2)  For purposes of this article, the term "owner of private property" means the holder of the title in fee simple and holder of every mortgage, deed to secure debt, lien or judgment, as recorded in the title records of the county. The term "interested party" means an interested party as defined in O.C.G.A. § 48-4-77 and persons in possession of said property and premises. 
                  (3)  The citation shall plead with specificity all facts necessary to show the existence and location of the alleged public nuisance and its duration or frequency or reoccurrence. 
                  (4)  The citation shall contain the specific date and time of the hearing before the magistrate court of the county, which hearing shall occur at least 14 days after issuance of the citation. 
                  (b)  Service of a citation. 
                  (1)  A copy of the citation shall be served in one of the following ways: 
                  a.  Personal service upon each respondent who is a resident of the city. Service shall be perfected at least ten days prior to the date of the hearing. If personal service cannot be perfected, service of the citation shall be made by utilizing the method set out in subsection (b)(1)b of this section. 
                  b.  Parties residing outside of the city shall be served by certified mail or statutory overnight delivery, return receipt requested, mailed at least 14 days prior to the date of the hearing. 
                  c.  For persons whose mailing address is unknown, a notice of the date, time, and place of the hearing shall be published in the newspaper in which the sheriff's advertisements appear in the county once a week for two consecutive weeks prior to the hearing. 
                  d.  In the event a party is a minor, estate, an incompetent person or person laboring under disabilities, the guardian or personal representative of such person shall be served. If such person has no guardian or personal representative, service shall be perfected upon the probate judge of the county of residence, who shall appoint a guardian ad litem for such person. 
                  (2)  Personal service under this article may be perfected by any code enforcement or law enforcement officer of the city, or any citizen over the age of 18 years specially appointed by the judge of the magistrate court of the county. 
                  (3)  Proof of service shall be filed with the clerk of the magistrate court of the county prior to the date of the hearing. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § IX) 
                  Sec. 14-62. - Trial procedure; appeal. 
                  (a)  Trial procedure. 
                  (1)  The burden at trial shall be upon the city to prove the existence of a public nuisance by a preponderance of the evidence. A written finding by any governmental officer, code enforcement officer, public health officer, fire inspector, life safety inspector or building inspector, based upon physical inspection, that real property or a structure or condition existing upon real property is a health, safety, or environmental hazard shall constitute prima facie evidence that such property, structure, or condition constitutes a public nuisance. 
                  (2)  In addition to any other penalties available, upon finding that a nuisance does exist, the court shall issue an order to the violator and/or the owner, the agent in control of or tenant in possession of the property stating that a nuisance has been found to exist and that the nuisance must be abated within so many hours or days as the judge may deem reasonable, having considered the nature of the nuisance and its effect on the public. The magistrate court is empowered to enforce its judgments by contempt. 
                  (b)  Appeal. Any final judgment entered by the magistrate court under this article is subject to review by certiorari in the superior court of the county, upon application filed within 30 days of the service of said order upon the respondents. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § X) 
                  Sec. 14-63. - Abatement by the city. 
                  (a)  In any case where the violator and/or owner, agent or tenant fails to abate the nuisance within the time specified by the court, or where the violator and/or owner, agent, or tenant cannot be served with notice, or where the nature of the nuisance is such, in the opinion of the judge, that it must be immediately abated, the judge may issue an order to the chief of police, fire chief, or code enforcement official directing the nuisance to be abated. The chief of police, fire chief, or code enforcement official, in such case, shall keep a record of the expenses and costs of abating the nuisance, and the costs shall be billed against the violator and/or owner, agent, or tenant for collection as for city revenues. The total expense, including administrative costs, incurred by the city in abating public nuisances under this article shall constitute a lien upon the property upon which the nuisance was abated. 
                  (b)  When a nuisance is of such a magnitude or degree that city equipment and personnel cannot safely or completely abate it, the city may contract with a private contractor to abate the nuisance on the city's behalf. 
                  (c)  City officers and employees, or any city contractor operating under subsection (b) of this section, shall have the right of entry upon real property and shall be immune from prosecution, civil or criminal, for trespass upon real property while in the discharge of their duties in removing or abating any public nuisance under this article. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2007, § XI) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="16">
               <head>Chapter 16 - OFFENSES[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Limitation on home rule powers of municipal corporations with respect to duplication of state criminal offenses, Ga. Const. art. III, § VI, ¶ IV; O.C.G.A. § 36-35-6(a)(2); Criminal Code of Georgia, O.C.G.A. § 16-1-1 et seq. 

                  Sec. 16-1. - Disorderly conduct. 
                  It shall be unlawful for any person or persons in the city to act in a violent or tumultuous manner toward another whereby: 
                  (1)  Any person is placed in fear of the safety of his life, limb or health; 
                  (2)  The property of any person is placed in danger of being damaged or destroyed; 
                  (3)  To cause, provoke or engage in any fight, brawl or riotous conduct to endanger the life, limb, health or property of another; 
                  (4)  To assemble or congregate with others for the purpose of, or with the intent to engage in, gaming; 
                  (5)  To be in or about any place where gaming or the use of illegal drugs is practiced, allowed or tolerated, for the purpose of consumption of said illegal drugs, narcotics or alcoholic beverages; 
                  (6)  To direct fighting words toward another, that is, words which by their very nature tend to incite a breach of the peace; 
                  (7)  To interfere, by acts of physical obstruction, with another's pursuit of lawful occupation; 
                  (8)  To congregate with others in or on any public way so as to halt the flow of vehicular or pedestrian traffic, and to fail to clear that public way after being ordered to do so by an officer of the city or other lawful authority; 
                  (9)  To intend to disrupt by actions which substantially impair the ordinary conduct of activities or a meeting occurring at any house of worship, home for the elderly or property which is federally funded, state subsidized or owned by private nonprofit or private citizen, or any lawful meeting, gathering, or procession of others both inside/outside and/or surrounding properties around those previously described; or 
                  (10)  To throw bottles, paper, cans, glass, sticks, stones, or any other debris on any public property. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-108) 
                  State Law reference— Fighting in a public place, O.C.G.A. § 16-11-32; use of "fighting words," obscene and vulgar or profane language, etc., O.C.G.A. § 16-11-39. 
                  Sec. 16-2. - Discharging firearms, air guns, etc. 
                  (a)  It shall be unlawful for any person in the city to discharge any gun, pistol, or other firearm within 350 yards of any street, alley, or building, or at any point upon the land of another person without the express consent of the owner or occupant thereof. 
                  (b)  This section shall not be construed to prohibit any officer of the law from discharging a firearm in the performance of his duty, nor to prohibit any citizen from discharging a firearm when lawfully defending person or property. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-109) 
                  Sec. 16-3. - Injuring public property. 
                  It shall be unlawful for any person to destroy, injure or deface in any manner whatsoever any public building or property of the city. Any violation of this section shall be punished as prescribed in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-111) 
                  State Law reference— Unlawful to intentionally injure or destroy equipment or other apparatus of city used for public services, O.C.G.A. § 16-7-25. 
                  Sec. 16-4. - Disturbing public worship. 
                  If any person whosoever shall disturb any congregation who are assembled together at any church or public place of worship to perform divine service, or shall cause any disturbance thereabout or therein, he, shall, for such offense, be subject to punishment as prescribed in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-112) 
                  Sec. 16-5. - Power of mayor to close public resort. 
                  The mayor shall have power to shut up any place of public resort when the maintenance of order and public safety or tranquility, or public decency may, in his judgment, require it. 
                  (Prior Code, § 31-113) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="18">
               <head>Chapter 18 - REVENUE AND FINANCE </head>
               <p>                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Secs. 18-1—18-18. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - TAXATION[1] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Taxation power of municipal and county governments, Ga. Const. art. IX, § IV, ¶ I(a) and (b)(2); ad valorem taxation of property, O.C.G.A. § 48-5-1 et seq.; municipal power of ad valorem taxation to provide for financial assistance to its development authority, O.C.G.A. § 48-5-350 et seq. 

                  Sec. 18-19. - Ad valorem tax. 
                  (a)  Rate of levy. There is hereby set and levied to meet the ordinary current expenses of the city an annual ad valorem tax as set by council from time to time upon all real and personal property within the city, and there is hereby set and levied for the payment of principal and interest on all property. 
                  (b)  Appeal of assessment. Any taxpayer may appeal from an assessment by the county board of tax assessors to the county board of equalization as to matters of taxability, uniformity of assessment, and value, and the taxpayer or the county board of tax assessors may appeal to the superior court of the county in which the property lies from a decision of the county board of equalization. All such appeals shall be made in the manner provided under state law. 
                  (c)  When taxes due and payable. Ad valorem taxes shall become due on October 1 each year and shall be deemed delinquent if not paid on or before December 20 thereafter. Tax bills showing the assessed valuations, amount of taxes due, tax due dates, and information as to delinquency dates and penalties shall be sent to all taxpayers at least 30 days prior to the due date, but failure to send a tax bill shall not invalidate any tax. Delinquent taxes shall bear interest at nine percent per annum from due date. 
                  (d)  Failure to pay tax. The city shall forthwith issue an execution against any person who has defaulted in the payment of any ad valorem tax to be paid. The execution thus issued shall be a lien on all the property of such person, both real and personal, and shall be placed in the hands of the city officer responsible for collection by levy and sale. 
                  (e)  Against whom charged. Taxes are to be charged against the owner of the property, if known, or against the specific property itself if the owner is not known. Life tenants and those who enjoy the use of the property are chargeable with the tax thereon. 
                  (f)  Exempted property. The following property shall be exempt from ad valorem taxation: 
                  (1)  All public property; 
                  (2)  All places of religious worship and places of burial; 
                  (3)  All buildings used as a college, university or other seminary of learning. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-101; Ord. of 8-4-2008, § 1) 
                  Sec. 18-20. - Gross direct premiums tax. 
                  (a)  Rate of levy. There is hereby set and levied upon each company authorized to write life, accident and sickness insurance and which is doing business within the municipal corporate limits a tax equal to one percent of the annual gross direct premiums received during the preceding calendar year from policies insuring persons residing within the corporate limits of the municipality. The term "gross direct premiums," as used in this section, shall have the same meaning as that used in O.C.G.A. § 33-8-4. The tax levied by this section is in addition to any license fee imposed by this Code. 
                  (b)  Due date and required report. The gross direct premiums tax shall be due and payable on February 15 of each calendar year and payment shall be accompanied by a report showing the names and addresses of the agents representing the insurance company in the city, the classes of insurance written and the premiums received for each class. Payments shall be deemed delinquent if not received within 45 days from the due date. 
                  (c)  Confidentiality of information. All reports required to be filed under this section shall be confidential and the information contained therein shall be used solely by the officers of the city responsible for the administration of this section. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-104; Ord. of 10-7-2007, § A) 
                  Note— A certified copy of the pertinent parts of all ordinances which impose a gross direct premiums tax of this kind must be filed with the Insurance Commissioner of the State of Georgia within 45 days after their enactment as a condition of their validity and enforceability. 
                  Sec. 18-21. - Municipal tax sales. 
                  (a)  Time, place and manner of sale. The time, place and manner of the sale of property, both real and personal, for taxes due this municipality shall be the same as that provided by law for sheriffs' sales for state and county taxes. 
                  (b)  Sale by parcels. When not impracticable, all property sold for municipal taxes shall be so offered for sale that the smallest amount that will bring the amount of taxes and costs shall alone be sold. 
                  (c)  Purchase by city. The city treasurer shall attend all sales of property for taxes due the city, and in the event no one person bids for the property put up to be sold as much as the tax due thereon, the treasurer shall place a bid for such property for the city and, if the bid is accepted, take custody of the deed for the city. No property so purchased by the city shall ever be sold by the city except at a public sale thereof to the highest bidder. 
                  (d)  Redemption of property sold for taxes. Any person whose property is sold in obedience to an execution issued for the collection of municipal taxes shall have such rights of redemption of said property as are set forth under state law and any other provisions of law not inconsistent therewith. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-106) 
                  Secs. 18-22—18-45. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - MUNICIPAL BONDS[2] 

                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (2) --- 
                  State Law reference— Municipal authority to create sinking fund for proceeds from bond tax, Ga. Const. 1983, art. IX, § V, ¶ VI; limitation on local debt, Ga. Const. 1983, art. IX, § V; revenue bonds, Ga. Const. 1983, art. IX, § VI; municipal bonds, O.C.G.A. §§ 36-38-1 et seq. and 36-82-1 et seq. 

                  Sec. 18-46. - Compliance to state rules and regulations; preliminary review of finance committee; record maintenance. 
                  (a)  Adoption of state rules and regulations. The rules, regulations and provisions contained in O.C.G.A. §§ 36-38-1 et seq. and 36-82-1 et seq. relating to debts of municipalities, counties and other political subdivisions are hereby adopted as the rules, regulations and provisions governing the issuance of general obligation and revenue bonds by this municipality. 
                  (b)  Preliminary review by finance committee. Prior to any issue of bonds by the city, the proposal for such issue shall be referred to the standing finance committee, which committee shall give careful consideration to the proposal and submit a recommendation to the council for approval or disapproval, with applicable reasons therefor. 
                  (c)  Records to be kept. A complete description of each bond issued by the city shall be kept by the city clerk in a suitable book, which book shall be open to public inspection. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-201) 
                  Sec. 18-47. - Registration. 
                  (a)  Application; required information. Any holder of a bond issued by the city may register such bond as to principal and interest or as to principal only by making written application for such registration to the city clerk and presenting the bond desired to be registered. Each application shall state: 
                  (1)  The number of bonds presented; 
                  (2)  Of what issue; 
                  (3)  The date; 
                  (4)  The amount; 
                  (5)  When due; and 
                  (6)  To what extent the bonds are to be registered; 
                  and each application shall be signed by the applicant who, if holding the bonds in any capacity other than for himself, shall sign the application in the name of the party for whose benefit he holds the bonds, state the capacity in which he signs and attach proof of such capacity. 
                  (b)  Bond register. A bond register shall be kept on file in the office of the city clerk in which, upon written application and presentation of the bond by the holder thereof as hereinabove provided, shall be entered a description of each bond so presented, which description shall state: 
                  (1)  The bond number; 
                  (2)  The nature of the issue; 
                  (3)  The face amount; 
                  (4)  The date issued; 
                  (5)  The date of maturity; 
                  (6)  The rate and due dates of interest; 
                  (7)  Whether the bond is registered as to principal and interest or as to principal only; 
                  (8)  The name and mailing address of the bond holder; 
                  (9)  The name of the person registering the bond; and 
                  (10)  The capacity in which such person is registering the bond. 
                  All bonds registered in compliance with this section shall be non-negotiable to the extent registered. 
                  (c)  Statement of registration and form. Upon registration of any bonds as hereinabove provided, the city clerk shall stamp, print or write upon each bond so registered a statement of the registration in substantially the following form, inserting in the blanks the matter applicable to each transaction: 
                  Registered by ____________ . Non-negotiable. Principal [and interest] to be paid only to ____________ located at ____________ or to his legal representative located at ____________ . This ____________ day of ____________ , 20 ____________ . 

                   
                  (d)  Procedure for transfer after registration. In order to transfer any bond which may have been registered under the provisions of this section, the holder thereof shall present the same to the city clerk and shall authorize such transfer, in writing, giving the name of the transferee, the number of the bond, of what issue and the date of issue and maturity. Such authority shall be signed and acknowledged in the presence of a notary public or some other officer authorized by law to administer oaths and such notary public or other officer shall certify, in writing and under seal of his office, that such authority was signed and acknowledged in his presence. In addition to giving such written authority, the holder shall enter a statement of the transfer on the face of each bond, properly dated and signed. Thereupon the city clerk shall enter the transfer of each bond opposite the original entry of registration in the bond register, giving the name of the transferee and date of the transfer, and shall enter the same on each bond over his official signature. The transferee may thereafter, in the manner herein prescribed, also transfer such bond. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-202) 
                  Sec. 18-48. - Disposition of bonds and coupons. 
                  Whenever the city clerk pays any bond or coupon of the city he shall forthwith stamp, print or write upon such bond or coupon the word "PAID" and shall notify the standing finance. 
                  (Prior Code, § 4-203) 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="20">
               <head>Chapter 20 - TRAFFIC CONTROL[1] </head>
               <p>
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Cities are authorized to exercise power over parking facilities and traffic control devices, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III(a)(4) and (11); power of local authorities with respect to uniform rules of the road, O.C.G.A. § 40-6-370 et seq.; jurisdiction of municipal courts over misdemeanor traffic offenses, O.C.G.A. § 40-13-21(a). 

                  Sec. 20-1. - Uniform Rules of the Road adopted. 
                  (a)  Adoption by reference. Pursuant to O.C.G.A. §§ 40-6-372 through 40-6-376, the provisions of O.C.G.A. §§ 40-6-1 through 40-6-395, excluding O.C.G.A. §§ 40-6-393 and 40-6-394, known as the Uniform Rules of the Road, are hereby adopted as and for the traffic regulations of this municipality, with like effect as if recited in full herein. 
                  (b)  Penalties. Unless another penalty is expressly provided by law, any person convicted of a violation of any provision of this section shall be punished according to the general penalties described in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 11-101) 
                  Sec. 20-2. - Temporary traffic regulations. 
                  In cases where traffic upon the roads of the city may become congested upon occasions of parades, at theaters and other public assemblages where large numbers of vehicles are assembled, a law enforcement officer may make temporary rules directing and regulating the traffic in these congested districts, and any person who, after being warned of the temporary traffic regulations, shall violate regulations, shall be liable therefor as for other violations of this chapter. 
                  Sec. 20-3. - Traffic, speed, zones; signs and traffic control devices. 
                  (a)  The city council will designate a person who shall be authorized to erect and maintain by appropriate traffic control signs, markings and devices: 
                  (1)  Crosswalks at intersections where there is particular danger to pedestrians crossing the roadway. 
                  (2)  Other safety zones for pedestrians. 
                  (3)  Traffic lanes. 
                  (4)  Speed, parking, truck or other traffic control zones. 
                  (5)  Stop, yield, one-way and other directional devices. 
                  (6)  Any other sign, marking, device or zone necessary for orderly and safe conditions on the roads and streets of the city. 
                  (b)  All traffic control signs, signals, devices and markings shall conform to specifications in the Manual on Uniform Traffic Control Devices adopted by the state transportation board. All signs and signals required under this chapter for a particular purpose shall, so far as practicable, be uniform as to type and location throughout the city. All traffic control devices so erected and not inconsistent with the provisions of state law or this article shall be official traffic control devices of the city. 
                  (c)  The city clerk shall keep and maintain an accurate official list setting out all traffic zones, markings, signs and other traffic control devices. The list, and any changes thereto, shall be approved by the city council and the list shall be known as the official traffic control list of the city. An official copy of this list shall be kept in the office of the city clerk; shall be available to the public; and copies certified by the city clerk shall be admissible in court as proof of the location of any traffic zone, marking, sign or other traffic control device. 
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter" n="22">
               <head>Chapter 22 - UTILITIES[1] </head>
               <p>                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  State Law reference— Home rule powers of municipality to regulate and provide sewage collection and disposal systems, stormwater systems, and water treatment systems, Ga. Const. art. IX, § II, ¶ III(a)(6), (7); Georgia Water Quality Control Act, O.C.G.A. § 12-5-20 et seq.; power of municipality to grant franchises or make contracts with public utilities, O.C.G.A. § 36-34-2(7); municipalities authorized to acquire, construct, operate and maintain water and sewage systems, O.C.G.A. § 36-34-5; adoption of ordinances, rules and regulations relating to payment for street improvements and construction of water, gas and sewer connections; payment of costs of connections, O.C.G.A. § 36-39-7. 

                  ARTICLE I. - IN GENERAL 

                  Sec. 22-1. - Municipal water works. 
                  The municipal water works shall be under the immediate control and supervision of the director of public works, who shall perform all acts that may be necessary for the prudent, efficient and economical management and protection of said water works, subject to the approval and confirmation of the mayor and council. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-101) 
                  Sec. 22-2. - Inspections. 
                  The director of public works, or his designated assistant or consultant, may enter the premises of any water taker at any reasonable time to examine the condition of the water pipes, meters and fixtures. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-102) 
                  Sec. 22-3. - Application for water. 
                  Application for the use of water shall be made to the city clerk by the owner or agent of the property to be benefited, designating the location of the property and stating the purpose for which the water may be required. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-103) 
                  Sec. 22-4. - Tapping charge. 
                  (a)  Upon the application for a new tap and service connection by any consumers within the corporate limits of the municipality, the applicant shall pay to the city clerk a tapping charge to cover the cost of the fittings, installation of the tap of the municipality, and 50 feet of pipe. Any length of service pipe in excess of 50 feet will be charged at cost. Businesses will pay the cost for a large meter. The amount of the tapping charge shall be as established by the city council, from time to time. 
                  (b)  The municipality shall own and maintain the water line from the main to the curb box to the premises served. 
                  (c)  All work upon the service line shall be performed by a licensed plumber. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-104; Prior Ord., § 20-104) 
                  Sec. 22-5. - Size of service tap. 
                  No service tap shall be more than three-fourths inch in diameter, provided that the director of public works may grant special permission for larger taps where the water supply and service facilities are sufficient to permit such taps. Where a larger tap is permitted, the director shall fix the tapping charge therefor. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-105) 
                  Sec. 22-6. - Water meters. 
                  Each building or structure using city water shall have a water meter installed by the city, which will be installed in a curb box. All such meters are the property of the city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-106) 
                  Sec. 22-7. - Service line regulations. 
                  No more than one residential structure shall be permitted to use a water service line. All service lines shall be installed at a depth at least 40 inches below the surface of the ground. Each service line shall contain a stop and waste cock where the water may be turned off. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-107) 
                  Sec. 22-8. - Water waste prohibition. 
                  Consumers shall prevent unnecessary waste of water and keep all water outlets closed when not in actual use. Hydrants, urinals, water closets, bathtubs and other fixtures must not be left running for any purpose other than the use for which they were intended. When any such waste occurs, the water service may be terminated. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-108) 
                  Sec. 22-9. - Sprinkling restrictions. 
                  In case of water shortage or scarcity, the mayor and council may by resolution place any restrictions upon the use of water for irrigation or sprinkling purposes which such body deems necessary. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-109) 
                  Sec. 22-10. - Use during fire alarms. 
                  During all fire alarms the use by persons other than municipal firefighters of hoses and other apparatuses maintaining a constant flow of water is absolutely forbidden. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-110) 
                  Sec. 22-11. - Water and sewer rates. 
                  The water and sewer rates shall be as established by the city council, from time to time. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-111) 
                  Sec. 22-12. - Water bills. 
                  Water meters shall be read at the end of each month, or as nearly as possible, and bills shall be mailed on the first day of each succeeding month. All water bills shall be due on or before the tenth day of the month following the reading of the meter, and if not paid by the end of the tenth, a penalty of ten percent will be charged. If the bill is not paid by the 15th of the same month, a cutoff fee shall be added thereto and paid by the water user. The amount of the cutoff fee shall be as established by the city council from time to time. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-112) 
                  Sec. 22-13. - Discontinuance of service. 
                  If any bill for water as provided in section 22-12 is not paid by the 15th of the month, the water service shall be cut off and in no case shall it be re-instated to the same property until the delinquencies shall have been paid in full. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-113) 
                  Sec. 22-14. - Charges for turning water on. 
                  (a)  If the water supply to any premises is turned off for failure of payment of the bill, a charge shall be made for turning the water back on. The amount of the charge shall be as established by the city council, from time to time. 
                  (b)  Before the water is turned back on, the original bill, plus all penalties, must be paid to the city. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-114; Prior Ord., § 20-114(intro. ¶), (A)) 
                  Sec. 22-15. - Illegal use of water. 
                  After a water meter is placed in service, regardless of ownership or other conditions unless under emergencies such as water leaks, no one shall move, tamper with, or cut off or cut on same; neither shall anyone bypass water around any meter under any condition. All private lines must have an individual cutoff. Any violation of any of this rule shall be considered sufficient evidence and reason for discontinuing service to the violator and any person found guilty of the violation of said rule shall be punished according to the general penalties described in section 1-9. 
                  (Prior Code, § 20-114; Prior Ord., § 20-114(B)) 
                  Secs. 22-16—22-33. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE II. - WELLHEAD PROTECTION 

                  Sec. 22-34. - Short title and purpose. 
                  (a)  This article is known as the "Wellhead Protection Ordinance." 
                  (b)  The purpose of this article is to ensure the provision of a safe and sanitary drinking water supply for the city by the establishment of wellhead protection zones surrounding the wellheads/springs for all wells/springs which are the supply sources for the city water system and by the designation and regulation of property uses and conditions which may be maintained within such zones. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 1) 
                  Sec. 22-35. - Definitions. 
                  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Hazardous waste or material means any waste or material which, because of its quantity, concentration or physical, chemical or infectious characteristics, may: 
                  (1)  Cause or significantly contribute to an increase in mortality or an increase in the serious irreversible or incapacitating reversible illness; 
                  (2)  Pose a substantial present or potential hazard to human health or to the environment when improperly treated, stored, transported, disposed of or otherwise managed. 
                  Sanitary landfill means a disposal site where solid wastes, including putrescible wastes, or hazardous wastes are disposed of on land by placing earth cover thereon. 
                  Wellhead means the upper terminal of a well, including adapters, ports, seals, valves and other attachments. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 2) 
                  Sec. 22-36. - Establishment of wellhead protection zone. 
                  There is hereby established a use district known as a wellhead protection zone, identified and described as all the area within a circle the center of any city water supply wellhead, the radius of which is 100 feet. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 3) 
                  Sec. 22-37. - Permitted uses. 
                  The following uses shall be permitted within wellhead protection zones: 
                  (1)  Any use permitted within existing agricultural or single-family residential districts, except that the minimum residential lot size for a lot any portion of which lies within the wellhead protection zone shall not be less than one acre; and 
                  (2)  Any other open land use where any building located on property is incidental and accessory to the primary open land use. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 4) 
                  Sec. 22-38. - Prohibited uses. 
                  The following uses of conditions shall be and are hereby prohibited within wellhead protection zones, whether or not such use or condition may otherwise be ordinarily included as a part of a use permitted under section 22-37: 
                  (1)  Surface use or storage of hazardous material, expressly including commercial use of agricultural pesticides; 
                  (2)  Septic tanks or drain fields appurtenant thereto; 
                  (3)  Impervious surfaces other than roofs or buildings and streets, and driveways and walks serving buildings permitted under section 22-37; 
                  (4)  Sanitary landfills; 
                  (5)  Hazardous waste disposal sites; 
                  (6)  Storm water infiltration basins; 
                  (7)  Underground storage tanks; 
                  (8)  Sanitary sewer lines within 150 feet of a wellhead. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 5) 
                  Sec. 22-39. - Administration. 
                  The policies and procedures for administration of any wellhead protection zone established under this article, including without limitation those applicable to nonconforming uses, exceptions, enforcement and penalties, shall be the same as provided in the existing zoning ordinance for the city, as the same is presently enacted or may from time to time be amended. 
                  (Ord. of 10-1-2001, § 6) 
                  Secs. 22-40—22-65. - Reserved. 
                  ARTICLE III. - OUTDOOR WATERING 

                  Sec. 22-66. - Definitions. 
                  The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in this section, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning: 
                  Address means the house number (a numeric or alphanumeric designation) that, together with the street name, describes a physical location of a specific property. 
                  Even-numbered address means a house number ending with the number 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, or no house number. 
                  Odd-numbered address means a house number ending in 1, 3, 5, 7, or 9. 
                  Declared drought response level means one of four levels of drought that can be declared, based on the severity of drought conditions, with one being the least severe and four being the most severe. 
                  (Ord. of 10-4-2004, § 1) 
                  Sec. 22-67. - Penalties and violations. 
                  Any person found in violation of this article shall be fined as follows: 
                  (1)  First offense: A written warning. 
                  (2)  Second offense: $50.00 fine. 
                  (3)  Third offense: $100.00 fine. 
                  (4)  Each additional offense will result in a $100.00 fine. 
                  (Ord. of 10-4-2004, § 4) 
                  Sec. 22-68. - Applicability of rule. 
                  These rules apply to all water customers of the city as permitted by the state environmental protection division for water withdrawal. 
                  (1)  Permitted outdoor water use during non-drought periods. Outdoor water use during non-drought periods other than exempted activities. 
                  a.  Odd-numbered address outdoor water use is allowed Tuesdays, Thursdays and Sundays. 
                  b.  Even-numbered address outdoor water use is allowed Mondays, Wednesdays, and Saturdays. 
                  (2)  Drought response levels; period and use limitations. Outdoor water use schedule during the declared drought response levels will be declared by the director of the environmental protection division. Periods other than exempted activities shall occur only as follows: 
                  a.  Declared water drought response level one. Outdoor water use may occur only as follows: 
                  1.  Scheduled days for odd-numbered address: Tuesdays, Thursdays and Sundays. 
                  2.  Scheduled days for even-numbered address: Mondays, Wednesdays and Saturdays. 
                  3.  Use of hydrants for any use other than firefighting, public health, safety, or flushing is prohibited. 
                  b.  Declared drought response level two. Outdoor water use may occur on scheduled days within the hours of 12:00 midnight and 10:00 a.m. 
                  1.  Scheduled days for odd-numbered address: Tuesdays, Thursdays and Sundays. 
                  2.  Scheduled days for even-numbered address: Mondays, Wednesdays, and Saturdays. 
                  3.  The following uses are prohibited: 
                  (i)  Using hydrants for any purpose other than firefighting, public health, safety or flushing. 
                  (ii)  Washing hard surfaces, such as: streets, gutters, sidewalks, and driveways except when necessary for public health and safety. 
                  c.  Declared drought response level three. Outdoor water use may occur on the scheduled day between the hours of 12:00 midnight and 10:00 a.m. 
                  1.  Scheduled day for odd-numbered address is Sunday. 
                  2.  Scheduled day for even-numbered address is Saturday. 
                  3.  The following uses are prohibited: 
                  (i)  Using hydrants for any purpose other than firefighting, public health, safety or flushing. 
                  (ii)  Washing hard surfaces, such as streets, gutters, sidewalks, driveways, except when necessary for public health and safety. 
                  (iii)  Filling installed swimming pools except when necessary for health care or structure integrity. 
                  (iv)  Washing vehicles, such as cars, boats, trailers, motorbikes, airplanes, golf carts. 
                  (v)  Washing buildings or structures except for immediate for protection. 
                  (vi)  Noncommercial fundraisers, such as car washes. 
                  (vii)  Using water for ornamental purposes, such as fountains, reflecting pools, and waterfalls except when necessary to support aquatic life. 
                  d.  Declared drought response level four. No outdoor water use is allowed, other than for activities or as the EPD director may order. 
                  (Ord. of 10-4-2004, § 2) 
                  Sec. 22-69. - Exemptions. 
                  (a)  This rule shall not apply to the following outdoor water uses: 
                  (1)  Capture and reuse of cooling system condensation or stormwater in compliance with applicable local ordinances. 
                  (2)  Reuse of gray water in compliance with applicable local ordinances. 
                  (b)  The following established landscape water uses are exempt from the outdoor water use schedules of this rule: Irrigation of personal food gardens. 
                  (c)  Newly (in place less than 30 days) installed landscapes are subject to the following: 
                  (1)  Irrigation of newly installed landscapes is allowed any day of the week, but during allowed hours for the drought response level in effect, for a period of 30 days following installation. No watering is allowed during drought response level four. 
                  (2)  For new landscapes installed by certified or licensed professional, commercial exemptions apply. 
                  (Ord. of 10-4-2004, § 3) 
                  Appendix A - MUNICIPAL FEES[1] 

                   
                  Footnotes: 
                  --- (1) --- 
                  Editor's note— Printed herein are the municipal fees for the City of Ellenton, Georgia. The fees were adopted by the Mayor and City Council through individual ordinances. Obvious misspellings and punctuation errors have been corrected without notation. For stylistic purposes, headings and catchlines have been made uniform and the same system of capitalization, citation to state statutes, and expression of numbers in text as appears in the Code of Ordinances has been used. Additions made for purposes of clarity are indicated by brackets. For the purpose of the following tables, the designation "TBD" means that the fees are to be determined by ordinance or resolution of the Mayor and City Council of the City of Ellenton, Georgia. 

                  CODE COMPARATIVE TABLE 
                  PRIOR CODE 
                  This table gives the location within this Code of those sections of the Prior Code of the city, as updated through March 7, 2011, which are included herein. Sections of the Prior Code, as updated, not listed herein have been omitted as repealed, superseded, obsolete or not of a general and permanent nature. For the location of ordinances adopted subsequent thereto, see the table immediately following this table. 

                   
                  CODE COMPARATIVE TABLE 
                  ORDINANCES 
                  This table gives the location within this Code of those ordinances which are included herein. Ordinances not listed herein have been omitted as repealed, superseded or not of a general and permanent nature. 

                   

                   
                  STATE LAW REFERENCE TABLE 
                  This table shows the location within this Charter and Code, either in the text or notes following the text, of references to Georgia state law. 

                   
</p>
</div>
         </div>
     </body>
</text>
</TEI>